{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This case overturned another whose plaintiff was indicted for robbery in Maryland, called\nBetts v. Brady. Abe Fortas [FORR-tuss] argued on behalf of this case’s plaintiff before the\nSupreme Court. An expanded public defender system was set up as a result of this case’s\nholding. For 10 points, name this landmark case whose plaintiff broke into a pool hall, which\nheld that the Sixth Amendment required the provision of counsel for indigent plaintiffs.",
      "answer": "Gideon v. Wainwright"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man is the namesake of the smallest and lightest nuclear weapons unit designed by the\nUnited States. After getting his start in the Lawrence County militia, this man was elected to the\nTennessee General Assembly and then to the House of Representatives, where he opposed Indian\nRemoval. With James Bowie and William Travis, he died as a volunteer at the Alamo. For 10\npoints, name this American known as the “King of the Wild Frontier,” who wore a coonskin cap.",
      "answer": [
        "Davy Crockett",
        "Crockett",
        "David Stern Crockett"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this king’s cabinet ministers was wounded at Putney Heath after a duel. He was\nadvised early in life by Lord Bute and married Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Strelitz [STRAYELits]. After this man refused to support Catholic Emancipation, his prime minister Pitt the\nYounger resigned. Earlier in his reign, Pitt the Elder helped this king defeat France and Lord\nNorth passed the Intolerable Acts. For 10 points, name this mad king who ruled during the\nAmerican Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "King George III",
        "George III"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Phil Ochs’ [oaks] song “Outside of a Small Circle of Friends” was inspired by this person’s\nfate. Social scientists have used this person’s story as an example of the diffusion of\nresponsibility and the bystander effect. After this Queens resident was stabbed by Winston\nMoseley, she was the subject of the New York Times article “Thirty-Seven Who Saw Murder\nDidn’t Call the Police.” For 10 points, name this New York City resident who was murdered in\nplain view of many unhelpful witnesses.",
      "answer": [
        "Kitty Genovese",
        "Genovese",
        "Catherine Susan Genovese"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man served as the chair of the Senate Judiciary Committee during the Robert Bork hearings. After after sharing confidential details from a conversation with President Erdogan [AIR-doh-ahn] in October 2014, he was forced to officially apologize to Turkey. He was forced to drop out of the 1988 Presidential election after plagiarizing a Neil Kinnock speech. The Onion created parody “Diamond” and “Uncle” versions of this current politician. For 10 points, name this gaffe-prone current Vice President of the United States.",
      "answer": "Joe Biden"
    },
    {
      "question": "This movement led to the founding of the American Tract Society and involved meetings at Gasper River and Cane Ridge. Influential figures in this movement included Barton Stone and Lyman Beecher. Charles Finney described regions of New York influenced by this movement as “burned-over districts.” For 10 points, identify this period of religious revival which ultimately gave rise to the emergence of Baptism and Methodism, a movement lasting from the early to mid-nineteenth century.",
      "answer": "Second Great Awakening"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, Robert Barnwell Rhett led the Bluffton movement, and the Fort Hill Address was delivered in this state. Events in this state inspired the coining of the phrase \"liberty and union, now and forever\" during the Webster-Hayne debate. The Force Bill allowed the president to send troops to this state. The Tariff of Abominations was attacked in an \"Exposition and Protest\" named for this state. For 10 points, name this state where the Nullification Crisis was sparked by John C. Calhoun.",
      "answer": "South Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "Participants in this uprising gathered at Braddock’s Field and Parkinson's Ferry. It began when members of a local “Democratic Society” burned John Neville’s home. This rebellion was sparked by an excise tax levied by Alexander Hamilton, and put down by a militia led by Virginia governor “Light-Horse Harry” Lee and President George Washington. For 10 points, name this 1794 rebellion in Pennsylvania named for an alcoholic beverage.",
      "answer": "Whiskey Rebellion"
    },
    {
      "question": "This individual earned a “production E” in a song by Redd Evans and John Jacob Loeb. This figure inspired a National Historical Park in Richmond, California that is home to the SS Red Oak Victory. Geraldine Doyle was the inspiration for one depiction of this character by Westinghouse employee J. Howard Miller, which depicts her with a red bandana and flexed bicep, saying “We Can Do It!” for ten points, name this icon that encouraged American women to take factory jobs during World War II.",
      "answer": "Rosie the Riveter"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to its invocation, this ruling was “sincerely believed to be an act of justice warranted by the Constitution.” This ruling came with one hundred days’ notice and specifically exempted New Orleans and the land that was to become West Virginia. The victory at Antietam led to its issuing, which only immediately took effect in territory controlled by Union forces. For ten points, name this executive order issued on January 1, 1863 by President Lincoln, which freed over three million slaves in the South.",
      "answer": "Emancipation Proclamation"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man appointed Edward Douglass White as Chief Justice. He used the “Saxbe fix” to appoint Philander Knox, who carried out a program of promoting corporate interests in foreign countries, or “dollar diplomacy.” In his re-election campaign, he only won Utah and Vermont, partially because his predecessor split from the Republican Party to run on the Bull Moose ticket. For ten points, name this President who succeeded Theodore Roosevelt, then served as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.",
      "answer": "William Howard Taft"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man called one of his works a “proper Vehicle for conveying Instruction among the common People;” that work was published under the name Saunders. He detailed his fleeing from Boston to New York and his writing of the Silence Dogood essays in an autobiography published in 1791. The aphorism “early to bed, early to rise/makes a man healthy, wealthy, and wise” is attributed to, for ten points, what author of Poor Richard’s Almanac, an American founding father?",
      "answer": "Ben Franklin"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first person prosecuted under this legislation was Vermont congressman Matthew Lyon, and another of its targets was the Philadelphia Aurora. The Kentucky and Virginia Resolutions declared these bills unconstituional, and three of them were repealed when the Democratic-Republican Party came to power in 1800. For ten points, name this quartet of laws signed by John Adams in 1798 that enabled the government to expel foreigners and punish anti-government speech.",
      "answer": "Alien and Sedition Acts"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was precipitated by armed unrest led by the CGL during the “two red years.” U.S. Ambassador Richard Child gave tacit American approval of this event before it began, shortly after news of Gabriele d’Annunzio’s similarly planned event. Luigi Facta resigned in the wake of this event, whose leader remained in Milan in case it failed. For ten points, name this 1922 demonstration by tens of thousands of Blackshirts, the supporters of Benito Mussolini.",
      "answer": "March on Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "This treaty’s first version resolved claims regarding Don Jose de Garay’s grant to develop a route across the Isthmus of Tehuantapec. This treaty, which tried to resolve William Lane’s claim to the Mesilla Valley, was approved to obtain land for a transcontinental railroad south of the Gila River. President Pierce signed, for ten points, what 1853 treaty in which America paid 10 million dollars to Mexico for a strip of land in southern New Mexico and Arizona?",
      "answer": "Gadsden Purchase"
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this family took power after overthrowing Salah Jadid. That man’s supporters violently suppressed his brother’s forces in Latakia in 1999, and in 1982, that man’s military carried out the Hama massacre to suppress the Muslim Brotherhood. Another member of this family is opposed by the al-Nusra front in a civil war that emerged from the Arab Spring. For ten points, give this name shared by Hafez and his son, Bashar, who have both served as President of Syria.",
      "answer": "al-Assad"
    },
    {
      "question": "With his brother Manuel, this man set up a “wet line” to prevent immigration and campaigned against the bracero program. He joined forces with the Filipino-dominated AWOC in a campaign where longshoremen refused to load grapes from Delano, California. With Dolores Huerta, he co-founded an organization whose slogan was “Si, se puede,” [pway-day] or “Yes we can.” The United Farm Workers were led by, for ten points, what Mexican-American labor activist?",
      "answer": "Cesar Estrada Chavez"
    },
    {
      "question": "This work ends by saying “instead of gazing at each other with suspicious or doubtful curiosity, let each of us hold out [...] the hearty hand of friendship,” before calling “Let the names of Whig and Tory be extinct.” Benajmin Rush edited this work, whose final section calculates the value of the British navy, noting America’s natural resources give it the potential to rival it. The absurdity of an island ruling over a continent is noted by, for ten points, what 1776 pro-revolution pamphlet by Thomas Paine?",
      "answer": "Common Sense"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1996, “Bob Dole” and “Clinton” were used interchangeably in one of these documents. One of these documents referenced Dieppe the day before it was raided, and these documents accidentally used codenames learned from American soldiers in the leadup to D-Day. For aesthetic purposes, these documents usually feature radial symmetry and no “cheater” black squares.” for ten points, name these word games, edited by Will Shortz for the New York Times, which feature clues to fill in words going across and down.",
      "answer": "crossword puzzles"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ruling in this case overruled an appelate ruling that found that the “Constitution is silent on the subject,” thereby protecting the implied power of Congress to carry out constitutional laws by “necessary and proper” means. Chief Justice John Marshall noted that “the power to tax involves the power to destroy” in his unanimous decision in, for ten points, what 1819 Supreme Court case lodged against the Bank of the United States by the state of Maryland?",
      "answer": "McCulloch v. Maryland"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the writing of the Articles of Confederation, New Hampshire and New York blocked the adoption of this measure. Roger Sherman and James Wilson re-introduced this measure at the Constitutional Convention, preserving language about the exclusion of “Indians not taxed.” The Thirteenth Amendment nullified this clause of the Constitution, which was used to balance Congressional representation between the North and South. For ten points, name this compromise regarding the value of the American slave population, which used a fractional formula.",
      "answer": "Three-Fifths Compromise"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man documented his youthful trek from Indiana to Florida in his A Thousand-Mile Walk To The Gulf. This man opposed a common ally, Gifford Pinchot, over the construction of a dam in the Hetch Hetchy Valley in the aftermath of the San Francisco fire. In 1903, he invited Theodore Roosevelt on a camping trip that inspired the President to transfer Yosemite to the U.S. government. For ten points, name this American conservationist, the founder of the Sierra Club.",
      "answer": "John Muir"
    },
    {
      "question": "Esther Peterson opposed this legislation in favor of “specific bills for specific ills.” Support for it was removed from the Republican platform in 1980. Its proponents cite Coleman v. Miller as precedent allowing a “three-state strategy” for its adoption. A campaign against this legislation was led by the Eagle Forum’s Phyllis Schlafly, who worried it would discriminate against housewives. Alice Paul first proposed, for ten points, what non-ratified constitutional amendment that would outlaw discrimination based on sex?",
      "answer": "Equal Rights Amendment or ERA"
    },
    {
      "question": "Future governor George McDuffie led a boycott in response to this act. It was unusually proposed by Southern Democrats, who planned it to be voted down by New England Whigs opposed to its impact on wool imports. This protectionist act was expected to be repealed with the defeat of John Quincy Adams. The South Carolina Exposition and Protest was written by John Calhoun in opposition to, for ten points, what 1828 tariff, the highest ever in American history, which triggered the Nullification Crisis four years later?",
      "answer": [
        "Tariff of Abominations",
        "Tarif f of 1828 before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This speaker noted “I want [slavery] root and branch destroyed” in an 1867 speech to the American Equal Rights Association that ended with a singing of “We are going home.” This speaker asked “Where did your Christ come from?”, noting “Man had nothing to do with Him!” in another speech; in that speech, she proclaimed “I have plowed and planted, [...] and no man could head me!” for ten points, name this 19th century activist and orator, a former slave who repeated the question “Ain’t I a Woman?” in her most famous speech.",
      "answer": "Sojourner Truth"
    },
    {
      "question": "Abraham Lincoln responded to one of this man’s letters by explaining “If I could save the Union without freeing any slave, I would do it,” a few weeks before issuing the Emancipation Proclamation. This author of the “Prayer of Twenty Millions” died a few weeks after he lost a Presidential election, so his 66 electoral votes were split to other candidates. The phrase “Go west, young man!” was popularized by, for ten points, what editor of the New York Tribune, who lost to Ulysses Grant in the 1872 Presidential election?",
      "answer": "Horace Greeley"
    },
    {
      "question": "In June 2016, this figure lined up a “sweet summer gig” installing above-ground swimming pools. He once asked a colleague to get him “some of those real throwing stars” while on a diplomatic trip to Japan; in December 2016, this man forged that colleague’s signature on an executive order naming December “Dokken History Month.” For ten points, name this politician, nicknamed “Diamond Joe” according to the last eight years of Onion articles about the hijinks of America’s “President of Vice.”",
      "answer": "”Diamond” Joe Biden"
    },
    {
      "question": "Legislation to undertake this project was introduced to Congress by Zadock Pratt. Thomas Durant helped finance this project, though scandal arose when Credit Mobilier attempted to overcharge a company for its construction. This project was completed when Leland Stanford drove in the golden spike at Promontory, linking the Union Pacific and Central Pacific lines. For ten points, name this man-made transportation route that connected the Western and Eastern United States.",
      "answer": "Transcontinental Railroad"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group regularly held meetings at the Menger Hotel Bar of San Antonio. After the Battle of Las Guasimas, the doctor Leonard Wood ceased to be the leader of this group, which presented a president with a bronze miniature of Remington’s Bronco Buster. In their most famous engagement, this group charged up the Kettle and San Juan Hills in Cuba. For ten points, name this volunteer cavalry unit that was led by Teddy Roosevelt during the Spanish American War.",
      "answer": "Rough Riders or the 1st United States Volunteer Cavalry Regiment, prompting on partial answers thereof"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s wounding at the Breymann redoubt is commemorated by the “Boot Monument” in New York. This man was forced to flee on the Vulture after he was implicated by a set of secret plans that were found with John Andre. After Horatio Gates took the credit for this man’s successes at the Battle of Saratoga, this man plotted to surrender West Point to the British. For ten points, name this treasonous American Revolutionary War general.",
      "answer": "Benedict Arnold"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization was criticized for being unable to control the Orange Riots. Charles Murphy tried to reform this organization, which supported Al Smith for President in 1928. Jimmy Hines was unable to stop this organization’s defeat by Fiorello LaGuardia. A leader of this organization was targeted by Samuel Tilden and depicted with a bag of money for a head by Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this Democratic political machine in New York City that was dominated by Boss Tweed.",
      "answer": [
        "Tammany Hall or the Society of St. Tammany",
        "the Sons of St. Tammany",
        "the Columbian Order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This President won the presidency thanks to James Birney’s Liberty Party sapping his opponent’s anti-slavery support in states like New York. He died just three months after leaving office, a record for shortest Presidential retirement. This man is the only President to have once been Speaker of the House. Supporters of this “dark horse” winner chanted “54-40 or fight!” in endorsing his policy of expansionism. For ten points, name this U.S. President during the Mexican-American War.",
      "answer": "James Knox Polk"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man claimed that there were 400 neatly marked graves because one soldier slept. As part of Operation Fortitude, this man was assigned command of the fictitious First U.S Army Group. This general led the breakout from Normandy and the relief of the garrison of Bastogne during the Battle of the Bulge, but was relieved of command after two slapping incidents in North Africa and Sicily. For ten points, name this aggressive commander of the American Third Army during World War II.",
      "answer": "George S. Patton Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. A group advocating this action modeled its activities on the Bryce Group in Britain. Edward House drafted a plan calling for this action, which relied upon the work of the Phillimore Committee. William Borah and Henry Cabot Lodge opposed this action, citing their disapproval of Article Ten of a certain proposed covenant. For ten points, name this action, never taken despite the efforts of President Woodrow Wilson, which doomed a certain international body to irrelevance.",
      "answer": [
        "the United States joining the League of Nations",
        "equivalent descriptions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader’s father launched the 1970 Corrective Revolution. A revolution against this leader began after a boy was arrested for political graffiti in Daraa. To stop the Southern Front and Army of Conquest, this Ba’athist leader allegedly ordered his air force to use barrel bombs in an ongoing civil war. This leader brokered a ceasefire with Vladimir Putin shortly after recapturing Aleppo in December 2016. For ten points, name the current president of Syria.",
      "answer": "Bashar al-Assad"
    },
    {
      "question": "A member of this family was targeted by the Soviet-backed Yanan Faction in the “Second Arduous March.” This family is honored on the “Day of the Sun.” A member of this family instituted the “Juche” [joo-chay] policy of self-reliance and took the title of “Eternal President,” while another member of this family allegedly ordered a hacking of Sony after he was unfavorably depicted in The Interview. Il-Sung, Jong-Il, and Jong-Un are members of, for ten points, what family that rules North Korea?",
      "answer": "Kim family"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote that “If [...] bad men can be got rid of only by killing, then the killing must be done,” leading some to claim he was an accessory to the murder of William McKinley. This man’s ranch on an “Enchanted Hill” in San Simeon, California, includes a massive castle open to public tours. This mogul inspired Charles Foster Kane in Orson Welles’ 1941 film Citizen Kane. For ten points, name this early 20th century American newspaper publisher whose New York Journal rivaled the New York World of Joseph Pulitzer.",
      "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. During this event, Captain Arthur Slatter helped kill a charging foe “just thirteen paces from where we stood.” This event was undertaken with hundreds of guides, including the leader’s son Kermit, and it provided the Smithsonian Institution with exhibits for its new Museum of Natural History. Eleven black rhinoceros, 17 lions, and thousands of birds were among the victims of, for ten points, what year-long expedition, begun in 1909 shortly after its leader declined to run for re-election, in which a former U.S. President shot and collected thousands of animals?",
      "answer": [
        "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt’s 1909-10 African safari",
        "any description of Roosevelt going on a hunt in Africa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An introductory quote made by this man titles a book chronicling his activities, I Heard You Paint Houses. This man rose to power by organizing support for Dave Beck. A prison sentence that this man received for illegally distributing pension funds was commuted by Richard Nixon in 1971. After eating at the Machus Red Fox restaurant outside of Detroit, this man vanished mysteriously in 1975. For ten points, name this thirteen-year president of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters.",
      "answer": "James “Jimmy” Hoffa"
    },
    {
      "question": "The action at the center of this case was first defined in Stromberg v. California, while the ruling of Bethel v. Fraser was held to be distinct from this case. Abe Fortas’s majority opinion in this case held that the action in question did not cause a disruption and that its participants did not lose their rights “at the schoolhouse gate.” This case dealt with five children who, in 1965, wore black armbands to protest the Vietnam War in Iowa. For ten points, name this Supreme Court case that protected students’ right to free speech.",
      "answer": "Tinker v. Des Moines Independent Community School District"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man worked to quell the revolt of Francis Rakoczi while working as president of the Imperial War Council. This man commissioned the Belvedere Palace after his victory at the Battle of Zenta, which led to the Treaty of Karlowitz and the Ottoman withdrawal from Central Europe. In 1704, this general joined up with the Duke of Marlborough to defeat the Duc de Tallard at the Battle of Blenheim. For ten points, name this Habsburg commander during the War of the Spanish Succession.",
      "answer": "Prince Eugene of Savoy"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man said “I am very sorry it is taking me so long to die” after attempting suicide during his arrest. The Imperial Rule Assistance Political Association was created by this man, who suggested not executing the pilots of the Doolittle Raid in fear of American retaliation. After being arrested, this man was given a new pair of dentures which had the phrase “remember Pearl Harbor” written in Morse Code. For ten points, name this politician who served as Japan’s Prime Minister from 1941 to 1944.",
      "answer": "Hideki Tojo"
    },
    {
      "question": "The first site to establish this industry in the U.S. was the Beverly Manufactory. A man nicknamed “the traitor” memorized the designs of British equipment used in this industry and recreated it in the U.S.; that man was Samuel Slater. The Waltham-Lowell system placed young girls in this industry in boardinghouses in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. The product of Eli Whitney’s gin was used in, for ten points, what industry that converted cotton into shirts and pants?",
      "answer": [
        "textile industry",
        "clothing industry",
        "garment industry",
        "cotton industry before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this war, a group of German mercenaries under French leadership called Lauzun’s Legion saw action at White Plains. A German officer in this war ordered the establishment of separate toilets and kitchens and educated troops about marching orders during a brutal winter encampment. A group of Hessian soldiers in this war were defeated in a surprise attack the day after Christmas in the Battle of Trenton. For ten points, name this war in which Baron von Steuben drilled troops at Valley Forge, Pennsylvania, during the winter of 1777.",
      "answer": "American Revolutionary War"
    },
    {
      "question": "Debate over this action was triggered by a plan to give Lorenzo Thomas a job. Prominent advocates for this action included John Bingham and an ailing Thaddeus Stevens. Edmund Ross earned a chapter of John F. Kennedy’s Profiles in Courage for casting the deciding vote against this action, which was a response to a violation of the Tenure of Office Act. The attempted firing of Edwin Stanton triggered, for ten points, what Congressional event that sought to remove Abraham Lincoln’s successor from office?",
      "answer": "impeaching Andrew Johnson"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these objects designed by Robert Moses was partially built using wartime rubble from England. Andrew Jackson vetoed a bill that would have created one of these structures named for Maysville, which would have been part of the Cumberland System. After his positive experience with the Autobahn, Dwight Eisenhower ordered the construction of, for ten points, what type of transportation infrastructure whose American examples include I-95 and Route 66?",
      "answer": [
        "roads",
        "specific answers, like highways",
        "turnpikes, etc.",
        "FDR Drive",
        "Maysville Road",
        "Cumberland Road",
        "Interstate system, Interstate Highway system, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "William Mead and this man were accused of “speaking in Gracechurch Street,” but when the jury refused to a provide a guilty verdict, the judge starved the jury for two days before imprisoning them, too. This man wrote No Cross, No Crown while imprisoned in the Tower of London for allegedly denying the Trinity. In order to pay a debt to this man’s father, Charles II made this man the largest non-royal landowner in the world. For ten points, name this Quaker who founded an American colony governed from Philadelphia.",
      "answer": "William Penn"
    },
    {
      "question": "Because Richard Lawrence believed that he held this position, he attempted to assassinate president Andrew Jackson and was thereafter confined to an insane asylum. FDR held a publicized hot dog dinner with the holder of this position in June, 1939. John Dickinson was the primary author of a document addressed to the holder of this position, which urged him to reconsider tax provisions over the American colonies. For ten points, the Olive Branch Petition was addressed to the holder of what position, George III?",
      "answer": [
        "King of England",
        "equivalents such as the British monarch"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1886, Herman Presser and his group Lehr und Wehr Verein cited this amendment to challenge an Illinois law. This amendment’s jurisprudence favored the collective rights interpretation established in US v. Miller until the Roberts Court recently applied the individual rights doctrine in DC v. Heller and McDonald v. Chicago. For ten points, name this amendment that mentions a “well-regulated militia” and guarantees the right to bear arms.",
      "answer": "2nd Amendment to the U.S. Constitution"
    },
    {
      "question": "This foodstuff was first made from a plant called teosinte [tay-oh-sin-tay]. In 1885, Charles Cretors invented a machine to make this foodstuff, which he displayed at the 1893 Chicago World’s Fair. During World War II, sugar rations led to the tripling in consumption of this good, which the Redenbacher family started selling during the Great Depression. For ten points, name this food, a sweetened variety of which is found with peanuts in Cracker Jack, and which is the highest-selling food in American movie theaters.",
      "answer": "popcorn"
    },
    {
      "question": "This President introduced the ISF solidarity tax on wealth after running on the 110 Propositions platform. This man announced his country would give grants, not loans, to African nations in a speech at La Baule describing a “south wind” of democratization. This President, whose last meal was the illegal Ortolan bird, sunk the Greenpeace ship Rainbow Warrior and was forced to “cohabitate” with his rival Jacques Chirac. For ten points, name this first socialist President of France.",
      "answer": "Franc¸ois Mitterand"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s brother killed Spencer Pettis after Pettis criticized this man’s work. Louis McLane was reassigned to the State Department for refusing to remove funds from an organization run by this man. After Langdon Cheves resigned, James Monroe replaced him with this man. In a political cartoon, this man is shown wearing a top hat as part of a many-headed monster being slain by the seventh President of the United States. Andrew Jackson was challenged by, for ten points, what final president of the Second Bank of the United States?",
      "answer": "Nicholas Biddle"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman mentored Marie Zakrzewska, who helped grow her dispensary at Tompkins Square into an institution that merged with New York Presbyterian in 2013. After receiving backlash from the United States Sanitary Commission, this woman helped establish the Women’s Central Relief Association during the Civil War. Charles Lee bowed to this woman in 1849 while granting her a degree earned after 150 students unanimously agreed to accept her admittance at Geneva College. For ten points, name this first woman to obtain an American medical degree.",
      "answer": "Elizabeth Blackwell"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this war, the USS Essex and USS Essex Junior were captured off the coast of Chile. One side in this war ambushed a convoy at Henderson Bay which led to the Second Battle of Sacket’s Harbor. In an 1882 book, Theodore Roosevelt says the American navy gave the populace confidence in the face of an ineffectual army during this war. Fort Niagara was captured in, for ten points, what war in which Oliver Hazard Perry won the Battle of Lake Erie?",
      "answer": "War of 1812"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group established October 16th as the Day of Atonement, on which men would refrain from engaging in activity harmful to their families. The beliefs of this group, collected in the book The Supreme Wisdom, tell of how Yakub created a race of evil people on the island of Patmos. A leader of this group, Louis Farrakhan, organized the Million Man March on Washington in 1995. For ten points, name this African-American religious group that adopted traditions of the prophet Muhammad.",
      "answer": [
        "Nation of Islam",
        "NOI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1910, this state’s constitution almost incorporated the Digges Amendment to disenfranchise African-Americans. Albert Ritchie governed this state for nearly 15 years in the early 20th century. With John McDuffie, a Senator from this state co-sponsored Filipino independence. This state’s flagship law school was integrated after Murray v. Pearson was argued by Thurgood Marshall, a native of this state. H.L. Mencken worked for a newspaper in this state when he covered the Scopes Trial in Tennessee. For ten points, name this state where Congressmen like Millard Tydings represented the city of Baltimore.",
      "answer": "Maryland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was led by the “Fighting Parson” John Elder, and another member, Lazarus Stewart, was killed in the Wyoming Massacre. John Penn placed a bounty on this group, who attacked victims in protective custody at Lancaster. Benjamin Franklin forced this group to disperse at Germantown. This group committed the Conestoga Massacre against the Susquehannock Indians. For ten points, name this group of Pennsylvanian vigilantes who acted against Native Americans in the wake of Pontiac’s Rebellion.",
      "answer": "Paxton Boys"
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist led a task force that outlined plans for a permanent lunar base and a manned mission to Mars in a strategic initiative regarding “America’s Future in Space.” Donald Kutyna was leaked internal documents by this figure, who sat with him on the Rogers Commission. This astronaut was insultingly asked “Will the flight affect your reproductive organs?” before a mission aboard the Challenger. For ten points, name this astronaut, the first American woman in space.",
      "answer": "Sally Ride"
    },
    {
      "question": "A student of this university named Sadie Tanner Mossell Alexander was the first African American woman to receive a Ph.D. A machine known as the “Giant Brain” was created at this university to calculate artillery firing tables; that early computer was ENIAC. The oldest medical school created in America is this university’s Perelman School, and it is also home to the first school of business, which is named after Joseph Wharton. For ten points, name this university founded by Benjamin Franklin in Philadelphia.",
      "answer": [
        "University of Pennsylvania",
        "UPenn"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Peter Greyson partially destroyed a copy of one of these documents by pouring red paint mixed with glue on it. The 7/50 formula concerns changes to one of these documents in Canada. The Indian version of this document is the longest in the world, and the American version includes a Revenue Clause, noting that spending bills begin in the House of Representatives. The Articles of Confederation were replaced with, for ten points, what type of governing law?",
      "answer": [
        "constitution",
        "additional information, like Canada’s Constitution"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A precursor to this object used by FDR was called Sacred Cow. Mark Tillman once controlled this object, which one man was forced to use after giving a speech at an elementary school in Sarasota, Florida. Golden livery in this object was designed with the help of Jackie Kennedy, who was present when Lyndon Johnson was sworn in aboard it. John F. Kennedy’s body was taken to Washington D.C. on, for ten points, what aircraft that transports the President?",
      "answer": "Air Force One"
    },
    {
      "question": "Concerns that she was too young for marriage may have prompted one member of this family to break off her engagement to the playwright Royall Tyler; that woman from this family was nicknamed “Nabby.” Another member of this family served as minister to the Netherlands during the Washington administration, helping John Jay negotiate his namesake treaty. That man from this family traveled with his father on a diplomatic journey to France in 1778 and was born in Quincy, Massachusetts. For ten points, name this early American family that included the second and sixth presidents.",
      "answer": "Adams family"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician issued a namesake Moratorium in an attempt to give Germany more time to catch up on reparation payments. In another postwar role, this man organized Belgian food relief efforts. The Smoot-Hawley Tariff was signed by this man, who promised “a chicken in every pot” during his presidential campaign. As unemployment peaked, shantytowns became named for, for ten points, what president who led the US into the Great Depression?",
      "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
    },
    {
      "question": "This practice is often said to have begun in America with a Northampton County court case between Anthony Johnson and Robert Parker. John Punch is sometimes seen as the first American subject of this practice, which the Code Noir, requiring Catholic education, established in New France. A series of Virginia codes in 1705 defined this state as applying to anyone not belonging to a Christian nation. For ten points, name this practice that began with indentured servants of African descent.",
      "answer": [
        "slavery",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Following his 1978 death, this man’s wife Muriel took over his Senate seat. At a 1948 national convention, this man stated that “The time has arrived for the Democratic Party to [...] walk forth- rightfully into the bright sunshine of human rights.” This man succeeded Eugene McCarthy as senator from Minnesota after being nominated for President at a convention where riots broke out in Chicago. For ten points, name this Democratic politician who lost the 1968 election to Richard Nixon.",
      "answer": "Hubert Horatio Humphrey, Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "The evacuation of Walnut Hills was overseen by Andrew Ellicott after the signing of this treaty. The cessation of a line between the Pearl and Perdido Rivers was agreed upon as part of this treaty. Ownership rights over the Tombigbee and Natchez districts were discussed as part of this treaty, which resolved the West Florida Controversy and gave the United States navigation rights of the Mississippi River. A prominent Federalist negotiated, for ten points, what 1795 treaty between the U.S. and Spain?",
      "answer": [
        "Pinckney’s Treaty",
        "Treaty of San Lorenzo",
        "Treaty of Madrid",
        "Treaty of Friendship, Limits, and Navigation Between Spain and the United States"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was forced to step down after the Rua Tonelero incident, in which an assassination attempt was launched on rival Carlos Lacerda. The Integralists were suppressed by this man after they advocated for fascism. This man declared he would “leave life to enter history” before shooting himself with a pistol. During his tenure, he established Petrobras and administered the South American Estado Novo period. For ten points, name this president of Brazil in the 1940s.",
      "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these events sparked unrest in Chicago that became the Battle of the Viaduct on Halsted Street. One of these events which began in Martinsburg, Virginia led to the Shamokin Uprising and many other smaller actions. One of these events in 1922 occurred in response to wage cuts that notably did not affect the “Big Four” unions in its industry. A “Great” one of these events in 1877 lasted for 45 days before being put down by federal troops across the country; that event targeted the B&O. For ten points, name this type of labor action, common in late 19th century America as transportation barons exploited workers.",
      "answer": "railroad strikes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This doctrine was used in conjunction with the concept of “bad tendency” in the conviction of a man who published a “Left Wing Manifesto.” Since Brandenburg v. Ohio, this doctrine has been replaced by the idea of “imminent lawless action.” This doctrine was introduced in an opinion that described the evils of “falsely shouting fire in a theatre.” Schenck v. U.S. originated, for ten points, what four-word doctrine by which justice Oliver Wendell Holmes described situations in which free speech was not protected by the Constitution?",
      "answer": "clear and present danger"
    },
    {
      "question": "Scholars have conjectured possible relatives of this man based on the fact that his last name means “deer” in Narragansett. This man, who used the alias Michael Johnson, had been a slave of Deacon William Brown. This man’s body lay in state in Faneuil Hall after men under Thomas Preston opened fire on a crowd that had been throwing snowballs. For ten points, name this Native American and African American patriot, the first person killed in the Boston Massacre.",
      "answer": "Crispus Attucks"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler broke with the Soviet Union and opened up his economy to the West under his policy of Infitah. Though he had planned the surprise attack Operation Badr, this leader was assassinated by Islamic Jihad because of his diplomatic efforts with Menachem Begin, with whom he shared the 1978 Nobel Peace Prize. For ten points, name this successor of Gamal Abdel Nasser as President of Egypt who signed the Camp David Accords with Israel.",
      "answer": "Muhammad Anwar el-Sadat"
    },
    {
      "question": "Causes of this war included the execution of the crew of the Virginius. During this war, hundreds of soldiers died thanks to Russell Alger’s cut-rate rations in the Embalmed Beef scandal. Frederic Remington was told to furnish pictures so that William Randolph Hearst could furnish this war, which was supported by yellow journalism. The sinking of the USS Maine helped trigger, for ten points, what war between the US and a European falling power in 1898?",
      "answer": "Spanish-American War"
    },
    {
      "question": "Investigations of this event included the Hoey Report, which was criticized by the U.S. Navy’s Crittenden Report. A slur by Everett Dirksen inspired the popular name for this event, in which President Eisenhower’s Executive Order 10450 led to numerous firings of “subversives” from the State Department. Roy Cohn was accused of being closeted during, for ten points, what 1950s “scare” regarding homosexuals in the US Government?",
      "answer": [
        "Lavender Scare",
        "Lavender Lads, the slur by Dirksen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Louise Stanley led this department’s Bureau of Home Economics, which produced the Aunt Sammy radio program from 1926 to 1944 and the first ever braille cookbook. Under Abraham Lincoln, Isaac Newton was the first head of what would become this department. The SNAP aid program is administered by this department, which was led by former Iowa governor Tom Vilsack in the Obama administration. For ten points, name this Cabinet department that runs the Farm Service Agency.",
      "answer": [
        "United States Department of Agriculture",
        "USDA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man and John Stott co-founded the Lausanne Movement. This deliverer of the “My Hope America” speech said “We have to stand in the middle in order to preach to all people” as a reason why he refused to join Jerry Falwell’s Moral Majority. Hour of Decision was broadcast in the early 1950s by this man, who went on hundreds of namesake Christianizing crusades. For ten points, name this celebrity Southern Baptist evangelist who advised twelve US Presidents.",
      "answer": "William Franklin “Billy” Graham Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "This character uses the informal insult “Casse toi” [cah-say TWAH] in his opening appearance before declaring himself “the best.” This figure, who announces “I’m takin’ this horse by the reins, makin’ Redcoats redder with bloodstains,” tries to rhyme “anarchy” with “monarchy” shortly before Hercules Mulligan and John Laurens give their verses in the song “My Shot.” Daveed Diggs portrayed Thomas Jefferson and this man in the original Broadway cast of Hamilton. For ten points, name this marquis who aided the colonies during the American Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette",
        "either",
        "both underlined names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader oversaw the abolition of privy purses by passing the 26th constitutional amendment in 1971. This leader’s son Sanjay advocated for a mass sterilization program that this leader implemented during a period known as the Emergency. This leader was assassinated in retaliation for launching a military assault on Amritsar’s Golden Temple as part of Operation Blue Star. For ten points, name this daughter of Jawarhalal Nehru, the first female Prime Minister of India.",
      "answer": "Indira Gandhi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Quakers and Anglicans fought over this state’s governorship in Cary’s Rebellion. This modern-day state was home to the Albemarle Settlements, and its Halifax Resolves were the first official resolution calling for American independence. This state and a southern neighbor were granted to Robert Heath as Cape Fear in 1629. The Battle of Guilford Court House took place in, for ten points, what Mid-Atlantic state with capital at Raleigh?",
      "answer": "North Carolina"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a speech at Boston’s Home Market Club, this man noted that the U.S. needs to “put an end to false economics which lure humanity to utter chaos” in a speech that opens by blaming a “fever [that] has rendered men irrational.” This man argued that “America’s present need is not heroics, but healing; not nostrums, but” the slogan of his presidential campaign, in which he beat Leonard Wood on the tenth ballot at the nominating convention and beat James Cox in the election. For ten points, name this US president who promised a “Return to Normalcy” after World War I.",
      "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
    },
    {
      "question": "A black-and-white photo of a 1913 rally is juxtaposed with a photo of this event that was digitally altered by the National Archives for an exhibit celebrating the centennial of the 19th Amendment; the alterations included blurring part of the phrase “God hates Trump.” Vanessa Wruble co-led this event, whose attendance dwarfed that of a ceremony held the previous day. For ten points, name this January 21, 2017 rally, the largest single-day protest in American history, against the policies of Donald Trump.",
      "answer": [
        "2017 Women’s March",
        "2017 Women’s March on Washington",
        "descriptive answers that include the words Women’s March"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gained the support of Century magazine editor Robert Johnson after the two of them took a trip to Tuolumne [too-AWL-um-nee] Meadows. This man worked with Henry Senger to form a resistance group to the Hetch Hetchy Dam. A famous photograph of this man shows him standing atop Glacier Point with Theodore Roosevelt. In 1906, this man successfully campaigned for Yosemite to be put under federal control. For ten points, name this Scottish-American naturalist who founded the Sierra Club.",
      "answer": "John Muir"
    },
    {
      "question": "A leader of this number became the final emperor of the Angelos dynasty and co-ruled during the second reign of his father, Isaac II Angelos. Lysippos may have sculpted a work consisting of this many bronze horses that were looted by Venetians and installed at the Basilica of Saint Mark; the Venetians acquired those horses during the 1204 sack of Constantinople, which ended the crusade of this number. For ten points, give this number of the crusade that was led by Enrico Dandolo.",
      "answer": [
        "four",
        "Alexios IV Angelos",
        "4 bronze horses of Saint Mark",
        "4th Crusade"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Walter Jarboe operated a gang of mercenaries in this state, kidnapping Yuki natives. Despite banning African American slavery, this state allowed for “apprenticing” of Native Americans in a form of slavery documented by John Ross Browne. In this state, Sheriff William Dixon massacred more than 150 Wintu people in the Bridge Gulch massacre. Slave labor in this state built New Helvetia, a fort owned by John Sutter. For ten points, name this state where many Native Americans were killed during an 1849 gold rush.",
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s daughter Mary played Kristin Shepard, who turned out to be the one who shot J.R. in the famous cliffhanger of the soap opera Dallas. This man, whose last TV appearance was on a Christmas special singing a duet with David Bowie, co-starred in a film series beginning with Road to Singapore with Bob Hope. A recording of this man was used in Operation Frequent Wind to signal the American evacuation from Saigon. For ten points, name this American actor and singer of “White Christmas.”",
      "answer": "Harold “Bing” Crosby"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Great Law of Peace was first recorded using symbols made of this material, and a Two Row Treaty made of this material was signed in 1613 with the Dutch. The Hiawatha Belt was made of this material, which was made from quahog [ko-hog] shells collected from Long Island Sound or Narragansett Bay. In Iroquois Culture, this material represented a person’s authority and was often kept on a belt. For ten points, name this type of shell bead used in barter between Native Americans and early colonists.",
      "answer": "wampum"
    },
    {
      "question": "The preface to this work critiques the historians Arnold and Creasy for slighting the topic of this work as a factor in Hannibal’s loss to Rome. This work, which was published by the president of a war college in Newport, advocates the creation of “resting-places” for “coal and repair” as “one of the first duties of government.” William McKinley’s management of the Spanish-American War was influenced by, for ten points, what expansionist book that uses history to argue for the development of a dominant navy, written by Alfred Thayer Mahan?",
      "answer": "The Influence of Sea Power Upon History: 1660-1783"
    },
    {
      "question": "Land sold and mortgaged by a member of this family was the subject of Bryan v. Kennett, the so called “ratification” of the Louisiana Purchase by the Supreme Court. Another member of this family fought Haden Edward’s Fredonian Rebellion and denounced Article 13 banning slavery. This family, which led the “Old 300” as empresarios, included a man who lost an 1836 election to Sam Houston. For ten points, name this family which includes Moses and his son, Stephen, the “Father of Texas.”",
      "answer": [
        "Austin family",
        "Stephen Austin",
        "Moses Austin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The best-selling book of Jules Archer focuses on this conspiracy, which J.P. Morgan’s executive Thomas Lamont dismissed as “perfect moonshine.” One man claimed that Gerald MacGuire paid regular visits to his hotel room to discuss this conspiracy, which was investigated by the McCormack-Dickstein Committee. Hiram Johnson was to be installed as dictator as part of this conspiracy, which was detailed in Congressional testimony in 1934 by Major General Smedley Butler. For ten points, name this alleged conspiracy in which Franklin Roosevelt would have been overthrown by well-funded conspirators.",
      "answer": "Business Plot"
    },
    {
      "question": "A man in this position, Newton Baker, rejected David Lloyd George’s advice on how to mobilize a nation. Robert Todd Lincoln served in this position during the James Garfield and Chester Arthur administrations, putting down the Cincinnati Riots of 1884. Andrew Johnson violated the Tenure of Office Act by sacking a man in this position, leading to his impeachment. For ten points, name this Cabinet position held by Jefferson Davis and Edwin Stanton, now known as the Secretary of Defense.",
      "answer": "United States Secretary of War"
    },
    {
      "question": "David Koch [[KOHK]] ran on this party’s ticket in the Election of 1980, being the only ticket to platform equality for LGBT individuals in America. It’s not the Republican Party, but one faithless elector voted for a member of this party named Ron Paul in the Election of 2016. The response “What is Aleppo?” was said by a presidential candidate from this party, Gary Johnson. For ten points, name this U.S. party which supports Laissez-faire economics and hands-off government.",
      "answer": "Libertarian Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "George McClellan fought a short engagement at this site during the Peninsular Campaign, forcing John MacGruder to retreat to Williamsburg. An American force was bolstered by the Expédition Particulière, led by the Comte de Rochambeau [[roh-sham- BOH]], in a siege at this site. That battle at this site led to the surrender of General Cornwallis, who presented his sword to General Washington through his aide-de-camp. For ten points, give this site of the final battle of the American Revolution.",
      "answer": "Yorktown, Virginia 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
    },
    {
      "question": "One story supporting the plausibility of an early Japanese version of this accomplishment concerns the plight of the Three Kichis [[KEE-chees]]. The Dorset culture accomplished this feat but had dissipated by at least 1500. Another group that accomplished this feat, the Thule [[THOO-lee]], were called skraelings by another group who accomplished this feat and established L’Anse aux Meadows [[lahn-tsoh-meh-DOH]]. For ten points, name this accomplishment whose celebration has been renamed in some states to Indigenous Peoples Day from Columbus Day.",
      "answer": [
        "Discovering the Americas",
        "discovering the New World",
        "descriptive answers indicating new settlement in America",
        "the New World"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A century-long war which was fought over this resource ended when Louis-Hector de Callière [[kah-LYEHR]] negotiated the Great Peace of Montreal. The French-Canadian coureurs des bois [[kor-UHR day-BWAH]] were men who traded these goods with Native Americans. The Embargo Act forced John Jacob Astor to found a company named for this good and to create trading posts in the Pacific Northwest. For ten points, name this good often processed from the pelts of beavers.",
      "answer": [
        "Furs",
        "beaver pelts before mentioned",
        "answers indicating animal skins"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In a depiction of this battle, lithographers Currier & Ives sketched the death of Henry Clay, Jr. while he led the 2nd Kentucky Volunteers. During this battle, the Saint Patrick’s Battalion, made up of Spanish-speaking Irish ex-pats, manned heavy batteries that were stormed by the 1st Dragoon regiment. This battle occurred in La Angostura, in the state of Coahuila [[kwah-HWEE-lah]]. For ten points, name this inconclusive battle between sides led by Zachary Taylor and Santa Anna during the Mexican-American War.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Buena Vista",
        "Battle of La Angostura before mentioned 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2016, this politician defeated Loretta Sanchez in one election following Sanchez's controversial remarks about Muslims. During the 2020 Democratic primary, this politician notably attacked Joe Biden for his opposition to bussing policies. Former Georgia Senator David Perdue drew criticism for allegedly intentionally mispronouncing this politician's first name. As a Senator, this politician was preceded in office by Barbara Boxer and succeeded by Alex Padilla. For ten points, name this U.S. vice president.",
      "answer": "Kamala Harris 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "As governor of New York, a man from this family instituted the “stop and frisk” and “no knock” rules for NYPD officers. That man from this family was not on the 1976 Republican ticket, although he had served as vice president for Gerald Ford. Another man in this family had his company split into smaller companies by anti-trust suits, forming the likes of Exxon, Mobil, and Chevron. For ten points, name this family which includes a vice president, Nelson, and John, the founder of Standard Oil.",
      "answer": [
        "Rockefeller",
        "Nelson Rockefeller",
        "John D. Rockefeller, Sr. 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s associate, Elbert A. Woodward, committed both larceny and forgery while en route to a Connecticut Senate seat. Future presidential candidate Samuel Tilden refused to let this political figure free from prison even after he testified to the Alderman Committee. This man and his New York cronies were depicted as vultures in a Harper’s Weekly political cartoon by Thomas Nast. For ten points, name this “Boss” of the political machine, Tammany Hall.",
      "answer": "William “Boss” Tweed"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the most lopsided results of this process was led by the slogan “Yes, we love this land,\" which is also the title of the anthem of Norway, which underwent this process in 1905. Another one of these was defeated by the “No Thanks” campaign, which countered the efforts of Alex Salmond and Nicola Sturgeon. An illegal one of these in Spain was preceded by multiple human chains and was followed by the arrest of the president of Catalonia. For ten points, name this democratic process, which sometimes results in new countries.",
      "answer": [
        "Independence referendums or independence referenda",
        "plebiscite"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In support of freedom fighters in this war, U.S. folk group the Almanac Singers, led by activist Pete Seeger, wrote an album of songs such as \"Jarama Valley\" from a U.S. battalion which fought in this war. The use of manufacturing plants in Nazi Germany allowed American companies like GM and Ford to provide twelve thousand vehicles to Falangist [[fah-LAHN-jist]] forces during this intranational war. The Neutrality Act of 1935 prevented the U.S. from intervening in, for ten points, what war between the Republicans and Fascists led by Francisco Franco?",
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Civil War or Guerra Civil Española",
        "Civil War in Spain"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s raid on Fort Brooke coincided with his ally Micanopy’s [[mih-CAN-oh- pees]] ambush of Francis Dade’s U.S. army regiment. General Thomas Jesup captured this leader under a false “white flag” truce, and the poor conditions at Fort Moultrie led to this man's death. This chief orchestrated the breaking of the Treaty of Payne’s Landing, beginning a second conflict between his tribe and the U.S. army. For ten points, name this Florida chief, the primary Native American leader during the Second Seminole War.",
      "answer": "Osceola"
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization attempted to exile the author of My Country and the World before he could earn his 1975 Nobel Peace Prize. The head of this organization, Vladimir Kryuchkov, helped lead a 1991 coup to stop the presidential reforms of a man who was championed by a former head of this organization, Yuri Andropov. The NKVD served as the predecessor of this organization, and Russian president Vladimir Putin served as an agent for this organization in the late 1980s. For ten points, name this Soviet equivalent to the CIA.",
      "answer": [
        "KGB",
        "Committee for State Security",
        "or Komitet Gosudarstvennoy Bezopasnosti 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This conflict coincided with John Doukas’s recapture of Rhodes, Smyrna, and Ephesus. Prior to this conflict, Peter the Hermit led pogroms against Jews in the Rhineland Massacres before rampaging through Hungary. This conflict first came about after Emperor Alexios I Komnenos called for western aid against the Seljuq Turks at the Council of Clermont. For ten points, name this Crusade called by Urban II which established the Kingdom of Jerusalem in the Holy Land.",
      "answer": [
        "First Crusade",
        "Princes' Crusade"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A presidential candidate from this party continued a speech despite having a bullet lodged inside him after an assassination attempt by John Flammang Schrank. This party, later revived for reformer Robert La Follette’s [[luh-FAH-lets]] 1924 presidential run, first formed after William Howard Taft beat an opponent at the RNC. This party’s first candidate campaigned on Women’s Suffrage and a continuation of his Square Deal program from the early 1900s. For ten points, name this party formed by Theodore Roosevelt to run in the Election of 1912.",
      "answer": [
        "Progressive Party",
        "Bull Moose Party"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After the dramatic final hours of this year's presidential election, a reporter phoned the loser and was told \"the president is asleep,\" to which he responded, \"When he wakes up, tell him he isn't the president.\" That loser in this year, Associate Justice of the Supreme Court Charles Evans Hughes, was the Republican candidate, and the Democratic candidate in this year ran on the slogan “He Kept Us out of War.\" For ten points, name this presidential election year in which a second electoral victory was won by Woodrow Wilson.",
      "answer": "1916"
    },
    {
      "question": "This character appeared in a black-and-white serial in 1944 but differs from the original Timely Comics character, appearing instead as District Attorney Grant Gardner. After this Joe Simon creation was controversially depicted punching a national leader, New York mayor Fiorello La Guardia personally contacted the creators in support. In continuous publication since having been revived in 1964, for ten points, who is this super soldier played by Chris Evans in the Marvel Cinematic Universe who carries a shield and steadfastly defends the U.S.?",
      "answer": [
        "Captain America",
        "Steve Rogers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This musician, together with saxophonist Paul Gonzalves. allegedly caused a riot at the 1956 Newport Jazz Festival with their performance of \"Diminuendo and Crescendo in Blue.\" This frequent performer at the Cotton Club described the role of slavery and the church in Black American history in his suite Black, Brown, and Beige. This artist made what is considered the first significant African-American film score for 1959's Anatomy of a Murder, created with Billy Strayhorn. For ten points, name this legendary jazz pianist and band leader.",
      "answer": "Edward \"Duke\" Ellington"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this campaign, a combined 25 American and British planes crashed, with 101 fatalities overall. Gail Halvorsen dropped candy to awaiting children during this prolonged campaign, becoming known as the \"Chocolate Flier.\" After the Deutsche [[DOY-chuh]] Mark was introduced, Soviet troops cut off road and rail access to supply an occupied city, immediately causing this event. For ten points, name this aerial campaign led by the United States to provide aid and supplies to the German capital.",
      "answer": [
        "Berlin Airlift",
        "Operation Vittles"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Under these laws, a high concrete wall was used to divide off the Eight Mile-Wyoming Area. Ferris State University contains a memorabilia museum that houses artifacts related to these laws, which created a \"ghetto domestic sector.\" These laws were almost circumvented in the 1875 Civil Rights Act, which the Supreme Court ruled unconstitutional. Leading to \"colored\" restrooms being a norm, for ten points, what were these racial segregation laws in the Southern United States?",
      "answer": "Jim Crow Laws"
    },
    {
      "question": "After living in self-imposed exile in Europe, this man returned to the U.S. to marry Eliza Jumel, while using his mother’s maiden name of “Edwards.” Due to this lawyer's previous failed lease of the Bastrop Tract from the Spanish government in present-day Louisiana, he was tried and acquitted of treason. After losing a gubernatorial election for New York, this man challenged a former Secretary of the Treasury to a duel. For ten points, name this vice president under Thomas Jefferson who shot and killed Alexander Hamilton.",
      "answer": "Aaron Burr Jr."
    },
    {
      "question": "Secretary of War Jefferson Davis sent this man to Europe to study the tactics of the Crimean War, and later in his life, he would serve as governor of New Jersey. In letters to his wife, this general describes himself as \"the power of the land\" and the commander in chief as a \"well meaning baboon.\" This general was removed from command following the Battle of Antietam, and would challenge President Lincoln in the Election of 1864. For ten points, name this prideful Union general, known for his cautiousness in battle.",
      "answer": "George B. McClellan"
    },
    {
      "question": "Queen Elizabeth II granted this title to Margot Fonteyn after her performance as the Queen of Air in Homage to the Queen. Following an international tour with the Kirov company, American Eva Evdokimova [[ehv-DOH-kee-MOH-vah]] was given the assoluta form of this designation. The solo dance known as The Dying Swan was originated by a person with this specific designation, Anna Pavlova, who held the title while a member of Ballet Russes [[ROOSE]]. The most talented and experienced ballet dancers in a company are given, for ten points, which designation?",
      "answer": "Prima ballerina"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man publicly protested segregation by sharing a small pool with an African- American character, Officer Clemmons, in a 1969 episode of his namesake series. This man quoted that show by saying \"What Do You Do with the Mad that You Feel?\" in an argument to save funding for PBS while testifying in front of the Senate Subcommittee of Communications in 1969. The opening theme \"Won't You Be My Neighbor?\" was written by, for ten points, which host of a long-running children's TV show about [this man's] Neighborhood?",
      "answer": [
        "Fred Rogers",
        "Mister Rogers",
        "Mister Rogers' Neighborhood"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these items found at Takalik Abaj [[tah-KAH-leek AH-bah]] that was turned into an altar is the only one found outside a certain region. The material for these items was mined at La Cobata [[koh-BAH-tah]], and the distinct features of these items indicate they represent rulers of the culture that created them. A popular pseudo-historical theory argues the features of these items show “African influences.” For ten points, name these distinctive artworks of the Mesoamerican “mother-culture” found at sites like San Lorenzo and La Venta.",
      "answer": "Olmec colossal heads"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1946, the Soviet Union prevented a production of this work \"on the grounds that the drama [would] inspire a [...] suicide wave.\" This play was first performed at McCarter Theatre in New Jersey before transferring to Broadway, where Edward Albee hailed it as “the greatest American play ever written.” Told in three acts, this metatheatrical play features an omniscient stage manager who oversees the performance and is set in Grover's Corners, a \"typical American community.\" For ten points, name this play by Thornton Wilder, which earned him his first Pulitzer Prize for Drama.",
      "answer": "Our Town"
    },
    {
      "question": "John Boehner [[BAY-ner]] attempted to draw this man into being the running mate of Bob Dole in the 1996 election, resulting in him saying, \"the possibility is too remote to comment upon, given my position.\" This man interpreted the term \"militia\" in the Second Amendment to mean \"a body of citizens\" in his majority decision in District of Columbia v. Heller. The media widely reported on this Reagan nominee's shared friendship with his left leaning colleague, Ruth Bader Ginsburg. For ten points, name this originalist and textualist U.S. Supreme Court judge who died in 2016.",
      "answer": "Antonin Scalia or Anton Gregory Scalia"
    },
    {
      "question": "This tribe negotiated with Maryland Loyalist leader William Bowles, who successfully convinced them to reinforce the British fort in Pensacola during the Revolutionary War. The Seminole were originally from this non-Florida tribe, who migrated to Florida in the 18th century and mixed with local tribes like the Calusa. The militant faction of this tribe, the Red Sticks, were defeated by Andrew Jackson at Horseshoe Bend. For ten points, name this member of the \"Five Civilized Tribes\" of the Southeastern U.S., also known as the Muscogee.",
      "answer": [
        "Creek",
        "Muscogee before mentioned",
        "Red Stick Creek before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1908, this commander's ship, the USS Decatur, ran aground, leading to this man being found guilty of dereliction of duty. This man served as the signing representative of the U.S. aboard the Missouri during the unconditional surrender of another country. In 1945, this man succeeded his superior Ernest King as Chief of Naval Operations after commanding forces against Japan. For ten points, name this U.S. fleet admiral who was the commander- in-chief of the Unites States' Pacific Fleet during World War Two.",
      "answer": "Chester William Nimitz"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the second of these wars, public opinion was outraged by rumors that bloodhounds imported from Cuba were being used to mutilate opponents. Wiley Thompson attempted to depose several chiefs, including Micanopy [[me-kah-NOH-pee]], during these wars. The first of these wars was ended by the Treaty of Moultrie Creek, and the third was ignited in 1855 by Billy Bowlegs. The physical copy of the Treaty of Payne's Landing was stabbed by Osceola at the start of one of these wars. For ten points, name this series of three wars in which all but 500 of the namesake Native Americans were removed from Florida.",
      "answer": "Seminole Wars"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's only wound during a war was a bayonet to the posterior while investigating a trench he constructed during the Siege of Ninety-Six. This man emigrated to the U.S. following his capture at the Battle of Maciejowice [[mah-cheh-yoh-WIT-seh]] and the subsequent partition of his homeland. This man, who strengthened the defenses of West Point, served as an advisor to Nathaniel Greene during his Southern campaign. For ten points, name this military engineer who led the 1794 Polish rebellion and also served as a fortifications expert during the American Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "Tadeusz Kościuszko or Andrzej Tadeusz Bonawentura Kościuszko",
        "Andrew Thaddeus Bonaventure Kosciuszko"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Merchant Harrison Gray Otis wrote Letters in Defense of [this meeting] while serving as overseer of Harvard University. Despite voting unanimously to not send a delegate to this meeting, a Vermont county sent one representative, William Hall Jr, anyway. A one-term presidential limit and prohibition of lengthy trade embargos were proposed at this convention populated exclusively by New England representatives. The Federalist Party collapsed following, for ten points, which purportedly treasonous \"Convention\" held in a Connecticut city?",
      "answer": "Hartford Convention"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This nation’s custom of “mourning wars” may have led to conflicts with the Anishinaabe [ahnish-uh-NAH-bee], among others, and it signed the Treaty of Fort Stanwix with the British\nfollowing the Royal Proclamation of 1763. Leaders from this nation such as Joseph Brant allied\nit with the British during the American Revolution. For 10 points, name this tribal nation, a\nconfederation of six tribes in New York.",
        "answer": [
          "Iroquois",
          "Iroquois Confederacy",
          "Haudenosaunee"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This early Iroquois leader co-founded the confederacy with the Great Peacemaker and\nwas memorialized in a Henry Wadsworth Longfellow poem.",
        "answer": [
          "Hiawatha",
          "The Song of Hiawatha"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "To promote this cause, Howard Hyde Russell signed children up to the Lee-Lincoln Legion.\nA group promoting this cause advocated for “Protection for the home” and was led by Matilda\nCarse and Frances Willard. One proponent of this cause used a hatchet to smash its targets. For\n10 points, name this cause advocated for by a namesake Women’s Christian Union, as well as\nCarrie Nation.",
        "answer": [
          "Temperance",
          "prohibition",
          "outlaw of alcohol"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What act, drafted by the Anti-Saloon League’s Wayne Wheeler and named for a\nMinnesota Congressman, helped to enforce the 18th Amendment?",
        "answer": [
          "Volstead Act",
          "Volstead",
          "National Prohibition",
          "National Prohibition Act"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man helped design the M1913 Cavalry Saber which often bears his name. He was a key\npart of Operation Fortitude, which convinced the Germans he was leading a force to invade\nCalais [cuh-lay]. This general led an invasion of Casablanca during Operation Torch and helped\nrelieve Bastogne. For 10 points, name this American World War II general who slapped two\nsoldiers.",
        "answer": [
          "George Smith Patton Jr.",
          "Patton",
          "George Patton"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This fellow American World War II commanded the largest portion of US troops\nduring the war. He was the last five-star general in US history.",
        "answer": [
          "Omar Nelson Bradley",
          "Bradley"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A document written by this man was ordered revoked by Francis Bernard. This man was\nsucceeded by Increase Sumner in one position, and this author of the Circular Letter often met at\nthe Old South Meeting House. This Massachusetts resident helped organize the Boston Tea\nParty. For 10 points, name this American revolutionary who was the cousin of the 2nd President.",
        "answer": [
          "Samuel Adams",
          "Adams",
          "Sam Adams"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Adams helped form this shadow government system that excluded loyalists and\nallowed patriots throughout the colonies to coordinate revolutionary efforts.",
        "answer": "committees of correspondence"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was discovered by Frank Wills, after being approved by Jeb Magruder. Elliot\nRichardson resigned rather than fire Archibald Cox, a special prosecutor investigating this event.\nH.R. Haldeman was imprisoned for his role in this event, which was organized by the Committee\nto Re-Elect the President. For 10 points, name this scandal in which a hotel break-in led to the\nresignation of Richard Nixon.",
        "answer": [
          "Watergate break-in",
          "Watergate",
          "Watergate scandal"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "H.R. Haldeman held this White House position at the time of the break-in. Later, in the\nFord Administration, it was held by Dick Cheney.",
        "answer": [
          "White House Chief of Staff",
          "Chief of Staff"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This sect has an understanding which allows member congregations to use the word “Greater” in naming themselves. In 1995, it formally apologized for its role in perpetuating slavery and racism. This sect began with a convention in Augusta. For 10 points, name this largest protestant denomination in the United States, named for its geographic origins.",
        "answer": "Southern Baptist Convention"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Southern Baptist pastor and televangelist founded Liberty University in Lynchburg, Virginia.",
        "answer": "Jerry Lamon Falwell, Sr."
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "As governor, this man authorized the invasion of Illinois by George Rogers Clark. As a lawyer, he defended his home colony’s Two Penny Act in the so-called “Parson’s Cause.” This man succeeded Lord Dunmore to become the first non-royal governor of Virginia, and said in one speech “If this be treason, make the most of it.” For 10 points, name this man who declared “give me liberty or give me death!”",
        "answer": "Patrick Henry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry served as a member of this legislature of colonial Virginia, the first such body in North America.",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man succeeded William Marcy as Governor of New York, and this man was friends with political boss Thurlow Weed. This anti-slavery politician, who was wounded by Lewis Powell, tried to purchase the U.S. Virgin Islands before buying land from Russia. For 10 points name this Secretary of State under Lincoln and Johnson who bought Alaska, his namesake “folly.”",
        "answer": "William Henry Seward"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Seward lost the 1860 Republican nomination for President, as did this man who would serve as Treasury Secretary under Lincoln.",
        "answer": "Salmon Portland Chase"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this nation was removed in the People Power Revolution, also known as the Yellow Revolution, following the assassination of Benigno Aquino. General Wainwright surrendered this present day nation to the Japanese while besieged in Corregidor. For 10 points, name this country where American troops experienced the Bataan Death March.",
        "answer": "Republic of the Philippines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The wife of Philippine dictator Ferdinand Marcos, Imelda Marcos, was known for owning a large number of this article of clothing.",
        "answer": "shoes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The name of one of this man’s works was inspired by a display at the Columbian Exposition in Chicago involving the lowering of the Liberty Bell. Another of his compositions was often used to accompany the two-step and was commissioned by its namesake newspaper, the Washington Post. For 10 points, name this composer of The Stars and Stripes Forever and many other marches.",
        "answer": "John Philip Sousa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the request of Chester Alan Arthur, Sousa composed “Semper Fidelis”, which became the official march of this organization.",
        "answer": "the United States Marine Corps"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was the subject of investigations by Admiral Rickover and the Sampson Board. The entity at the center of this event was commanded by Charles Sigsbee, and Joseph Pulitzer edited articles about this event in one of the first examples of Yellow Journalism. For 10 points, name this 1898 event in which a coal explosion may have led to the explosion of a United States sea vessel in Havana Harbor.",
        "answer": "sinking of the USS Maine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other journalist also edited articles of Yellow Journalism. This rival of Joseph Pulitzer published the De Lome Letter.",
        "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1900, this state's governor William Goebel [Go-BELL] became the only sitting governor in U.S. history to be assassinated. Andrew Jackson used a campaign song that referred to \"the hunters of\" this state. After initially declaring neutrality in the Civil War, this state eventually stayed with the Union. For 10 points, name this state, the birthplace of Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln.",
        "answer": "Kentucky"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Kentucky joined the Civil War, this former Southern Democratic presidential candidate from Kentucky resigned from the Senate to become a Confederate general.",
        "answer": "John C. Breckinridge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man supported the mayoral campaign of George Moscone, leading to his appointment as chairman of the San Francisco Housing Committee. People loyal to this man assassinated Congressman Leo Ryan, after which he laced barrels of Flavor-Aid with cyanide. For 10 points, name this leader of the People’s Temple whose followers committed mass suicide in Guyana.",
        "answer": "Jim Jones"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Congressman who died in office was Larry McDonald, who perished after a Soviet fighter pilot shot down this airline’s Flight 007.",
        "answer": "Korean Airlines"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One member of this group drew a map of the world while in the service of the Wanli Emperor. An influential member of this order is the dedicatee of the Novena of Grace and preached in Goa and Japan. Those two men are Matteo Ricci and Frances Xavier. The founder of this order was wounded at the Siege of Pamplona and wrote The Spiritual Exercises. For 10 points, name this religious order founded by Ignatius of Loyola.",
        "answer": "Jesuits"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Jesuits hosted the Guarani and other indigenous tribes on what settlements in South America?",
        "answer": "Jesuit Reductions"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This election year’s Democratic convention was depicted in Norman Mailer’s “Superman Comes to the Supermart.” Claims of election fraud in Texas and Richard Daley’s Chicago led the losing candidate to wait a full day to concede. The first television debate in U.S. history was held during this election; in that debate, the winner of this election was praised for his tan, though radio listeners thought Richard Nixon debated well. For ten points, name this election in which John F. Kennedy became President.",
        "answer": "Election of 1960"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Nixon had pledged to perform this action, which may have led to his exhaustion before his first debate. Nixon fulfilled this promise by campaigning in Alaska days before the election was decided.",
        "answer": "visiting all 50 states or similar descriptions"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this battle, James Calhoun’s men held high ground but lost their horses when their handlers were shot. Reports of incoming soldiers shortly before this battle were dismissed by the elder Runs the Enemy, who noted that Americans never attacked in midday. The death of the scout Bloody Knife triggered Marcus Reno’s retreat from this battle, shortly before the 7th Cavalry was utterly destroyed. For ten points, name this June 1876 battle in which George Custer made his failed “last stand.”",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Little Bighorn or Battle of the Greasy Grass",
          "Custer’s Last Stand before Custer is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the battle, this Lakota warrior led a charge to break the American lines. A memorial to this man is being carved in the Black Hills roughly 20 miles from Mount Rushmore.",
        "answer": "Crazy Horse or Thasunke Witko"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man provided Harry Truman with a list of 12,000 Americans suspected of disloyalty, though Truman refused action. After press coverage of the Apalachin Meeting in 1957, this man began attacking the U.S. Mafia. Clyde Tolson very briefly succeeded him in his highest post, after a 37-year tenure during which he coordinated the arrests of John Dillinger and Al Capone. For ten points, name this first director of the FBI.",
        "answer": "J. Edgar Hoover"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hoover’s COINTELPRO program attempted to have this man, who he called the “most notorious liar” in the U.S., arrested for extramarital affairs and communist leanings. The FBI sent a letter to this civil rights leader trying to convince him to commit suicide.",
        "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. or MLK"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Paul Stevens wrote a 2014 New York Times editorial calling for the removal of this amendment from the Constitution. George Tucker applauded this amendment’s shift from language in the English Bill of Rights restricting its right to the wealthy, and the phrase “the People” in this amendment was held to apply to private citizens by Antonin Scalia in the 2008 decision D.C. v. Heller. The NRA holds that this amendment conveys an individual right. For ten points, name this constitutional amendment which bars infringing upon the right of the people to “keep and bear arms.”",
        "answer": "2nd Amendment to the U.S. Constitution"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 2nd Amendment was officially incorporated in a 2010 case named for McDonald v. this city, where the death of Laquan McDonald in 2014 sparked massive protests.",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One Superintendent for these workers quarreled with Frederick Law Olmstead and required applicants to be “very plain looking” and at least 30 years old. Walt Whitman and Louisa May Alcott briefly served in this role. Henry Whitney Bellows led the U.S. Sanitary Commission, which mobilized these people and their supplies. Mary Edwards Walker earned a Medal of Honor for her work in, for ten points, what civilian role, also served during the American Civil War by Elizabeth Blackwell and Clara Barton, who founded the American Red Cross?",
        "answer": [
          "Union Army nurses",
          "any description of the medical profession, including doctor, surgeon, medic, etc."
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This advocate for the insane and founder of America’s first mental asylums served as the Superintendent of Army Nurses during the Civil War.",
        "answer": "Dorothea Dix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This president ran on the slogan “Public office is a public trust.” This man granted Native Americans citizenship if they accepted an allotment of tribal land provided by the Dawes Act, which he signed. He ordered the leader of a “Petition in Boots” to be arrested after the “Army of the Commonwealth in Christ” trespassed on the White House lawn, and he sent federal troops to Illinois to guarantee mail delivery. Coxey’s Army and the Pullman strike were put down by, for ten points, what U.S. president who served two non-consecutive terms?",
        "answer": "Grover Cleveland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1894, Cleveland signed the Wilson-Gorman Tariff, reducing tariff rates from those set in 1890 by this Ohio representative and future President.",
        "answer": "William McKinley or McKinley tariff"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Amendments to this treaty were included in the Protocol of Queretaro, and it was preceded by a cessation of hostilities known as the Capitulation of Cahuenga. The chief negotiator of this treaty was Nicholas Trist. One party to this treaty paid the other 15 million dollars in exchange for land that included Alta California, and it established the Rio Grande as the undisputed southern border of Texas. For ten points, name this 1848 treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What proposal, named after its Pennsylvania sponsor, attempted to ban slavery in territory acquired by America in the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo?",
        "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One leader of this organization sued William Havemeyer for libel; Havemeyer died on the day of that trial. This organization, led by “Honest” John Kelly, faded away shortly after the fall of Carmine DiSapio. The first Catholic nominee for president, Al Smith, was strongly backed by this organization, which was developed by Aaron Burr but lost influence during Franklin D. Roosevelt’s governorship. Thomas Nast depicted this group as a tiger devouring democracy in 1871. Boss Tweed led, for ten points, what New York political machine?",
        "answer": [
          "Tammany Hall",
          "Society of St. Tammany",
          "Sons of St. Tammany"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In spite of Tammany Hall opposition, this Italian-American was elected mayor of New York in 1933 and served for 12 years.",
        "answer": "Fiorello H. La Guardia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "James Farmer coined the name for these people, who John Siegenthaler was trying to assist when he was knocked unconscious with a pipe. The lack of enforcement of the Supreme Court’s decision in Boynton v. Virginia inspired these people, as that case was supposed to prevent discrimination in public transportation. The Congress of Racial Equality, or CORE, was one sponsor of the Journey of Reconciliation taken by these people, who were firebombed and chased by white mobs. For ten points, give this term for civil rights activists who took buses into the segregated South in the 1960s.",
        "answer": "Freedom Riders"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This civil rights organization, co-founded by Julian Bond and chaired by John Lewis, sent students to assist with the Freedom Rides. It dropped “non-violent” from its name during Stokely Carmichael’s leadership of this group.",
        "answer": [
          "Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee or SNCC",
          "Student National Coordinating Committee"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this conflict, in response to Quaker George Logan’s attempt to create peace, Congress banned citizens from making unauthorized international diplomacy. The Retaliation was captured and re-captured in this conflict, which was ended by a treaty signed at Mortefontaine, which dissolved an alliance created in 1778. This event was caused by a breakdown in diplomatic relations regarding American debt owed to the pre-revolutionary government in France. The XYZ Affair was one cause of, for ten points, what officially-not-declared war that lasted from 1798 to 1800.",
        "answer": "Quasi-War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the XYZ Affair, Talleyrand preferred to meet with this American diplomat, a future Vice President, who traveled to France with Charles Pinckney and John Marshall.",
        "answer": "Elbridge Gerry"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted “your eyes and mine are never destined to see [the] miracle” of “peaceable secession” in a “plea for Harmony and Peace.” That speech, given on the seventh of March, controversially supported the Compromise of 1850, leading to this man’s resignation from the Senate. This man’s reply to Robert Hayne declared “Liberty and Union, now and forever, one and inseparable!” The 19th century “Great Triumvirate” consisted of John Calhoun, Henry Clay, and, for ten points, what Massachusetts senator?",
        "answer": "Daniel Webster"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Daniel Webster was an alumni of this university, whose private charter he defended in the Supreme Court against William Woodward. Webster called this Ivy League school “a small school [...] yet there are those who love it.”",
        "answer": "Dartmouth College"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This treaty’s Protocol of Queretaro was later ignored because one side’s representatives did not have the power to agree to it. Article XI of this treaty attempted to resolve cross-border raids by the Apache tribe, and territorial disputes arising from this treaty were later settled by the Treaty of Mesila in the Gadsden Purchase. The Rio Grande was set as the southern boundary of Texas in this treaty, which grantedCaliforniatotheUnitedStates.Fortenpoints,namethistreatythatendedtheMexican-American war.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo was embraced by those who supported this expansionist belief. This concept, whose name is usually attributed to John O’Sullivan, argues that American exceptionalism entitles the U.S. to expand to the Pacific coast.",
        "answer": "Manifest Destiny"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During an election held in this year, Jared Ingersoll was nominated for the losing ticket’s vice presidency; oddly, both main candidates ran as Democratic-Republicans in this year, including DeWitt Clinton. Fort Mackinac [mack-in-aw] was captured in this year, during which the Battle of Queenston Heights was fought and Detroit surrendered to Isaac Brock. For ten points, name this year in which James Madison was re-elected as president and in which a namesake war erupted between the U.S. and Britain.",
        "answer": [
          "1812",
          "War of 1812"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The War of 1812 was ended in 1815 with the signing of this treaty, which generally returned most borders and agreements to the status quo from before the war.",
        "answer": "Treaty of Ghent"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Baldus study was used to attack the injustice of this practice in the 1987 case of McClesky v. Kemp. John Stuart Mill conducted a famous debate with a Mr. Gilpin about the effectiveness of this practice in a modern society. Abolishing this practice is a requirement for joining the EU. Justice Brennan claimed that this penalty violated the Constitution’s ban on cruel and unusual punishment in 1972’s Furman v. Georgia. For ten points, name this judicial punishment whose methods include lethal injection and hanging.",
        "answer": [
          "capital punishment",
          "the death penalty"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This state conducted over a third of all of the United States’ executions from 1976 to 2016, though Alabama executed more prisoners per capita. This non-Alabama state’s “Huntsville Unit” was the first to carry out an execution by lethal injection in 1982.",
        "answer": "Texas"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one post, this man signed the Collier-Burns Highway Act to strengthen infrastructure within his state. The right for a defendant to remain silent was affirmed when the court led by this former California governor heard the case Miranda v. Arizona. Lyndon B. Johnson ordered this man to form a commission to investigate the assassination of John F. Kennedy. Dwight Eisenhower appointed, for ten points, what liberal Chief Justice who served from 1953 to 1969?",
        "answer": "Earl Warren"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Warren Commission included Allen Dulles, who had earlier served as the director of this American governmental agency. Its other directors included George H.W. Bush.",
        "answer": "Central Intelligence Agency"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This case built upon the ruling of Powell v. Alabama, which was unclear in whether certain rights were afforded in non-capital instances. Betts v. Brady was overruled by this case, in which Abe Fortas was assigned to work with the defendant. The accused in this case had broken into a Florida pool hall and, due to his poverty, was forced to represent himself in trial. For ten points, name this 1963 Supreme Court case that established the right to a state-appointed attorney for poor defendants.",
        "answer": [
          "Gideon v. Wainwright",
          "in either order"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The right toan attorney derives from this amendment inthe Bill of Rights, which also guarantees a speedy, public trial.",
        "answer": "6th Amendment"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Early knowledge about this event was derived from the journals of Patrick Gass. This event’s only casualty was Charles Floyd, who died of appendicitis in present-day Sioux City. A slave named York and the translator Toussaint Charbonneau aided this journey, which Thomas Jefferson ordered to explore the newly bought Louisiana Territory. Sacagawea aided, for ten points, what American expedition into the Western United States?",
        "answer": "Lewis and Clark Expedition or the Corps of Discovery expedition"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lewis and Clark Expedition set off from Camp Dubois [doo-bwah] in this state, from which they entered modern-day Missouri. Roughly three decades later, Joseph Smith brought his followers from Missouri to the village of Nauvoo in this state.",
        "answer": "Illinois"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s reputation suffered when two dozen miners were killed in a firefight at his Ludlow colony. Charles Pratt and Henry Rogers decided to work with this man after their companies were priced out in the “Cleveland Massacre.” When this man’s monopoly was found to be in violation of the Sherman Antitrust Act, it was split into companies that became Exxon and Mobil. For ten points, name this wealthiest American of all time, the founder of the Standard Oil Company.",
        "answer": "John D. Rockefeller"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rockefeller’s underhanded pricing tactics were exposed by this muckraker, who published The History of the Standard Oil Company in McClure’s magazine.",
        "answer": "Ida Tarbell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "ThismandecidednottocontestanelectionafterEstesKefauverwontheNewHampshireprimary.This man used Turnip Day as an opportunity to attack the Republican majorities in the 80th Congress. This man, who ordered the integration of the armed forces, suffered in popularity later for his nationalization of the steel mills during the Korean War. For ten points, name this president who was not defeated by Dewey during the 1948 Presidential election.",
        "answer": "Harry S. Truman"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1948, Truman’s Secretary of State introduced this economic policy, which sent a large amount of aid to help rebuild the economies of Western Europe.",
        "answer": [
          "Marshall Plan or the European Recovery Program",
          "ERP",
          "George Marshall"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man nicknamed after this animal, Charles Jones, worked with Charles Goodnight in a conservation effort to preserve their numbers. Another man nicknamed for this animal called his rifle Lucretia Borgia and once killed over sixty of these animals in an eight-hour hunting competition. The 10th Cavalry bore a nickname referencing this animal, a term eventually applied to several African-American regiments. William Cody’s nickname was that of, for ten points, what animal, whose population plummeted as American settlers traveled west?",
        "answer": [
          "buffalo",
          "bison",
          "Buffalo Bill",
          "Buffalo Soldiers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show included this man, at times a U.S. marshal and at times a vigilante, who was murdered while holding the Dead Man’s Hand at a poker game in Deadwood, South Dakota.",
        "answer": "”Wild Bill” Hickok or James Butler Hickok"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man briefly suspended one campaign on Larry King Live. This man’s running mate asked “Who am I? Why am I here?” in a vice-presidential debate. Admiral James Stockdale ran with this founder of Electronic Data Systems, who used charts to advocate for a balanced budget and briefly led both George H.W. Bush and Bill Clinton in polling. For ten points, name this Texas businessman who founded the Reform Party and won nineteen percent of the popular vote in the 1992 election.",
        "answer": "Henry Ross Perot"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ross Perot argued against what 1990s international political agreement, claiming it would create a “giant sucking sound?”",
        "answer": "NAFTA or North American Free Trade Agreement"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A political cartoon of this man depicts him urging his soldiers to fight while sitting on the mast of a boat with a telescope. This man rose to fame after a victory against Robert Garnett at Rich Mountain. He ran on a ticket with George Pendleton, though the capture of Atlanta hurt his peace platform in a presidential campaign. This man was removed from command after failing to pursue Robert E. Lee’s troops after a victory at Antietam. For ten points, name this overly-cautious Union general who ran against Lincoln in the 1864 election.",
        "answer": "George McClellan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Peninsular Campaign in summer 1862, McClellan’s indecision led to his failure to capture Richmond in this set of battles, including skirmishes at Oak Grove and Malvern Hill.",
        "answer": [
          "Seven Days Battles",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1833 court case originating in this state held that the restrictions in the Bill of Rights did not apply to state governments and was launched after a diversion of water ruined John Barron’s wharf. This state was a party to a ruling in which a liberal interpretation of the Necessary and Proper Clause allowed the creation of a national bank; that ruling struck down this state’s tax on out-of-state banks. For ten points, name this state, which lost its suit against James McCulloch, head of a bank in its city of Baltimore.",
        "answer": [
          "Maryland",
          "McCulloch v. Maryland BONUS:InadditiontotheNecessaryandProperClause,JohnMarshall’srulinginMcCulloch v. Maryland made use of this Constitutional clause, which makes state laws subordinate to federal laws. ANSWER: Supremacy Clause",
          "Article VI, Clause Two of the Constitution"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hall of Bulls is found at this Paleolithic cave complex in France. it also includes a drawing of a bird-headed figure being impaled by a bison.",
        "answer": "Lascaux caves"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location is home to the Timbisha Shoshone tribe, who use this location’s clay to make a red ochre [“oak-er”] paint. Accumulated salts in this location’s Badwater Basin have made its water undrinkable. In July 1913, this location’s Furnace Creek reached 134 degrees Fahrenheit, the hottest temperature ever recorded in the Western hemisphere. For ten points, name this location in the Mojave Desert of California, the lowest point in the US.",
        "answer": "Death Valley National Park"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Death Valley was proclaimed a National Park by this President, one month before he left office. This man’s Presidential library is in West Branch, Iowa, and his home in California is now the official residence of the President of Stanford University.",
        "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This policy was largely ignored by Congress as senators flocked to buy from “the man in the green-hat,” George Cassiday. Neal Dow became one of the first mayors to implement this policy under the Maine Law. Contraband violating this policy was destroyed by a hatchet-wielding Carrie Nation from the WCTU. This policy became law when the Volstead Act was enacted to carry out the Eighteenth Amendment. For ten points, name this 1920s policy that banned liquor throughout the US.",
        "answer": [
          "Prohibition",
          "temperance"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Prohibition, this leader of the Chicago Outfit, known as Scarface, made massive profits smuggling alcohol.",
        "answer": "Alphonse “Al” Capone"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s Operation Griffin included a violation of the Hague Convention when Otto Skorzeny dressed his troops in enemy uniforms. During this battle, American troops were fired on after surrendering at Malmedy. Anthony McAuliffe led a spirited defense of the town of Bastogne in this battle, whose losing side tried to use tanks to recreate the 1941 invasion of France. For ten points, name this 1944 battle that made a namesake shape in Allied lines.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Bulge",
          "Operation Watch on the Rhine",
          "Wacht am Rhein",
          "Ardennes Counteroffensive before “Ardennes” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The siege of Bastogne was lifted by this American commander of the Third Army. He was briefly disgraced for slapping a shell-shocked soldier during the Sicily landings.",
        "answer": "George S. Patton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man rebuked Henry Proctor, saying “I conquer to save, you [conquer] to kill” after their joint army perpetrated a massacre of prisoners at Fort Meigs. The New Madrid earthquake was interpreted by locals as a sign to join this man, whose death at the Battle of the Thames led to the dissolution of his tribal confederacy and its alliance with Great Britain. For ten points, name this chief of the Shawnee who fought the United States before and during the War of 1812 but was absent from the disastrous Battle of Tippecanoe.",
        "answer": "Tecumseh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tecumseh journeyed West in a failed attempt to ally with this five member tribal group. This group, composed of the Cherokee, Creek, Seminole, Choctaw and Chickasaw, received its name because it adopted Western customs.",
        "answer": "Five Civilized Tribes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Iconic photos from this site include a snapshot of Zbigniew Brzezinski [z’big-nee-ev breh-ZHIN-skee] playing chess and Paul Vathis’ “Serious Steps” showing John F. Kennedy and Dwight Eisenhower walking side by side. This site’s Dogwood, Aspen and Laurel buildings have been used to house visitors like Anwar Sadat and Menachem Begin, who met on a 1979 retreat. For ten points, name this Presidential compound where Jimmy Carter helped broker a peace accord between Egypt and Israel.",
        "answer": "Camp David"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Camp David was Barack Obama’s hosting ground for the 38th G8 summit, where tensions escalated when Vladimir Putin sent this current Prime Minister of Russia to attend in his place.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Medvedev"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This civilization’s writing system evolved into an “Epi” script, though their initial writings were recorded at the Cajascal [cah-has-kal] block in San Andres. This civilization became known as the “rubber people” for their ability to extract latex from nearby trees. Ritual bloodletting was practiced for the first time in Central America at this civilization’s center at San Lorenzo. For ten points, name this Mesoamerican civilization, known for their creation of large stone heads.",
        "answer": "Olmec civilization"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Olmec were the first to play this court-based Mesoamerican sport, which has had a modern resurgence. In later Mayan myth, the Hero Twins play this sport after descending to Xibalba [she-balba]",
        "answer": "Mesoamerican ball game"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man resigned his rank of colonel after he was compared to Clement Vallandigham for a speech in which he blamed the British, Jews, and the presidency for pushing towards war. This man became the first ever Time Man of the Year after successfully completing a trip to Le Bourget that earned him the Orteig prize. The Spirit of St. Louis was flown by, for ten points, what American pilot who completed the first solo transatlantic flight?",
        "answer": "Charles Lindbergh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charles Lindbergh controversially became an advocate for this anti-Semitic political group that strongly opposed American entry into World War II. This group dissolved after Pearl Harbor.",
        "answer": "America First Committee or AFC"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scandal was carried out by middlemen Adnan Khashoggi and Manucher Ghorbanifar. As part of this scandal, secretary Fawn Hall shredded evidence of violations of the Boland Amendment. This scandal was investigated by the Tower Commission and led to indictments for Caspar Weinberger and John Poindexter, who had aided in the funding of an anti-Sandinista force abroad. For ten points, name this Reagan-era scandal in which funds from arms sales to the Middle East were redirected to aid rebels in Nicaragua.",
        "answer": "Iran-Contra scandal or affair, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fawn Hall worked for this Marine lieutenant colonel, who was charged with 16 felonies for destroying evidence. However, all charges against this man were either dropped or vacated, as he was granted immunity for Congressional testimony.",
        "answer": "Oliver “Ollie” North"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This period was mitigated by the creation of shelterbelts by the Forestry Service. This period received its name after Robert Geiger’s visit to Boise City on the Sunday of April 14 coincided with an incidence of “black blizzards.” Dorothea Lange’s photograph Migrant Mother became symbolic of this period’s mass displacement of “Okies” who traveled to California after facing crop failure. For ten points, name this period of the 1930s in which severe drought affected the American plains.",
        "answer": "Dust Bowl"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This singer became known as the “Dust Bowl troubadour” after composing a series of ballads that included Pretty Boy Floyd. This man, whose guitar “kills fascists,” also wrote “This Land is Your Land.”",
        "answer": "Woodrow “Woody” Guthrie"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An inscription on this object bears the words “PASS AND STOW,” in honor of the two men who brought itback into use.A popular taleabout thisobjectholds thatits finaltask was theannouncement of John Marshall’s death. This object was first struck to mark the reading of the Declaration of Independence and has since received a two-foot-long crack on its side. For ten points, name this American landmark in Philadelphia that has not been rung in over a hundred years.",
        "answer": "Liberty Bell"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When the British threatened to occupy Philadelphia in 1777, the Liberty Bell was transported to, and briefly held in, this Pennsylvania town. A 19th century steel company named for this town was once the second-largest steel company in the US, after Pittsburgh’s US Steel.",
        "answer": "Bethlehem Steel"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1917, this state’s governor, Frank Lowden, sent National Guardsmen to stop a race riot, but most Guardsmen refused to help while police joined the fighting; a 1917 Silent Protest Parade in New York City was a direct response to that riot in this state. The arrest of two black men in this state’s capital sparked a 1908 race riot that led to the creation of the NAACP. For ten points, name this state where mass lynchings took place in East St. Louis and Springfield.",
        "answer": "Illinois"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Some reports claim that this man took part in the 1919 Chicago race riot as a teenager, four decades before he was elected mayor and five decades before he used so-called “Gestapo tactics” in the streets of Chicago.",
        "answer": "Richard Joseph Daley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This treaty required one signatory to cancel Article 27 of its constitution, which guaranteed reparations of land to indigenous people. As a result, this treaty was publicly attacked in the Lacandon Jungle Declaration by a group led by the ski-mask wearing Subcomandante Marcos, the Zapatistas. Carlos Salinas de Gortari and Brian Mulroney were key negotiators of this treaty, which was described as causing a “giant sucking sound” by Ross Perot in a debate against Al Gore. For ten points, name this 1992 trade agreement signed by Canada, Mexico, and the US.",
        "answer": "North American Free Trade Agreement or NAFTA"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prior to NAFTA’s provisions on agriculture, the US had recruited these Mexican laborers to work on farms under a program that lasted from 1942 to 1964.",
        "answer": "braceros"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1969, protesters at this university advocated the creation of a Black Studies program during the Allen Building Takeover. This university’s president, Terry Sanford, tried to place the Richard Nixon Presidential Library at this school, which was initially founded by Quakers and Methodists in the town of Trinity. One namesake of this school fought the Black Patch Wars and bought Lucky Strike as head of the American Tobacco Company. For ten points, name this private university in Durham, North Carolina.",
        "answer": "Duke University"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the assassination of Martin Luther King, students at Duke held a week-long Silent Vigil protesting racial discrimination and the non-recognition of Duke’s local chapter in this union for non-academic employees. This union, part of the AFL-CIO, is the largest union of public workers in the country.",
        "answer": "American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees or AFSCME"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Attack ads aired against this man in South Carolina accused him of fathering an illegitimate child with an African-American woman, though the images used were actually of his adopted Bangladeshi daughter. This man, who was permanently injured during a fire on board the USS Forrestal, sponsored a campaign finance reform act with Russ Feingold and entered the Senate by winning a seat vacated by Barry Goldwater. For ten points, name this Vietnam War veteran and longtime Arizona congressman.",
        "answer": "John McCain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Russ Feingold, McCain’s co-sponsor on campaign finance reform, was a three-term senator from this Midwestern state, which has also been represented by Isaac Walker and Herb Kohl.",
        "answer": "Wisconsin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this event, William Graham was criticized for memorializing members of the 5th Artillery who were killed on a dynamite-laced bridge while en route to stop this event. A rally to drum up support for this event was held at Blue Island, and it occurred despite an injunction from Richard Olney. When this event was deemed to interfere with federal mail, Grover Cleveland stepped in to end it. For ten points, name this 1894 Chicago strike against a namesake railway company.",
        "answer": "Pullman Strike"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This labor leader helped lead the Pullman Strike, years before he ran as a Socialist Party candidate for President from a jail cell.",
        "answer": "Eugene V. Debs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city failed to annex a section of neighboring land after the Mafia organized it into an unincorporated town called Paradise. In 2010, a stock image of a landmark in this city was accidentally used for a Forever Stamp; that half-size replica of the Statue of Liberty stands outside the New York-New York Hotel. The construction of the Hoover Dam fueled the early growth of, for ten points, what most populous city in Nevada, a gambling resort town?",
        "answer": "Las Vegas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This American business tycoon purchased the Desert Inn in Las Vegas after refusing to leave one of its rooms. This famously reclusive man designed the Spruce Goose, a wooden plane.",
        "answer": "Howard Hughes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The phrase “pig in the python” titled a cultural history of this group, which was collectively named Time Person of the Year in 1966. Reduced adult supervision led this group’s successor to be called the “latchkey generation.” Lower mortgage requirements and the G.I. bill contributed to the rise of, for ten points, what American generation that was succeeded by Generation X and was born after World War II?",
        "answer": "Baby Boomers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aging curve of the Baby Boomers is often cited as a financial threat to Medicare, which was introduced as part of this set of domestic policies by Lyndon Johnson in 1964.",
        "answer": "Great Society"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A popular dime novel referred to this woman as “The White Devil of the Yellowstone.” A first-hand account claimed that the rescue of Captain Egan at Goose Creek inspired this woman’s nickname. Jean McCormick claimed to be the daughter of this woman who allegedly chased after Jack McCall with a meat cleaver after he killed Wild Bill Hickok. For ten points, name this American frontierswoman and storyteller in Buffalo Bill’s Wild West Show.",
        "answer": [
          "Calamity Jane",
          "Martha Jane Canary"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Calamity Jane was buried next to Wild Bill Hickok in this South Dakota town, where Hickok was shot.",
        "answer": "Deadwood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man became politically influenced by Craig Rodwell, a member of the Mattachine Society. Martin Blinder argued that the killer of this man was suffering from depression by using examples of the sugary foods he had recently been binging on. The “Twinkie defense” was employed by Dan White, who murdered this man and mayor George Moscone in 1978. For ten points, name this San Francisco politician, the first openly gay elected official in California.",
        "answer": "Harvey Bernard Milk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When Milk and Moscone were shot, the police were called by this San Francisco politician, who was at City Hall at the time and succeeded Moscone as mayor. This politician now serves as California’s senior senator.",
        "answer": "Dianne Feinstein"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In John Steinbeck’s East of Eden, Cyrus Trask makes a living telling lies about his role in this war. The historical fiction novel The Last Full Measure by Jeff Shaara ends a trilogy about this war that began with his father’s more famous work, The Killer Angels. Another story about this war describes Peyton Farquhar’s hanging at Owl Creek and was written by Ambrose Bierce. Stephen Crane’s The Red Badge of Courage describes Henry Fleming fighting in, for ten points, what war for the Union?",
        "answer": "American Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another Ambrose Bierce work set in the Civil War is this short story about a young child’s horrifying experience in war. This short story is named for a bloody September 1863 battle in Georgia in which Bierce fought.",
        "answer": [
          "Chickamauga",
          "Battle of Chickamauga"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This President’s administration attempted to curb the arrival of communists by passing the Per Centum Act, which limited yearly immigration to 3% of a current ethnicity’s population. After this man was nominated at the Blackstone Hotel in a “smoke filled room,” he routed James Cox in the general election. Secretary Albert Fall’s sale of Navy land in the Teapot Dome scandal tarnished the legacy of, for ten points, what US president who promised a “return to normalcy” in the election of 1920?",
        "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Both candidates in 1920, Harding and James Cox, hailed from this state, as did Harding advisors Joseph Foraker and Harry Daugherty.",
        "answer": "Ohio"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This policy was formulated in a memorandum authored by William Woodville Rockhill. The Nine-Power Treaty upheld this policy, which was issued as part of U.S. foreign policy in a namesake 1899 note. Elihu Root continued this policy, which was first implemented under his predecessor as Secretary of State. This policy was nearly abandoned after the Boxer Rebellion, which threatened to break this policy’s central nation into spheres of influences. For ten points, name this American policy aimed at keeping China’s economy accessible to all major powers.",
        "answer": "Open Door Policy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Secretary of State issued the original Open Door Note while serving under President McKinley. This man, who worked as a secretary for Abraham Lincoln, negotiated a failed treaty with Tom´as Herr´an of Colombia in 1903.",
        "answer": "John Hay"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician was removed as the head of the Foreign Relations Committee after spearheading resistance against the annexation of the Dominican Republic. In his most famous oration, this politician noted his rival had a “mistress, who though ugly to others, is lovely to him,” then compared that rival to Don Quixote. This man was confronted for producing “libel on South Carolina” before he was physically attacked for his speech “The Crime Against Kansas.” For ten points, name this Massachusetts Senator who was caned on the Senate floor by Preston Brooks.",
        "answer": "Charles Sumner"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charles Sumner declared “the harlot, Slavery” to be the mistress of this South Carolina senator in the “Crime Against Kansas” speech. A US Marine Corps general with the same surname warned Congress of the Business Plot, a coup against FDR.",
        "answer": [
          "Butler",
          "Andrew Butler and/or Smedley Butler"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Linda Nash received over $5 million dollars for injuries received during this event, which resulted in six deaths. A tip given to Bill Miller of the Diplomatic Security Service resulted in the capture of this event’s perpetrator, who said “I am a terrorist and proud of it” during his trial. Eyad Ismoil was involved in this event, which targeted the B-2 level of a parking garage in Manhattan. Ramzi Yousef carried out, for ten points, what 1993 terrorist attack in New York City?",
        "answer": [
          "1993 World Trade Center bombing",
          "descriptions of the 1993 WTC attack,",
          "the first WTC attack",
          "Twin Towers in place of WTC"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Five of the six fatalities in the World Trade Center bombing were employees of this organization, which operates the airports, tunnels, and bridges of the New York/New Jersey area. 84 of its employees were killed on 9/11.",
        "answer": "Port Authority of New York & New Jersey"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This piece of legislation is depicted as a stone tripping a carriage in which the driver asks his companion “Do slack up a little there, Horace.” The Congressional Library holds the original draft of this document, written by Jacob Brinkerhoff. The namesake of this bill was a member of the Free Soil Party. This bill passed in the House, but was stopped by the Southern-dominated Senate, causing it to never actually be added to the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. For ten points, name this bill that would have outlawed slavery in territories gained in the Mexican-American War.",
        "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Even if the Wilmot Proviso had passed the Senate, it may not have gotten into the final treaty anyway; after all, this American diplomat ignored his instructions from President Polk and negotiated the treaty on his own.",
        "answer": "Nicholas Trist"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jesse Langdon was the final surviving member of this group, which frequently met in the Menger Bar. This group, which was sometimes described as its founder’s “Weary Walkers,” had a 50th anniversary stamp that commemorated the death of its captain “Bucky” O’Neill, who had died at Kettle Hill. Alongside the Buffalo Soldiers, this group fought against the forces of Antero Rubin at the Battle of Las Guasimas in Cuba. The 1st US Volunteer Cavalry was the official name of, for ten points, what Spanish-American War-era cavalry unit containing Teddy Roosevelt?",
        "answer": [
          "Rough Riders",
          "1st US Volunteer Cavalry before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This colonel was the first commander of the Rough Riders and the man referenced in the “Weary Walkers” nickname.",
        "answer": "Leonard Wood"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of the countries involved in this event sabotaged ICAO investigations into it. This event was triggered by the actions of Major General Genadi Osipovich, and came after an increased period of tension between two nations from the FleetEx naval exercise. Deviations in heading after leaving Anchorage caused the subject of this event to fly through restricted airspace over Kamchatka, leading to its crash near Sakhalin. For ten points, name this 1983 incident in which a Soviet Su-15 fighter attacked a civilian flight.",
        "answer": [
          "shooting down or equivalents of Korean Air Lines Flight 007",
          "shooting down of KAL 007"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Georgia congressman and former president of the John Birch Society was killed aboard Korean Air Lines Flight 007.",
        "answer": "Larry McDonald"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1540, this man was made adelantado of the R´ıo de la Plata. This explorer’s family name was supposedly inspired by an object that an ancestor of this man used to mark a secret pass at the Battle of Las Navas de Tolosa. With his Moorish slave Estevanico, this man was one of four who survived the Narv´aez expedition; that expedition was chronicled by this man in La Relac´ıon, the first account of the Americas written by a European. For ten points, name the Spanish conquistador of the early sixteenth century who was shipwrecked in the Gulf of Mexico and wandered the American southwest.",
        "answer": "A´lvar Nu´n˜ez Cabeza de Vaca"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The four survivors of the Narv´aez expedition re-encountered Spanish traders in what is now this Mexican state, south of Sonora. During the Mexican-American War, the US occupied the city of Mazatlan in this state.",
        "answer": "Sinaloa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader, who defined peace as “respect for the rights of others,” confiscated Catholic Church land in the Law of the Nationalization of the Ecclesiastical Wealth. This man’s Minister of the Interior, Francisco Zarco, created the rurales, a mounted police force that was expanded by Porfirio Diaz. This man’s family fled to New York after an invasion by Maximilian I, but he was restored to power in 1867. For ten points, name this Zapotec president who led the Liberals during the Reform War and opposed the French invasion of Mexico.",
        "answer": "Benito Pablo Ju´arez Garcia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Juarez’s presidencey, Ignacio Zaragoza won this May 5, 1862 battle that delayed the French takeover of Mexico. This battle is annually commemorated on Cinco de Mayo.",
        "answer": "Battle of Puebla"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This agency changed its policies after an incident involving four year old Charlotte May Pierstorff. In 1970, this agency allowed its workers to be given collective bargaining rights after a nationwide strike involving 210,000 employees. People were forbidden to use this agency for obscene purposes by the Comstock Laws. Until 1971, the leader of this agency was a member of the Cabinet. For ten points, name this government agency for which Ben Franklin served as the first postmaster general.",
        "answer": [
          "United States Postal Service",
          "USPS",
          "US Mail"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charlotte May Pierstorff changed USPS policy by performing this action. Henry “Box” Brown escaped slavery via the Adams Express Company and this process.",
        "answer": [
          "they mailed themselves",
          "descriptions relating to living people being shipped in the mail"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The territory that became this state was governed by the Howell Code and Hoyt Code. Jesuit Father Eusebio Francisco Kino worked with Native Americans in this state at Mission San Xavier del Bac. In 1917, the Phelps Dodge corporation deported many mine workers from this state’s town of Bisbee. In 2011, a congresswoman from this state resigned after being shot in an assassination attempt. For ten points, name this southwest state where Teddy Roosevelt supported the creation of Petrified Forest and Grand Canyon National Parks.",
        "answer": "Arizona"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This former Arizona congresswoman co-founded a gun control Super PAC after her shooting injuries forced her resignation from Congress.",
        "answer": "Gabrielle “Gabby” Giffords"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The death of this man’s daughter Anna led him to decline one campaign for president. This man, who lived on the Ashland plantation, once dueled John Randolph. Andrew Jackson’s biggest presidential regret was supposedly that he didn’t hang John C. Calhoun and didn’t shoot this man. A tariff, national bank, and system of roads were among the improvements advocated in the “American System” by, for ten points, what Kentucky stateman known as the Great Compromiser?",
        "answer": "Henry Clay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Clay’s duel with John Randolph ended peacefully, but he and a member of this family named Humphrey were each wounded in an 1809 duel. Other members of this political family included the Chief Justice in the cases McCulloch v. Maryland and Gibbons v. Ogden.",
        "answer": [
          "Marshall family",
          "Humphrey and/or John Marshall"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these events probably killed Union soldier Boston Corbett, the man who shot John Wilkes Booth. Wisconsin’s Green Island Lighthouse had to be kept on during the day during one of these events that may have been caused by fragments of Comet Biela. Peshtigo was struck by one of these events on the same day that one began on DeKoven Street, possibly after a cow kicked over a lantern. For ten points, name this type of natural disaster that destroyed thousands of wooden houses in Chicago in 1871.",
        "answer": [
          "fires",
          "additional information, like the Great Peshtigo Fire",
          "Great Chicago Fire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "According to an anti-Irish legend, the Great Chicago Fire began when this woman’s cow kicked over a lantern.",
        "answer": [
          "Catherine O’Leary",
          "Mrs. O’Leary"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man created the Bureau of Indian Affairs while serving as Secretary of War under James Monroe. This man, who became Secretary of State after the USS Princeton disaster, declared slavery to be a “positive good” in an 1837 Senate speech. The Tariff of Abominations was vehemently opposed by this author of the South Carolina Exposition and Protest. For ten points, name this member of the Great Triumvirate who often stood for states’ rights in the Senate.",
        "answer": "John C. Calhoun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Tariff of Abominations produced this crisis, which centered on whether or not states could choose to ignore federal law.",
        "answer": "Nullification crisis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hot deck imputation used by this agency was ruled constitutional in the case Utah v. Evans. Robert W. Marx helped create the TIGER system for this agency, and it also used the UNIVAC I computer. Frederick Jackson Turner developed the Frontier Thesis after this agency stopped tracking the frontier in 1890. Federal courts have blocked this agency from including a citizenship question in its upcoming forms. The U.S. Federal Statistical System includes, for ten points, what agency that, since 1790, has tabulated data about the American people every 10 years?",
        "answer": "U.S. Census Bureau"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 19th century, a US Census statistician discovered the Alabama paradox when trying to carry out this process, the constitutionally mandated purpose of the census.",
        "answer": [
          "apportionment of the House of Representatives",
          "descriptive answers regarding “calculating how many representatives in Congress each state will have”"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The fifth of the nine points of this proposal called for an executive-appointed Supreme Tribunal to oversee federal impeachment accusations, and its sixth point affirmed the Articles of Confederation as the law. William Paterson put forth this 1787 proposal calling for a unicameral legislature in which each state had one vote and thus equal representation. The Virginia Plan competed with this plan until the Connecticut Compromise was reached. For ten points, name this proposal at the Constitutional Convention that favored small states.",
        "answer": "New Jersey Plan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The New Jersey Plan included this concept, which was included in Article 1, Section 2, Clause 3 of the Constitution until 1868.",
        "answer": "Three-Fifths Compromise"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Robinson, a speaker for this group, faced an estate scandal after prot´eg´e Edmund Pendleton discovered debts. This group created eight shires, and its first meeting was cut short by a malaria outbreak. This assembly, which met at the Wren Building, passed the 1705 Slave Codes, stripping rights from African Americans, to prevent a repeat of Bacon’s Rebellion. The “Give me liberty or give me death” speech was given by Patrick Henry at a meeting of, for ten points, what legislative body of colonial Virginia?",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peyton, a member of this family, served as the last Speaker of the House of Burgesses. Another member of this family served in two positions in George Washington’s Cabinet.",
        "answer": [
          "Randolph",
          "Peyton and/or Edmund Randolph"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this movement, the Bishop of Worms tried to shelter Jews in his house and Ruthard of Mainz fought alongside his personal guard to defend Jews during the Rhineland massacres, which were perpetrated by men under Count Emicho, a leader of this movement. Another leader of this movement, WalterSansAvoir,causedtensionsbylootingoutsideofBelgrade.Thepeasantforcewithinthismovement was defeated at Civetot by Kilij Arslan. Peter the Hermit led peasants in a poorly-organized movement during, for ten points, what 1095-1099 campaign to recapture the Holy Land?",
        "answer": [
          "First Crusade",
          "People’s Crusade and/or Peasant’s Crusade and/or Pauper’s Crusade until “peasant” is read, and"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The People’s Crusade and First Crusade were each inspired by this meeting, where Pope Urban II cried “Deus Vult!”",
        "answer": "Council of Clermont"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s popular education bill eventually led to the “common-school” system in Pennsylvania. Langdon Cheves was replaced by this man, who prepared Lewis and Clark’s expedition report for publication. After Louis McLane and William Duane refused to withdraw from an institution led by this man, Roger Taney was appointed Treasury Secretary. The Whigs’ support for this man and his institution was countered by Andrew Jackson, who refused to renew his charter. For ten points, name this final president of the Second Bank of the United States.",
        "answer": "Nicholas Biddle"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among Biddle’s supporters was this co-founder of the Second Bank who served as Minister to the UK and France after spending nearly 13 years as Secretary of the Treasury under Jefferson and Madison.",
        "answer": "Albert Gallatin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An image near the top left of one of these artworks shows seven black stars and a blue figure blowing a trumpet in a depiction of the Dark Day of May 19, 1780. Harriet Powers created Pictorial and Bible versions of these artworks. Two of these artworks, Echoes of Harlem and Who’s Afraid of Aunt Jemima? were created by Faith Ringgold. One of these artworks organized by the NAMES Project commemorates victims of AIDS by displaying their names on three-foot by six-foot interlocking panels. For ten points, name these cloth artworks that are often used as blankets.",
        "answer": "quilts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The collaborative International Honor Quilt is an international project currently housed at the University of Louisville and planned by this modern American artist, who planned the quilt to enhance her feminist piece The Dinner Party.",
        "answer": [
          "Judy Chicago",
          "Judith Sylvia Cohen"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Albert Toven and Randy Lawrence discovered aluminum versions of these objects which had been released in 1974, but were told they were government property. A large version of these objects included Wreath, Flowing Hair, and Draped Bust variants. Victor Brenner designed the Wheat stalk variety of these objects, many of which depict Abraham Lincoln. Made of zinc and copper, it is debated whether these coins are still necessary. For ten points, name this smallest denomination of U.S. coinage.",
        "answer": "U.S. Penny"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lincoln Penny first appeared in 1909, having been ordered on the way out of office by this Republican president who considered himself to be Lincoln's political heir.",
        "answer": "Theodore \"Teddy\" Roosevelt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In one of these institutions, Frank “Big Black” Smith and Cleveland “Jomo” Davis led a notable 1971 uprising. The history of these facilities as an extension of slavery and segregation was chronicled by Michelle Alexander in The New Jim Crow. The number of these facilities grew in England due to unpopularity of the \"Bloody Code,\" under which individuals such as petty thieves could be given the death penalty. For ten points, name these facilities, whose overuse is referred to as \"mass incarceration.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Prisons",
          "jails",
          "penitentiarys"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "With Ruth Wilson Gilmore, this American activist founded Critical Resistance to help promote prison abolition. This feminist scholar was charged and later acquitted over her alleged involvement in the Soledad Brothers' courtroom kidnapping attempt.",
        "answer": "Angela Yvonne Davis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a crisis in this state, one mayor said that he was sick of \"lazy\" residents expecting a government \"handout.\" This state's governor falsely claimed that a power shortage in this state was due to renewable energy sources. In February 2021, four million residents of this state lost power due to Winter Storm Uri [[YOOR-ee]]. This state is the only one of the lower 48 states to have its own power grid. For ten points, name this state from which John Cornyn and Ted Cruz have served as U.S. senators.",
        "answer": "Texas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This governor of Texas repeatedly refused to request FEMA or military aid during Winter Storm Uri, prompting speculation that Beto O'Rourke would challenge him in 2022.",
        "answer": "Greg Abbott"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nations like Estonia and Persia sponsored a letter by this group presented to the League of Nations to gain further autonomy in two North American nations. This organization relinquished claims to the American Midwest in the Nanfan Treaty. This group, whose people resided in Longhouses, negotiated the Proclamation of 1763 to protect themselves from settler colonization past the Appalachians. Tribes like the Oneida and Mohawk made up, for ten points, which “Confederacy” of six nations who acted as allies of the British throughout the 18th century?",
        "answer": [
          "Iroquois Confederacy or Haudenosaunee",
          "Iroquois League",
          "Five Nations before \"Six\"",
          "Six Nations before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Iroquois Confederacy fought so-called “Mourning Wars” to gain this resource from rival tribes.",
        "answer": "Slaves 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This program was allegorized as Fascism by Kurt Weill [[VILE]] and Maxwell Anderson in Knickerbocker Holiday. Democrat Jouett Shouse [[JO-ett SHOUSS]] opposed this program which was attacked by the American Liberty League, including Empire State Building creator John J. Raskob and the du Pont brothers. This program created the FDIC and allowed for farmers to have electricity in the Rural Electrification Act. The TVA was created under, for ten points, what set of FDR-created programs which aided Americans in the Great Depression?",
        "answer": "The New Deal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Knickerbocker Holiday was based on stories which took place in New Netherland written by this New York writer who went by the pseudonym \"Diedrich Knickerbocker\" and wrote works including \"Rip Van Winkle.\"",
        "answer": "Washington Irving"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man argued before the U.S. Supreme Court in Fletcher v. Peck and befriended Tsar Alexander I as the first U.S. ambassador to Russia. This man suspended the Treaty of Indian Springs after learning it had been forced upon the Muscogee and led the repeal of a gag rule preventing Congressional debates on abolition. As Secretary of State, this man helped create the Monroe Doctrine. For ten points, name this son of a former president who in 1828 lost the presidency to Andrew Jackson.",
        "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1870, John Quincy Adams's son, Charles Francis, built the first of these institutions at Adams National Historical Park in Massachusetts to store such items as the Mendi Bible and George Washington's Farewell Address.",
        "answer": [
          "Presidential librarys",
          "Presidential Center"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A 1946 Conference in this nation’s capital was coordinated by \"Lucky\" Luciano to coordinate mob policies and discuss collective business interests. The U.S. refused to recognize this nation’s government, which was led by Ramón Grau, after he nullified the Platt Amendment. The explosion of the USS Maine off this nation’s coast led to war between the U.S. and the Kingdom of Spain. The U.S. trained exiled men as paramilitaries to overthrow, for ten points, what nation’s Castro government as part of the Bay of Pigs Incident?",
        "answer": "Republic of Cuba"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The American government supported this Cuban dictator, the predecessor to Fidel Castro, who was overthrown by the 26th of July Movement.",
        "answer": "Fulgencio Batista 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, an incident in which four police officers were killed by Robert Charles sparked deadly race riots in 1900. In 1873, Sheriff Christopher Columbus Nash orchestrated a massacre of Black militiamen in this state’s Colfax massacre. Homer Plessy intentionally violated this state’s Separate Car Act by sitting in a whites-only car headed to St. Tammany Parish, leading to a landmark U.S. Supreme Court case. For ten points, name this state whose diversity is exemplified by its Creole culture.",
        "answer": "Louisiana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Plessy v. Ferguson established this legal doctrine justifying segregation, later declared unconstitutional in Brown v. Board of Education.",
        "answer": "Separate but equal"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Article 7 of this law was supposedly written by Nathan Dane or Manasseh Cutler and banned slavery in one region. Five thousand free males were required to have a representative in office according to this law, which called for the creation of a public educational institution, later called Ohio University. This law allowed for the creation of between three to five states, which today include Indiana and Michigan. The Congress of the Confederation created the first U.S. Territories through, for ten points, what 1787 law?",
        "answer": "Northwest Ordinance"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A portion of the Northwest Ordinance region was disputed between the U.S. and Prince Rupert's Land and is today mostly comprised of Superior National Forest in this U.S. state.",
        "answer": "Minnesota"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man attempted to deter American militia from fighting in the Patriot War to support the fledgling Republic of Canada. Ralph Waldo Emerson wrote an open letter to this man to cease any further removal of the Cherokee. This man, who spoke Dutch as his first language, gained Andrew Jackson’s favor for his support during the Petticoat Affair, leading to his appointment as Jackson’s second Vice President. For ten points, name this one-term Democratic president whose term was derailed by the Panic of 1837.",
        "answer": "Martin Van Buren"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A court case revolving around this Spanish schooner occurred during the Van Buren presidency. The U.S. courts allowed the Mende slaves who took control of this ship to return to Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "La Amistad",
          "United States v. Schooner Amistad 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Gaston Means claimed this man's \"strange death\" resulted from poisoning, not a cerebral hemorrhage or cardiac arrest. In 1923, Charles R. Forbes, who served as director of the Veterans' Bureau in this man's administration, was indicted for fraud, just one of many scandals involving this man. This man had extramarital affairs with Nan Britton and Carrie Fulton Phillips. For ten points, name this U.S. president whose involvement in the Teapot Dome scandal came to light only after he died in office.",
        "answer": "Warren Gamaliel Harding"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "U.S. Secretary of the Interior Albert Bacon Fall was convicted for accepting bribes from oil companies in the Teapot Dome scandal, whose namesake petroleum reserves are located in this state.",
        "answer": "Wyoming 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After openly testifying about this military event, abolitionist Silas Soule was killed by a fellow militiaman for outing his commander to a Samuel Tappan-led Congressional tribunal. This event was perpetrated by the “Fighting Parson,'' John Chivington, and occurred after he ignored a white flag raised by Southern Cheyenne leader Black Kettle. For ten points, name this 1864 “massacre” of Cheyenne and Arapaho women and children near a namesake Colorado tributary.",
        "answer": [
          "Sand Creek Massacre",
          "Chivington Massacre before mentioned",
          "Battle of Sand Creek"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Texas Mounted Rifles drew with Chivington’s Union forces at the Battle of Glorieta Pass in what is now this U.S. state which entered the Union in 1912.",
        "answer": "New Mexico"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Antonín Dvořák [[DVOR-jahk] premiered his American string quartet at this event, having composed it during his time among Czech immigrants in Iowa. Frederick Jackson Turner first argued his “Frontier Thesis” in a lecture given at this event. One of the stars on a Midwestern city's flag represents this 19th century event, whose fairgrounds were designed by Frederick Law Olmstead. For ten points, name this 1893 World's Fair held in Chicago and named for the anniversary of a Genoan explorer's rediscovery of the New World.",
        "answer": [
          "World's Columbian Exposition",
          "World's Fair: Columbian Exposition, 1893 World's Fair before mentioned,",
          "Chicago World's Fair",
          "Chicago World's Exposition before \"Chicago\" is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The structures built for the Columbian Exposition followed this architectural style developed and named for a specific art school in Paris whose American proponents included Daniel Burnham and Louis Sullivan.",
        "answer": "Beaux-Arts ] architecture"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the Great Depression, John Collier orchestrated this tribe's namesake \"Livestock Reduction\" in response to the growing Dust Bowl. This tribe constructed pueblitos to defend themselves from Comanche raids in their homeland of Dinétah. During World War Two, the U.S. War Department used members of this tribe to relay important messages in their native language. For ten points, name this tribe whose reservation, the largest in the United States, covers over 27 thousand square miles of Arizona, Utah, and New Mexico.",
        "answer": "Navajo"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Navajo Livestock Reduction nearly caused the Navajo-Churro, a breed of this animal key to the production of traditional blankets and rugs, to disappear completely.",
        "answer": "Sheep"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The fanfare Buckaroo Holiday begins a ballet by this composer, whose choreographer, Agnes de Mille, later worked on the thematically similar Oklahoma!. Martha Graham earned a Pulitzer Prize for her work with this composer for a piece which celebrates the American pioneer and includes a reworking of the Shaker hymn \"Simple Gifts.\" Rodeo, Fanfare for the Common Man, and Appalachian Spring were written by, for ten points, which American composer?",
        "answer": "Aaron Copland ]"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Copland composed a work named for which outlaw who was gunned down by Pat Garrett in 1881?",
        "answer": [
          "Billy the Kid",
          "William Bonney"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This acquisition was retroactively confirmed by the decision American Insurance Co. v. Canter. Secretary of the Treasury Albert Gallatin informed the sitting president that this acquisition was protected by the treaty-making provision in the Constitution. The costliness of the Haitian revolution led to this sale of territory by Napoleon to the United States. The Jefferson administration facilitated, for ten points, what \"Purchase\" which doubled the size of the United States?",
        "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The territory of the Louisiana Purchase was explored by which duo of officers who led the Corps of Discovery?",
        "answer": [
          "Lewis and Clark or Merriweather Lewis and William Clark",
          "in either order"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A subset of the \"Great Railroad Strike of 1877\" in this city included strikers trapping police officers on the Halsted Street bridge in the Battle of the Viaduct. During the \"Red Summer,\" this city suffered a race riot on its South Side after African-American teen Eugene Williams was killed for swimming near an \"All-White\" beach. This city's Hyde Park neighborhood hosted the Columbian Exposition of 1893. Hull House was founded in, for ten points, which Midwestern city that suffered a \"Great Fire\" in the 1870s?",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Contributing to the violence of the Chicago Race Riot, the Hamburg Athletic Club, which included future mayor Richard J. Daley, was composed primarily of what white immigrant ethnic group that fiercely guarded neighborhoods like Bridgeport and Back of the Yards.",
        "answer": "Irish-Americans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"Joe and Jerry\" show took place in this election year, which featured the first formal vice presidential debate. The loser in this election year used a \"Rose garden\" strategy to present as a leader compared to his opponent. That same candidate sank in the polls in this election year after claiming \"there is no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe.\" For ten points, name this U.S. presidential election in which Gerald Ford was defeated by Jimmy Carter.",
        "answer": "1976 United States Presidential Election"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Though Jimmy Carter won the election, he suffered in the polls due to an interview with this lifestyle magazine, in which he claimed to have \"lusted in my heart\" for women other than his wife.",
        "answer": "Playboy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Despite winning this battle, one commander's resignation was called for by the public, leading the president to reply, \"I can't spare this man; he fights.\" W.H.L. Wallace's men managed to hold the Hornet's Nest during this battle, which was won after the arrival of the Army of the Ohio under Don Carlos Buell. William T. Sherman emerged as a war hero following, for ten points, what 1862 Civil War victory for General Grant in southwestern Tennessee?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Shiloh",
          "Battle of Pittsburg Landing before mention"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the Battle of Shiloh, which Kentucky-born general was killed during the fighting, becoming the highest ranking Confederate officer to be killed in combat?",
        "answer": "Albert Sidney Johnston"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A person from this colony opened a ferry service at Blue Rock, sparking a territorial conflict that was only resolved by royal proclamation from George II. Thomas Cresap was from the colony that became this U.S. state, which used the Necessary and Proper clause to attempt to tax a federal institution led by James McCulloch. With Virginia, this state agreed to give up territory to establish the District of Columbia. The U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis was founded in, for ten points, which Mid-Atlantic state on the Chesapeake?",
        "answer": "Maryland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "McCulloch v. Maryland arose out of attempt by the state to tax what federal institution, whose last president was Nicholas Biddle?",
        "answer": [
          "Second Bank of the United States",
          "Second Bank of the U.S.",
          "or Second B.U.S."
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Architect William Thornton convinced one side during this event to spare the Patent Office, which briefly hosted Congress following this event. Partially motivated by the American invasion of Upper Canada, Robert Ross's victory at the Battle of Bladensburg led to this violent incursion. Dolley Madison saved a portrait of George Washington during, for ten points, what destructive event during the War of 1812 that followed the capture of the U.S. national capital?",
        "answer": [
          "Burning of Washington",
          "Burning of D.C.",
          "equivalents to \"burning\" like \"destruction\""
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Burning of Washington destroyed the first iteration of the Library of Congress, resulting in which former president donating and selling many works from his private collection?",
        "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This law's namesake representative introduced the Kinkaid Act to modify it, aiming to settle the Nebraska Sandhills. Grover Cleveland's last speech to Congress requested that this act be amended to allow the Indian Territory, now in modern Oklahoma, to be opened to prospective settlers. George Henry Evans supported the passage of this act by using the phrase \"Vote Yourself a Farm.\" 160 free acres of government land were offered to U.S. citizens by, for ten points, which 1862 act during the Lincoln administration?",
        "answer": "Homestead Act of 1862"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An early bill meant to encourage Homesteading was proposed by this New York Tribune editor who lost the 1872 general election to Ulysses S. Grant.",
        "answer": "Horace Greeley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "General Nisbet Balfour ordered Samuel Tynes and a Loyalist militia to capture this man, resulting in the Battle of Tearcoat Swamp. This man was unable to prevent the American loss at Camden after Horatio Gates sent him on a scouting mission with the Williamsburg militia. Banastre Tarleton stated that the \"Devil himself could not catch [this officer]\" during an unsuccessful trek through 26 miles of Carolina wetlands to capture him. The \"Swamp Fox\" was the nickname given to, for ten points, which Southern Revolutionary War officer and pioneer of guerilla warfare?",
        "answer": "Francis Marion"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the French and Indian war, Francis Marion led a protracted and brutal campaign against which southern indigenous tribe, developing his techniques of irregular warfare?",
        "answer": [
          "Cherokee or Anigiduwagi",
          "Tsalagi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this man broke with other Southern congressmen to oppose the Clayton Compromise, he was stabbed during a fight with state supreme court justice Francis Cone at an Atlanta hotel in 1848. This \"sage of Liberty Hall\" spent most of the Civil War writing both anonymous and signed letters denouncing Jefferson Davis's policy of conscription before leading the Confederate delegation at the Hampton Roads peace conference. For ten points, name this vice-president of the Confederacy.",
        "answer": "Alexander Stephens or Alexander Hamilton Stephens"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In this March 1861 speech, Stephens used the metaphor of a building block to explain that slavery was the foundational idea of the Confederacy.",
        "answer": "Cornerstone speech"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The private Joint Church Aid launched an airlift to relieve mass starvation using the island of São Tomé as a base during this war. Chinua Achebe formally joined a breakaway state as a propagandist until his home city of Aba fell during this war. Pogroms of the Igbo [[EE-boh]] people in the mid-1960s prompted military officer Emeka Ojukwu [[oh-\"JUKE\"- woo]] to declare independence from a West African state, which led to this war. For ten points, give this 20th-century civil war named for a breakaway state in Southeastern Nigeria.",
        "answer": [
          "Biafran Civil War",
          "Nigerian Civil War before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Israeli intelligence agency that captured Adolf Eichmann secretly sold arms to the Biafrans through neutral Switzerland?",
        "answer": [
          "Mossad or The Institute",
          "HaMossad leModiʿin uleTafkidim Meyuḥadim",
          "or The Institute for Intelligence and Special Operations"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A vice-presidential candidate during this election year went on to serve as Ambassador of France during the Civil War. Andrew Jackson’s nephew was a vice- presidential candidate in this election year, during which Salmon Chase and William Seward withdrew their names from consideration. Anti-Catholic sentiment prompted the Know Nothing Party to run former-president Millard Fillmore in this election year, during which the first Republican National Convention was held. For ten points, in what election year did Republican John C. Fremont lose to Democrat James Buchanan?",
        "answer": "1856 United States Presidential Election"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "John C. Fremont would also lead this fringe political party, which was formed due to Abraham Lincoln's perceived moderate policies. This abolitionist party eventually withdrew from the 1864 election to avoid spoiling Lincoln's re-election.",
        "answer": [
          "Radical Democracy Party",
          "Radical Democrats"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "REVOLUTIONARY WAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Were the two Massachusetts towns where the war started?",
          "answer": "Lexington and Concord"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the 1775 pyrrhic victory for the British, actually fought on Breed’s Hill?",
          "answer": [
            "Bunker Hill",
            "Battle of Bunker Hill"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the British general who surrendered at Yorktown?",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Cornwallis",
            "Cornwallis",
            "First Marquess Cornwallis",
            "Viscount Brome",
            "Brome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the American general who attempted to betray West Point?",
          "answer": [
            "Benedict Arnold",
            "Arnold"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the American general who won at Saratoga but was disgraced at Camden?",
          "answer": [
            "Horatio Lloyd Gates",
            "Gates"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the spy who stated “I only regret I have but one life to give for my country?”",
          "answer": [
            "Nathan Hale",
            "Hale"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Rhode Island general who led the American army at Guilford Courthouse?",
          "answer": [
            "Nathanael Greene",
            "Greene"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the South Carolina “Swamp Fox” who led guerrilla warfare against the British?",
          "answer": [
            "Francis Marion",
            "Marion"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "During the Revolutionary War, who or what…"
    },
    {
      "category": "CRUSADES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Led Muslim resistance to the Third Crusade after capturing Jerusalem in 1187?",
          "answer": [
            "Saladin",
            "Salah ad-Din"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Third Crusade as the King of England and won the Battle of Arsuf [ar-soof]?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard I",
            "Richard the Lionheart"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a military monastic order founded in 1119 and named after a prominent Jerusalem site?",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Templar",
            "Templar",
            "Poor Fellow-Soldiers of Christ and of the Temple of Solomon",
            "Soldiers of the Temple of Solomon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the other prominent Christian military order, which survived on Malta and Rhodes after\nthe Crusades?",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Hospitaller",
            "Hospitaller",
            "Order of Hospitallers",
            "Order of the Knights of St. John",
            "St. John"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the city, notably not in the Holy Land, was the capital of an Empire led by Alexius I?",
          "answer": "Constantinople"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the 1187 crushing defeat for the Kingdom of Jerusalem that prompted the launch of the\nThird Crusade?",
          "answer": "Battle of the Horns of Hattin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first ruler to use the title “King of Jerusalem”?",
          "answer": [
            "Baldwin I",
            "Baldwin",
            "Baldwin IX of Flanders",
            "Baldwin IX",
            "Baldwin VI Count of Hainaut",
            "Baldwin VI Hainaut"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the last Crusader city to fall, in 1291?",
          "answer": [
            "Acre",
            "Akka",
            "Akko"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "During the Crusades, who or what…"
    },
    {
      "category": "1956",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was re-elected President of the United States?",
          "answer": [
            "Dwight D. Eisenhower",
            "Eisenhower",
            "Ike"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost the US Presidential election?",
          "answer": [
            "Adlai Stevenson II",
            "Stevenson",
            "Adlai Stevenson"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the European country invaded by the Soviet Union in October to put down a revolt?",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Hungary",
            "Hungary",
            "Magyarorszag"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the country that joined France and Britain in briefly seizing control of the Suez Canal?",
          "answer": [
            "State of Israel",
            "Israel"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the New York Yankees pitcher who threw a perfect game in the World Series?",
          "answer": [
            "Don Larsen",
            "Larsen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nation led by Anastasio Somoza Garcia, who was assassinated in 1956?",
          "answer": "Nicaragua"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nation that hosted the first Summer Olympics in the Southern Hemisphere?",
          "answer": [
            "Commonwealth of Australia",
            "Australia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The Italian ocean liner that sank off the coast of Massachusetts, killing 46 people?",
          "answer": [
            "S.S. Andrea Doria",
            "Andrea Doria",
            "SS Andrea Doria"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In the year 1956, who or what…"
    },
    {
      "category": "JACKSONIAN DEMOCRACY",
      "prompt": "Who or what was or were...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The state where Andrew Jackson lived at the Hermitage?",
          "answer": "State of Tennessee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated Jackson in the 1824 Presidential election?",
          "answer": "John Quincy Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Whig opponent of Jackson from Kentucky?",
          "answer": "Henry Clay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political deal which denied Jackson the 1824 election in the House of Representatives?",
          "answer": "Corrupt Bargain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Financial institution led by Nicholas Biddle which Jackson refused to renew?",
          "answer": "Second Bank of the United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "Frenchman who analyzed American life in the time of Jackson in his Democracy in America?",
          "answer": "Alexis de Tocqueville"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jackson’s Attorney General who became Chief Justice, later authoring the Dred Scott opinion?",
          "answer": "Roger Taney"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Kentucky road whose funding Jackson vetoed?",
          "answer": "Maysville Road"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "SPANISH-AMERICAN WAR",
      "prompt": "During the Spanish-American War who or what was…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The American President who launched the war?",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "The European capital where the treaty ending the war was signed?",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "The naval battle in the Philippines where George Dewey defeated the Spanish fleet?",
          "answer": "Battle of Manila Bay"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Filipino independence leader who fought the US after the war?",
          "answer": "Emilio Famy Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "The rival of Joseph Pulitzer whose New York Journal rallied support for the war?",
          "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Assistant Secretary of the Navy at the start of the war, who was one of the Rough Riders?",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The 1898 battle in Cuba where the Rough Riders made their famous charge on Kettle Hill?",
          "answer": "San Juan Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "The nickname given to the African-American cavalry regiments that saw the hardest action at San Juan Hill?",
          "answer": "Buffalo Soldiers"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CONSTITUTIONAL CONVENTION",
      "prompt": "During the Constitutional Convention, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City hosted the meeting in Independence Hall?",
          "answer": "Philadelphia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presided over the meeting after leaving retirement at Mount Vernon?",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Pennsylvanian who came to the meetings in a sedan chair?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is known as the Father of the Constitution and took notes of the debates?",
          "answer": "James Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposal favoring the large states became the blueprint for the Constitution?",
          "answer": "Virginia Plan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor of Virginia from a famous family who did not sign the Constitution?",
          "answer": "Edmund Jennings Randolph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Competing plan that protected the rights of small states?",
          "answer": "New Jersey Plan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed the Connecticut Compromise, creating the House and Senate?",
          "answer": "Roger Sherman"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "WOODROW WILSON",
      "prompt": "Answer some questions about the Presidency of Woodrow Wilson:",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wilson was the first president from this party since Grover Cleveland.",
          "answer": "Democratic Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Along with Theodore Roosevelt, Wilson defeated this Republican incumbent in 1912.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "This Socialist candidate took 6% of the vote when Wilson was elected.",
          "answer": "Eugene Victor Debs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wilson signed legislation creating this central banking system.",
          "answer": "Federal Reserve"
        },
        {
          "question": "He restarted the practice of giving this annual message as a speech before Congress.",
          "answer": "State of the Union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Before his political career, Wilson was president of this Ivy League college.",
          "answer": "Princeton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Give the name of Wilson’s progressive agenda.",
          "answer": "The New Freedom"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wilson appointed this advocate of “sociological jurisprudence” known as “the People’s Lawyer” to the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "Louis Brandeis"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CIVIL WAR GENERALS",
      "prompt": "Which Civil War General…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Led the Army of Northern Virginia and lost at Gettysburg?",
          "answer": "Robert Edward Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "As Union general-in-chief received Confederate surrender at Appomattox?",
          "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was killed at Chancellorsville and earned a famous nickname after First Manassas?",
          "answer": "Thomas “Stonewall” Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Union to victory in the West with his destructive March to the Sea?",
          "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commanded the Army of the Potomac during the last stages of the war?",
          "answer": "George G. Meade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was replaced by Hood in the West and led the Confederate retreat after the fall of Atlanta?",
          "answer": "Joseph E. Johnston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a Confederate raid on Washington and helped found the Lost Cause interpretation?",
          "answer": "Jubal A. Early"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was nicknamed “Old Brains” and was the Union general-in-chief in the early war?",
          "answer": "Henry W. Halleck"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CENTURY",
      "prompt": "Which Supreme Court case…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Desegregated public schools?",
          "answer": "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created a fundamental right to an abortion?",
          "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruled banning interracial marriage unconstitutional?",
          "answer": "Loving v. Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Upheld the internment of Japanese-Americans?",
          "answer": "Korematsu v. United States"
        },
        {
          "question": "Created a right to privacy?",
          "answer": "Griswold v. Connecticut"
        },
        {
          "question": "Upheld parental notification but struck down spousal notification laws for abortion in 1992?",
          "answer": "Planned Parenthood v. Casey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Excluded illegally obtained evidence from trials?",
          "answer": "Mapp v. Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Guaranteed “liberty of contract” against state regulation and involved bakers’ working hours?",
          "answer": "Lochner v. New York"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1968",
      "prompt": "In the year 1968, who or what…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the President of the United States who did not seek re-election because of the unpopularity of the Vietnam War?",
          "answer": "Lyndon Baines Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was shot after the California Democratic primary in a hotel by Sirhan Sirhan?",
          "answer": "Robert Francis Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the group of protesters controversially arrested and put on trial for their actions at that Democratic National Convention?",
          "answer": "Chicago Seven"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the manned space mission that became the first to orbit the Moon?",
          "answer": "Apollo 8"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the March massacre in which US army soldiers killed over 400 villagers in South Vietnam?",
          "answer": "My Lai massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was city in which Martin Luther King Jr was assassinated?",
          "answer": "Memphis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the European city that saw massive student protests and strikes in May?",
          "answer": "Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the US Navy ship captured by North Korea, whose crew was held prisoner for 11 months?",
          "answer": "USS Pueblo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reconstruction",
      "prompt": "In America’s Reconstruction period, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "War that it followed.",
          "answer": "American Civil War"
        },
        {
          "question": "President, unpopular for his leniency to the South, who was impeached in 1868.",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historian who wrote Black Reconstruction in America and The Souls of Black Folk and debated Booker T. Washington.",
          "answer": "W.E.B. Du Bois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment that protected the right to vote, regardless of race.",
          "answer": "15th"
        },
        {
          "question": "Perjorative term for Southern whites who supported Reconstruction efforts.",
          "answer": "scalawags"
        },
        {
          "question": "State ruled by the first African-American governor, P. B. S. Pinchback.",
          "answer": "Louisiana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two farming needs promised to ex-slaves by the Freedmen’s Bureau.",
          "answer": [
            "forty acres and a mule",
            "in either order"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kansas senator featured in Profiles in Courage for voting against the President’s impeachment.",
          "answer": "Edmund Ross"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Reincarnation",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where reincarnation-believing religions like Hinduism and Jainism were founded.",
          "answer": "Republic of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary medieval king who will be reincarnated as England’s savior.",
          "answer": "King Arthur Pendragon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mesoamerican people whose soul-preserving mummies were destroyed by Francisco Pizarro.",
          "answer": "Incas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Apple CEO who allegedly believed himself a reincarnated World War II fighter pilot.",
          "answer": "Steve Jobs"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former leader of North Korea said to be a reincarnation of his father, Il-Sung.",
          "answer": "Kim Jong-Il"
        },
        {
          "question": "Town in Guyana where 909 Americans died “drinking the Kool-Aid” of a claimed Christ reincarnate.",
          "answer": "Jonestown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas city in which David Koresh, another self-proclaimed Christ, was killed in an ATF siege on the Branch Davidian complex.",
          "answer": "Waco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religion that describes reincarnation in the Kitab al-Hikma.",
          "answer": "Druze"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Watergate",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who resigned after the Watergate scandal.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who claimed “our long national nightmare is over” after succeeding Nixon as President.",
          "answer": "Gerald Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper for which Woodward and Bernstein investigated the story.",
          "answer": "Washington Post"
        },
        {
          "question": "Codenamed source, a former CIA admin, that provided Woodward and Bernstein with important leaks.",
          "answer": [
            "Deep Throat",
            "W. Mark Felt"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Fundraising organization led by John Mitchell that funded that Watergate burglars’ defense fund.",
          "answer": "Committee for the Re-Election of the President"
        },
        {
          "question": "1973 event in which the Attorney General and Deputy Attorney General resigned, rather than fire Special Prosecutor Archibald Cox.",
          "answer": "Saturday Night Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "British journalist who paid hundreds of thousands of dollars to interview the resigned President in 1977.",
          "answer": "David Frost"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House Chief of Staff who assisted in the cover-up and resigned in April 1973.",
          "answer": [
            "Harry Robbins “Bob”",
            "H.R. Haldeman"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American Expansion",
      "prompt": "In the history of American land acquisition, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French emperor who sold Louisiana to America.",
          "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northernmost state in New England, whose border was clarified by the Webster-Ashburton Treaty.",
          "answer": "Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that marks the border between the US and Mexico between El Paso and the Gulf of Mexico.",
          "answer": "Rio Grande or Rio Bravo del Norte"
        },
        {
          "question": "46th state admitted to the Union, having been an unorganized Indian Territory until the early 20th century.",
          "answer": "Oklahoma"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who signed the bill officially annexing Texas.",
          "answer": "James K. Polk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caribbean island group purchased from Denmark just before the U.S. entered World War I.",
          "answer": "U.S. Virgin Islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "1819 treaty with Spain that gave Florida to the U.S.",
          "answer": "Adams-Onis Treaty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Price, within 10%, that the U.S. paid to Russia to purchase “Seward’s Folly.”",
          "answer": [
            "$7,200,000",
            "any answer between $6,480,000 and $7,920,000"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Confederacy",
      "prompt": "In the history of the Confederate States of America, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Year in which it lost the Civil War.",
          "answer": "1865"
        },
        {
          "question": "First state to secede from the Union, where the first shots of the war were fired at Fort Sumter.",
          "answer": "South Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederate general who surrendered to General Grant at Appomattox.",
          "answer": "Robert E. Lee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederacy’s first and only President.",
          "answer": "Jefferson Davis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Georgia park where those two aforementioned men, as well as Stonewall Jackson, are carved on the face of a rock dome.",
          "answer": "Stone Mountain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union plan, devised by Winfield Scott, to blockade Confederate ports.",
          "answer": "Anaconda Plan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederacy’s first and only Vice President.",
          "answer": "Alexander H. Stephens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Captured British vessel on which James Mason and John Slidell tried to sail to Europe to gain international recognition for the CSA.",
          "answer": [
            "RMS Trent",
            "Trent Affair"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Spanish-American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Future U.S. President who led the Rough Riders in Cuba.",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "American battleship sunk in Havana harbor, leading to the declaration of war.",
          "answer": "USS Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "1898 treaty that ended the war.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Paris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacific island, still a US territory with capital Hagatna, ceded by Spain after the war.",
          "answer": "Guam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodore who led the American fleet to victory at Manila Bay.",
          "answer": "George Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Newspaper published by William Randolph Hearst, a rival of Pulitzer’s New York World, which “furnished the war” via yellow journalism.",
          "answer": "New York Journal"
        },
        {
          "question": "First President of the Philippines, who originally fought with the Americans against the Spanish, but was captured in 1901 during the Philippine-American War.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorado senator whose namesake amendment, passed prior to the war, required the U.S. to help Cuba gain independence, then leave without annexing it.",
          "answer": [
            "Henry Teller",
            "Teller Amendment"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Native Americans",
      "prompt": "Which Native American tribe or ethnic group...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Inspired the name of the capital of Wyoming?",
          "answer": "Cheyenne"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was scouted for “code talkers” like Chester Nez during World War II?",
          "answer": "Navajo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is divided into Santee, Yankton, and Lakota groups?",
          "answer": "Sioux"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had a syllabary invented by Sequoyah?",
          "answer": "Cherokee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fought three wars in Florida, the first two against Andrew Jackson?",
          "answer": "Seminole"
        },
        {
          "question": "Includes groups like the Zuni and Hopi and was named by the Spanish for the adobe buildings they lived in?",
          "answer": "Pueblo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave its name to a downslope wind common off the Rockies in the Great Plains, which can cause rapid temperature changes?",
          "answer": "Chinook"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the easternmost member of the Five Nations and was led by Joseph Brant?",
          "answer": "Mohawk"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "A War Within a War",
      "prompt": "Which conflict...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Included bombing of the Ho Chi Minh trail as part of the larger Cold War?",
          "answer": "Vietnam War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was in part triggered by the smaller Bear Flag Revolt in California?",
          "answer": "Mexican-American War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included British troops fighting in Spain as part of the Napoleonic Wars?",
          "answer": "Peninsular War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was named for the lack of fighting on the Western Front during the early stages of World War 2?",
          "answer": "Phoney War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included the smaller Tanker War and the use of chemical weapons at Halabja?",
          "answer": "Iran-Iraq War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the North American theater of the War of Spanish Succession and was named for a monarch?",
          "answer": "Queen Anne’s War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a revolt against Mazarin and Louis XIV during the Franco-Spanish War?",
          "answer": "the Fronde"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included smaller wars such as the Hannibal War and War of Mantuan Succession?",
          "answer": "Thirty Year’s War"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "NAFTA",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Economic concept supported by NAFTA, making up the “FT” in the name.",
          "answer": "free trade"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who signed NAFTA into law in 1993.",
          "answer": "Bill Clinton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed agreement between Pacific Rim countries, approved in October 2015, that would supersede some NAFTA agreements.",
          "answer": [
            "Trans-Pacific Partnership",
            "TPP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Third party Presidential candidate who warned that NAFTA would create a “giant sucking sound” of jobs going south.",
          "answer": "H. Ross Perot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican political party whose president, Carlos Salinas, supported NAFTA.",
          "answer": [
            "Institutional Revolutionary Party",
            "Partido Revolucionario Institucional",
            "PRI"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican militant group that declared war against Mexico over the feared sale of Native American land under NAFTA.",
          "answer": [
            "Zapatistas or Zapatista Army of National Liberation",
            "Ejercito Zapatista de Leberacion Nacional",
            "EZLN"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican factories that boomed after NAFTA reduced tariffs on importing raw material.",
          "answer": "maquiladoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Canadian Prime Minister who signed NAFTA and rejected the Meech Lake and Charlottetown Accords.",
          "answer": "Brian Mulroney"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Alamo",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern U.S. state whose Sam Houston-led revolution against Mexico included the Battle of the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home city of the Alamo.",
          "answer": "San Antonio de B´exar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican General whose forces defeated the Alamo’s defenders.",
          "answer": "Antonio L´opez de Santa Anna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee Congressman and frontiersman who died defending the Alamo.",
          "answer": "David “Davy” Crockett"
        },
        {
          "question": "Actor who portrayed that frontiersman in 1960’s The Alamo and Rooster Cogburn in True Grit, two of his dozens of Westerns.",
          "answer": "John Wayne or Marion Morrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Knife enthusiast who commanded the Alamo defenders and was ill during the battle, dying while fighting from his cot.",
          "answer": [
            "James Bowie",
            "Bowie knife"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Town where POWs were massacred 3 weeks after the fall of the Alamo, inspiring a similar cry to “Remember!”",
          "answer": "Goliad Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mass evacuation of settlers from the oncoming Mexican army, led by Sam Houston after the fall of the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Runaway Scrape"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cuba",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Cuba, where the USS Maine was sunk.",
          "answer": "Havana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who led Cuba through the second half of the 20th century. His brother, R´aul, is currently president.",
          "answer": "Fidel Castro"
        },
        {
          "question": "Weapons stationed on Cuba by the Soviet Union in 1962 to threaten the United States.",
          "answer": "ballistic missiles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of economic action taken by the United States to prevent trade with Cuba.",
          "answer": "embargo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted 1961 invasion by CIA-backed rebels, driven off by the Cuban government.",
          "answer": [
            "Bay of Pigs Invasion",
            "descriptions of the invasion of Playa Giron"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Marxist revolutionary, instrumental in the 1959 Cuban revolution, who also aided movements in the Congo and Bolivia.",
          "answer": [
            "Che Guevara",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator overthrown in the 1959 Cuban Revolution.",
          "answer": "Fulgencio Batista"
        },
        {
          "question": "1901 amendment that granted the United States the right to dominate Cuban politics.",
          "answer": "Platt Amendment"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The U.S. in World War I",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Second-to-last year of the war, in which the U.S. finally joined the fighting?",
          "answer": "1917"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prior American policy of not officially supporting either side, also held by Switzerland.",
          "answer": [
            "neutrality",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of vehicle operated by “Aces” such as Eddie Rickenbacker and the German Red Baron.",
          "answer": [
            "aircraft",
            "airplanes",
            "fighters"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Note sent by Germany proposing an anti-American alliance with Mexico.",
          "answer": "Zimmerman Telegram"
        },
        {
          "question": "Secretary of State who resigned in 1915, years after delivering the “Cross of Gold” speech?",
          "answer": "William Jennings Bryan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man, nicknamed “Black Jack,” who led the American Expeditionary Force.",
          "answer": "John Pershing"
        },
        {
          "question": "Slang term that described A.E.F. infantrymen and marines and was eventually superseded by “GIs” in World War II.",
          "answer": "Doughboys"
        },
        {
          "question": "Businessman who oversaw the War Industries Board to oversee American military preparedness.",
          "answer": "Bernard Baruch"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Organized Labor in the US",
      "prompt": "In the history of organized labor in America, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Industry’s workers were led by Walter Reuther in the UAW?",
          "answer": [
            "automotive industry",
            "car manufacturing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Number of hours in a workday was won by unions, creating the forty-hour workweek?",
          "answer": "eight-hour day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union merged with the Congress of Industrial Organizations, or CIO, in 1955?",
          "answer": "AFL"
        },
        {
          "question": "Does the “I” stand for in the name of the William Heywood’s, union, the IWW?",
          "answer": [
            "industrial",
            "Industrial Workers of the World"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President’s veto was overridden by Congress to pass the union-restricting Taft-Hartley Act?",
          "answer": "Harry Truman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Union was led by Terence Powderly and Uriah Stephens and peaked in the 1880s?",
          "answer": [
            "Knights of Labor",
            "KoL",
            "K of L"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Objects were produced by an International Union once led by Samuel Gompers?",
          "answer": "cigars"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of contract, forbidding union membership, was outlawed by the Norris-LaGuardia Act?",
          "answer": "yellow-dog contracts"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Constitutional Amendments",
      "prompt": "Which Constitutional amendment...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Protects freedoms of speech and exercise of religion?",
          "answer": "1st Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Protects against cruel and unusual punishment, but not the death penalty?",
          "answer": "8th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Includes the Due Process Clause and Citizenship Clause and was passed during Reconstruction?",
          "answer": "14th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Responded to Vietnam War criticism by lowering the voting age?",
          "answer": "26th Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inspired by Franklin Roosevelt’s unprecedented fourth electoral victory?",
          "answer": "22nd Amendment number is required"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the subject of D.C. vs. Heller and McDonald v. Chicago this century?",
          "answer": "2nd Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was revived by student Gregory Watson in 1982, then ratified in 1992? Description or number acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "27th Amendment",
            "descriptions of “delaying Congressional pay raises until after the next election”",
            "“Congresspeople can’t give themselves raises”"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended a process that was defended in Federalist Paper No. 62 as a “double advantage” linking state and federal governments? Description or number acceptable.",
          "answer": [
            "17th Amendment",
            "descriptions of “requiring direct election of Senators”"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Robert Walpole",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Position, the head of the British government, that Walpole was the first to hold in 1721.",
          "answer": [
            "Prime Minister",
            "PM"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Name shared by the two British monarchs served by Walpole, the first two to take the name.",
          "answer": "George I and/or II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prominent tower where Walpole was imprisoned by his political enemies.",
          "answer": "Tower of London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Residence that Walpole bequeathed to his political successors.",
          "answer": "10 Downing Street"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party to which Walpole belonged. They opposed the Tories and the concept of absolute monarchy.",
          "answer": "Whig Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Position held by Walpole as a junior minister, equivalent to America’s Secretary of the Treasury.",
          "answer": "Chancellor of the Exchequer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Credit bubble that occurred during Walpole’s rule, as a joint-stock company for trade in South America crashed.",
          "answer": "South Sea Bubble"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political subdivision that elected Walpole to Parliament. Walpole’s was a “pocket” kind, where he controlled over half the voters in the subdivision.",
          "answer": "pocket borough"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Plessy v. Ferguson",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State in which Plessy was arrested for occupying a whites-only railcar in New Orleans.",
          "answer": "Louisiana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three-word phrase for the Plessy-approved form of segregation.",
          "answer": "separate but equal"
        },
        {
          "question": "1954 case that overturned Plessy.",
          "answer": "Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civil rights activist who repeated Plessy’s crime on a Montgomery bus on December 1, 1955.",
          "answer": "Rosa Parks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law clerk who wrote a “Random Thought” supporting Plessy in 1952 and later became Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "William Rehnquist"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only Justice who dissented in Plessy.",
          "answer": "John Marshall Harlan I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Clause of the 14th Amendment, immediately following the Due Process clause, interpreted in Plessy.",
          "answer": [
            "Equal Protection Clause",
            "descriptive answers that use forms of those two words"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Judge and lawyer who argued for Plessy before the Supreme Court and coined the legal term “color blind.”",
          "answer": "Albion Tourg´ee"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Maine",
      "prompt": "In the history of Maine, what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Other state, the site of Lexington and Concord, originally controlled Maine’s territory?",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "War, the colonial phase of the Seven Years’ War, included a raid on Woolwich, Maine?",
          "answer": "French and Indian War"
        },
        {
          "question": "1863 Civil War battle included the defense of Little Round Top by the 20th Maine?",
          "answer": "Battle of Gettysburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "WarwascausedbyaborderdisputeinvolvingMaineloggersandwasendedbytheWebster-Ashburton Treaty?",
          "answer": "Aroostook War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Industry included the Lewiston-Auburn strike and the development of mills in Freeport?",
          "answer": [
            "textile industry",
            "clothing industry",
            "shoemaking",
            "garment manufacturing"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician was nicknamed the “magnetic man” and the “continental liar from the state of Maine?”",
          "answer": "James Gillespie Blaine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Female senator from Maine delivered the anti-McCarthyist “Declaration of Conscience” speech?",
          "answer": [
            "Margaret Chase Smith",
            "either underlined name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Native American peoples, whose name calls their home “Dawnland,” once lived in present-day Maine?",
          "answer": [
            "Wabanaki Peoples",
            "Abenaki Peoples"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Figures in Philippine History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Former Mayor of Davao City and current President of the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Rodrigo Duterte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Combat sport mastered by Filipino Senator Manny Pacquiao [pack-ee-ow].",
          "answer": [
            "boxing",
            "word forms, like boxer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Fashion item of which former First Lady Imelda Marcos collected hundreds of pairs.",
          "answer": "shoes"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who led during the Spanish-American War and retained the Philippines thereafter.",
          "answer": "William McKinley"
        },
        {
          "question": "First President of the Philippines, who fought until 1901 against the United States.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary author of Noli Me Tangere who was executed in 1896 by the Spanish.",
          "answer": "Jos´e Rizal"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female President, who succeeded Ferdinand Marcos after the People Power Revolution.",
          "answer": "Corazon Aquino"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second female President, who was acquitted of lottery theft in 2016.",
          "answer": "Gloria Macapagal Arroyo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First country the US declared war on, doing so in 1812.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland",
            "Great Britain",
            "England"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Military title assigned to the President in the Constitution as head of the armed forces.",
          "answer": "Commander-in-Chief do not"
        },
        {
          "question": "Article of the Constitution that details the President’s powers and roles, including that title.",
          "answer": "Article 2 of the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cuban naval base used by the US to detain terror suspects and enemy combatants.",
          "answer": [
            "Guantanamo Bay Naval Base",
            "Gitmo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial 1973 law that restricts the President’s power to deploy armed troops beyond 60 days.",
          "answer": "War Powers Act or Resolution, Law, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Writ that prevents unlawful detention but was suspended unlawfully by Abraham Lincoln during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "writ of habeas corpus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Yugoslavian country, unrecognized by Serbia, whose 1999 bombing led Tom Campbell to sue Bill Clinton.",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        },
        {
          "question": "1952 Supreme Court case that limited President Truman’s ability to seize private property during war.",
          "answer": [
            "Youngstown Sheet and Tube Company vs. Sawyer",
            "Youngstown Steel case",
            "Steel Seizure case"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "U.S.-French Relations",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1803 land purchase in which the U.S. acquired much of the Midwest.",
          "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for ceasing trade to a foreign nation, as the U.S. did to France with an 1807 act.",
          "answer": [
            "embargo",
            "Embargo Act"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1797 incident in which bribes were demanded of three American diplomats.",
          "answer": "XYZ Affair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, a defeat for John Burgoyne in the Revolutionary War, that convinced France to support the American Revolution.",
          "answer": "Battle of Saratoga"
        },
        {
          "question": "American politician who co-names an 1928 anti-war pact with French minister Aristide Briand.",
          "answer": "Frank Kellogg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial 18th century French “citizen” ambassador who wanted to bring America into war with Britain.",
          "answer": "Edmond-Charles Genet"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unofficial war between the U.S. and France that was ended by the Conventions of 1800.",
          "answer": "Quasi War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomat who negotiated a loan from France to the Confederacy and who was captured along with James Mason in the Trent Affair.",
          "answer": "John Slidell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Governors of New York",
      "prompt": "Name the governor of New York who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Became President in 1933 and championed the New Deal.",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was nicknamed “Old Kinderhook” and succeeded Andrew Jackson as President.",
          "answer": "Martin Van Buren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was also the first Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a former Mafia prosecutor and unexpectedly lost a presidential election to Harry Truman.",
          "answer": "Thomas Dewey"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fathered the current governor, Andrew, and gave a keynote address at the 1984 DNC.",
          "answer": "Mario Cuomo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became Vice President under Gerald Ford and led a wing of moderate Republicans.",
          "answer": "Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Inaugurated the Erie Canal and unsuccessfully challenged James Madison for the presidency.",
          "answer": "DeWitt Clinton"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated Rutherford B. Hayes in the popular vote, but not the Electoral College, in 1876.",
          "answer": "Samuel J. Tilden"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Redistricting",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Number of Congressional districts in the US, equal to the size of the House of Representatives.",
          "answer": "435"
        },
        {
          "question": "Practice, named after a Massachusetts Senator, of redistricting to favor a particular party.",
          "answer": "gerrymandering"
        },
        {
          "question": "Justice, the first woman on the Supreme Court, whose opinion in Shaw v. Reno established strict scrutiny for racial redistricting.",
          "answer": "Sandra Day O’Connor"
        },
        {
          "question": "State, governed by Roy Cooper, where a federal court struck down a district map on partisan, rather than racial, grounds in 2018.",
          "answer": "North Carolina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chief Justice who first ruled on redistricting issues, as well as Brown v. Board of Education.",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "1965 act whose Section Five required states with histories of discrimination to clear redistricting maps with the Department of Justice.",
          "answer": "Voting Rights Act of 1965"
        },
        {
          "question": "2013 Supreme Court case that weakened Section 5 preclearance and originated in an Alabama county.",
          "answer": "Shelby County v. Holder"
        },
        {
          "question": "1962 Supreme Court case that decided redistricting was not a political question and could be ruled upon.",
          "answer": "Baker vs. Carr or Carr vs. Baker"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Western Expansion",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Third US President, who bought the Louisiana Purchase.",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Territory, now a state with capital Salem, whose northern border was disputed with Britain.",
          "answer": [
            "Oregon Territory",
            "state"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Concept,whosenamewascoinedbyJohnSullivan,thatarguedwesternexpansionwasapredetermined right.",
          "answer": "Manifest Destiny"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 act that gave western settlers land plots if they farmed the land for five years.",
          "answer": "Homestead Act of 1862"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which the French and Indian War ended and a Proclamation banning expansion beyond the Appalachians was issued.",
          "answer": "Proclamation of 1763"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to those who settled Oklahoma Unassigned Lands before the official proclamation.",
          "answer": "Sooners"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historian whose Frontier Theory argued that American democracy developed through western expansion.",
          "answer": "Frederick Jackson Turner"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican-American war general whose namesake code governed the New Mexico territory and who served as military governor of California.",
          "answer": "Stephen Kearney"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "US Presidents Before They Were Presidents",
      "prompt": "Concerning pre-Presidential careers, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President who served as a Five-Star General during World War II.",
          "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who defeated Tenskwatawa [tensk-wah-ta-wah] at Tippecanoe and used the victory in his campaign slogan.",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was a Governor of Arkansas and ran with a Tennessee Senator, Al Gore.",
          "answer": [
            "William Jefferson “Bill” Clinton",
            "William Jefferson Blythe"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Home state of Senator Warren Harding and Governor Rutherford B. Hayes.",
          "answer": "Ohio"
        },
        {
          "question": "Asian country where William Howard Taft served as governor-general from 1901 to 1903.",
          "answer": "The Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who helped write the Ostend Manifesto as Ambassador to Great Britain.",
          "answer": "James Buchanan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political boss who helped Harry Truman with a political machine based in Kansas City.",
          "answer": "Thomas Pendergast"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political group that dominated the New York legislature in the 1820s under Martin van Buren.",
          "answer": "Albany Regency"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Antebellum Disputes over Slavery",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "“Bleeding” state that co-names an 1854 act with Nebraska.",
          "answer": "Bleeding Kansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-slavery crusader who committed the Pottawatomie Massacre and raided Harper’s Ferry.",
          "answer": "John Brown"
        },
        {
          "question": "President, known as “Old Rough and Ready,” whose death led to the passage of the Compromise of 1850.",
          "answer": "Zachary Taylor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Concept, supported by Stephen Douglas, that states that the people of a state should decide if they want slavery.",
          "answer": "popular sovereignty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-slavery political party for whom Martin Van Buren unsuccessfully ran in 1848.",
          "answer": "Free Soil Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposal that would have banned slavery in land acquired in the Mexican-American War.",
          "answer": "Wilmot Proviso"
        },
        {
          "question": "1850 “bloodhound” law that was briefly ruled unconstitutional in Wisconsin, until the case of Abelman v. Booth.",
          "answer": "Fugitive Slave Act of 1850"
        },
        {
          "question": "Client of Robert Morris whose conviction under that act triggered a “vile procession” of 50,000 marchers in Boston.",
          "answer": "Anthony Burns"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Calvin Coolidge",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State Coolidge served as Governor.",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "President he succeeded after a fatal heart attack.",
          "answer": "Warren G. Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "French term for Coolidge’s “hands-off” economic philosophy.",
          "answer": "laissez-faire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which Coolidge was elected to a full term as President.",
          "answer": "1924"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leading third party candidate in that election, a senator who carried his home state of Wisconsin.",
          "answer": "Robert M. La Follette, Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Former UK ambassador who finished second in that election.",
          "answer": "John Davis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wealthy Secretary of the Treasury from Pittsburgh who Coolidge inherited from his predecessor.",
          "answer": "Andrew Mellon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who Coolidge appointed Attorney General and, later, to the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "Harlan Fiske Stone"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Suffragettes Around the World",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that gave American women the right to vote.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "American who was arrested for voting in the 1872 election and was briefly honored on American coinage.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deliverer of the “Ain’t I a Woman” speech, a former slave who was born Isabella Baumfree.",
          "answer": [
            "Sojourner Truth",
            "Isabella Baumfree if given before mentioned"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1848 meeting in New York at which the Declaration of Sentiments, calling for women’s suffrage, was issued.",
          "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Americans organized by Alice Paul who kept vigil outside the White House for 2.5 years.",
          "answer": "Silent Sentinels"
        },
        {
          "question": "British family of suffragettes that included Sylvia and Emmeline.",
          "answer": "Pankhurst family"
        },
        {
          "question": "British act that allowed suffragettes on hunger strikes to be released, then recaptured once they’d recovered",
          "answer": [
            "Cat and Mouse Act",
            "Prisoners Act of 1912"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Method by which British suffragette Emily Davison died in 1913, possibly suicidal and possibly in protest, in an accident at the Epsom Derby.",
          "answer": [
            "ran out onto the horse track and/or was hit by a passing racehorse",
            "either",
            "both underlined parts, and descriptions thereof"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Supreme Court Justices",
      "prompt": "Name the Supreme Court justice who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Currently serves as Chief Justice and was nominated by George W. Bush.",
          "answer": "John Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the only President to later serve on the court.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was Chief Justice during the Brown v Board case and switched parties in 1962.",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Issued the majority opinion in the Dred Scott case.",
          "answer": "Roger Taney , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Argued that the 14th Amendment “does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer’s Social Statics” in his Lochner dissent.",
          "answer": "Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned from the court in 1969 after bribery allegations led to impeachment hearings.",
          "answer": "Abe Fortas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote “I know it when I see it” in his opinion in Jacobellis v. Ohio, an obscenity trial.",
          "answer": "Potter Stewart Army Group South"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Central America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Project completed by the US across Panama, linking the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans.",
          "answer": "Panama Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sport whose FIFA World Cup qualifier instigated a brief war between El Salvador and Honduras.",
          "answer": [
            "soccer",
            "association football"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where a 19th century civil war led the capital to be moved from Cartago to San Jose.",
          "answer": "Costa Rica"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American country that controlled Panama, its neighbor, until American intervention.",
          "answer": "Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Panamanian dictator who was ousted by the US in 1989.",
          "answer": "Manuel Noriega"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial name of Belize from 1862 to 1973, reflecting its European controllers.",
          "answer": "British Honduras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central American country where the US carried out Operation PBSUCCESS.",
          "answer": "Guatemala"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictatorial family that was overthrown by the Sandinistas.",
          "answer": "Somoza family"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Polish Military....",
      "prompt": "Name the the polish military.......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was overwhelmed by the Blitzkrieg at the start of what war?",
          "answer": "World War II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sought to prevent the country’s partitioning by what “great” tsarina of Russia?",
          "answer": [
            "Catherine the Great",
            "Catherine II"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated what Germanic crusading order at the 1410 Battle of Grunwald?",
          "answer": [
            "Teutonic Knights or the Teutonic Order",
            "the Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Faced the Khmelnytsky [kem-ill-nitz-kee] Uprising against what horseriding people based near the Don river?",
          "answer": "Cossacks"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lifted a 1683 siege of what foreign capital city after the arrival of Jan III Sobieski’s hussars?",
          "answer": "Vienna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had its officers targeted and buried in a mass grave in a forest in what 1940 massacre by the NKVD?",
          "answer": "Katyn Forest massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent what officer, who died at the Siege of Savannah, to reform the American cavalry during the Revolutionary War?",
          "answer": "Casimir Pulaski"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sent what engineer of West Point to aid the American Revolution? He later led an uprising against Russia.",
          "answer": "Tadeusz Kosciuszko , but be lenient"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Conflict with Native Americans",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1876 battle where George Custer was killed in Montana.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Little Bighorn or Battle of the Greasy Grass"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lakota Sioux leader at that battle, where he joined with Crazy Horse. He was killed by American police in 1890.",
          "answer": "Sitting Bull or Thathanka Iyotake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Shawnee leader who allied with Britain during the War of 1812 and was killed at the Battle of the Thames.",
          "answer": "Tecumseh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious movement promoted by Wovoka, which sought to bring peace through the spirits of the dead.",
          "answer": "Ghost Dance movement"
        },
        {
          "question": "1670s war, named for a Wampanoag chief, in New England in which several thousand people were killed.",
          "answer": "King Philip’s War or Metacomet’s War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottawa chief who led a 1760s rebellion against the British, besieging Fort Detroit.",
          "answer": [
            "Pontiac",
            "Obwandiyag"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1630s war that wiped out a New England tribe and included the Mystic Massacre.",
          "answer": "Pequot War"
        },
        {
          "question": "1794 battle where Little Turtle and Blue Jacket’s alliance was defeated near the Maumee River.",
          "answer": "Battle of Fallen Timbers"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "American Journalists",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival of ABC and NBC whose Evening News was anchored by Walter Cronkite.",
          "answer": [
            "CBS",
            "Columbia Broadcasting System"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Publisher of the New York World and namesake of annual prizes for journalism, literature, and music.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph Pulitzer",
            "Pulitzer Prize"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Owner of the New York Journal and rival of that publisher, famous for “providing” the Spanish- American War with yellow journalism.",
          "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
        },
        {
          "question": "Either of the authors of All the President’s Men who investigated Watergate for the Washington Post.",
          "answer": "Bob Woodward and/or Carl Bernstein"
        },
        {
          "question": "German-born publisher who was acquitted of libel in New York in 1735.",
          "answer": "John Peter Zenger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muckraker whose flash photographs were collected in How the Other Half Lives.",
          "answer": "Jacob Riis"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Sage of Baltimore,” a satirist who covered the Scopes Trial",
          "answer": "Henry Louis “H.L.” Mencken"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-founder of the NAACP who researched lynching in Memphis until a white mob burned down her office.",
          "answer": "Ida B. Wells"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "America’s Westward Expansion",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nickname for California gold rushers, based on the second year of the rush.",
          "answer": "49ers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived mail carrier service that employed hundreds of horses to make quick exchanges between stations.",
          "answer": "Pony Express"
        },
        {
          "question": "Phrase coined by John O’Sullivan to advocate the annexation of Texas, as it was America’s divine right to control the continent.",
          "answer": "manifest destiny"
        },
        {
          "question": "1862 law that granted millions of acres to small farmers, commonly 160 acres at a time.",
          "answer": "Homestead Act or Law, etc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Ranching equipment, developed by Joseph Glidden, that made enclosure of grazing land possible.",
          "answer": "barbed wire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Firearms company whose Model 1873 rifle was the “Gun that Won the West.”",
          "answer": [
            "Winchester Repeating Arms Company",
            "descriptions of Winchester rifles"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "TheoryproposedbyFrederickJacksonTurnertoexplainchangesindemocracyasAmericanexpansion progressed.",
          "answer": "Frontier thesis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fur trapper and colleague of John Fremont who led thousands of Navajo on the forced “Long Walk” to Bosque Redondo.",
          "answer": "Christopher “Kit” Carson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "John Marshall",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State he represented in Congress; its other Congressmen included James Madison.",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cabinet position he held under John Adams, for whom he negotiated an end to the Quasi War.",
          "answer": "Secretary of State"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who supposedly ranted “Marshall has made his decision, now let him enforce it!” after Worcester v Georgia.",
          "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legal principle established by Marshall’s decision in Marbury v Madison, allowing the Court to deem laws unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "judicial review"
        },
        {
          "question": "Institution deemed constitutional by Marshall in McCulloch v. Maryland.",
          "answer": [
            "a national bank",
            "Second Bank of the United States"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "New Hampshire college whose trustees sued the state for breach of contract; Daniel Webster’s moving speech persuaded Marshall.",
          "answer": [
            "Dartmouth College",
            "Trustees of Dartmouth College v. Woodward"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1810 case relating to the Yazoo land scandal, the first time a state law was ruled unconstitutional.",
          "answer": "Fletcher v. Peck"
        },
        {
          "question": "1833 case that ruled the Bill of Rights did not apply to the states, only the federal government.",
          "answer": "Barron v. Baltimore"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colonial Women",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Wife of John Adams, who advised him “Remember the ladies...”",
          "answer": "Abigail Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "First First Lady of the United States, who oversaw Mount Vernon.",
          "answer": "Martha Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "First English child born in the New World; she disappeared with the Roanoke Colony.",
          "answer": "Virginia Dare"
        },
        {
          "question": "Seamstress who legendarily made the first American flag.",
          "answer": [
            "Elizabeth “Betsy” Ross",
            "Elizabeth Griscom",
            "Elizabeth Ashburn",
            "Elizabeth Claypoole"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname of a woman, probably Mary Ludwig Hays, who heroically assisted at the Battle of Monmouth.",
          "answer": "Molly Pitcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Freed slave and poet who met “his Excellence, George Washington” in 1776.",
          "answer": "Phillis Wheatley"
        },
        {
          "question": "British spy who assisted her husband, Benedict Arnold, in his plot to betray West Point.",
          "answer": "Margaret “Peggy” Shippen"
        },
        {
          "question": "Quaker who was hanged in June 1660 after a brief staged reprieve, becoming the third Boston Martyr to be executed.",
          "answer": "Mary Dyer"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Philippines Independence",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country from which the Philippines declared its independence in 1898.",
          "answer": "Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-European country that gained the Philippines from that country and controlled it until 1946.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "USA",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1946 treaty, signed in the Philippine capital, granting independence.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Manila"
        },
        {
          "question": "First civilian governor of the Philippines, serving from 1901 to 1903; he later served as President.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary republic, named for a Philippine language, that fought for independence.",
          "answer": "Tagalog Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who served as first President of the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Emilio Aguinaldo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim-majority ethnic group that fought a fourteen-year insurgency in the southern Philippines.",
          "answer": [
            "Moro people",
            "Moro Rebellion, Insurgency, etc."
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret independence movement that formed after Jos´e Rizal was exiled.",
          "answer": "Katipunan"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "20th Century US Vice Presidents",
      "prompt": "Name the Vice President who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Supposedly “invented” the Internet before serving under Bill Clinton.",
          "answer": "Albert Gore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became President after fighting with the Rough Riders in Cuba.",
          "answer": "Theodore Roosevelt or Teddy Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Became President after the death of Warren Harding.",
          "answer": "Calvin Coolidge"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served under Dwight Eisenhower.",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned in 1973 for tax evasion, after which he was replaced with Gerald Ford.",
          "answer": "Spiro Agnew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was appointed in 1974 to serve under Ford.",
          "answer": "Nelson Rockefeller"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served FDR for eight years and legendarily said the Vice Presidency was “not worth a bucket of warm spit.”",
          "answer": "John Nance Garner"
        },
        {
          "question": "Devised a German reparations plan in 1925.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles Dawes",
            "Dawes Plan"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Political Cartoons",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Company, founded by John Rockefeller, that was depicted as a giant octopus destroying Washington, DC.",
          "answer": "Standard Oil Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founding Father who created the “Join, or Die” cartoon of a segmented snake.",
          "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
        },
        {
          "question": "1807 Act represented as “this cursed Ograbme” biting a merchant.",
          "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boss of Tammany Hall who was depicted with a money bag for a head in one cartoon.",
          "answer": "William Magear “Boss” Tweed"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who created that cartoon, many others attacking Tammany Hall, and the elephant symbol for the GOP.",
          "answer": "Thomas Nast"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York-based political magazine that employed that cartoonist and thoroughly covered the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Harper’s Weekly, A Journal of Civilization"
        },
        {
          "question": "Three word name of a William Charles cartoon attacking the Hartford Convention.",
          "answer": "LEAP NO LEAP"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cartoonist for the Washington Post who coined the term McCarthyism.",
          "answer": [
            "Herbert Lawrence Block",
            "Herblock"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ohio Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the politician from Ohio who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Died 31 days after giving his presidential inauguration address in 1841.",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was assassinated in 1881 by Charles Guiteau.",
          "answer": "James Garfield"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served in the Senate after flying in space as a member of the Mercury Seven.",
          "answer": "John Glenn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Authored an 1890 Antitrust Act and was the brother of William Tecumseh.",
          "answer": "John Sherman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Served as Treasury Secretary and Chief Justice in the 1860s.",
          "answer": "Salmon Chase"
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-sponsored a 1947 anti-union act with Fred Hartley.",
          "answer": "Robert Taft, Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Managed William McKinley’s presidential campaigns and served in the Senate from 1897 to 1904.",
          "answer": "Mark Hanna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sponsored a 1900 act that created a popular government in Puerto Rico, whose residents became American citizens.",
          "answer": [
            "Joseph Foraker",
            "Foraker Act"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Women’s Suffrage",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US constitutional amendment that guarantees women’s suffrage.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who eventually supported suffrage as a key to winning World War I.",
          "answer": "Thomas Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette who was arrested for voting in 1872 and charged a $100 fine by Ward Hunt.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York city where that woman tried to vote.",
          "answer": "Rochester"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group led by Alice Paul that picketed the White House for suffrage; its members were tortured in prison.",
          "answer": "Silent Sentinels"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pacifist Montana representative who was the first woman in Congress.",
          "answer": "Jeannette Rankin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Populist Party chairwoman who was President of the WCTU for 20 years.",
          "answer": "Frances Willard"
        },
        {
          "question": "1875 Supreme Court case that ended the “new departure” strategy by ruling the Constitution didn’t give anyone the right to vote.",
          "answer": "Minor v. Happersett"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mexican Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Commander of the Division del Norte who led a 1916 raid on Columbus, New Mexico.",
          "answer": [
            "Francisco “Pancho” Villa",
            "Jos´e Doroteo Arango Ar´ambula"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President, advised by the cientificos, who was challenged by Francisco Madero as the target of the initial rebellion in 1910.",
          "answer": "Jos´e de la Cruz Porfirio Diaz Mori"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebel from Morelos who led an agrarian movement and who names a modern militant group.",
          "answer": [
            "Emiliano Zapata Salazar",
            "Zapatistas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "February 1913 event in which violent chaos erupted after the assassination of Madero.",
          "answer": [
            "Ten Tragic Days",
            "La Decena Tr´agica"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who rose to power after that February 1913 event; the Germans helped him flee a year later.",
          "answer": "Jos´e Victoriano Heurta M´arquez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man whose Constitutionalist Army ousted the previous answer; he was assassinated in the wake of the Plan of Agua Prieta.",
          "answer": "Jos´e Venustiano Carranza Garza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Plan written by Madero that attacked the legitimacy of the 1910 elections, triggering the revolution.",
          "answer": "Plan of San Luis de Potosi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Populist politician who declared state atheism and was in power at the start of the Cristero War.",
          "answer": "Francisco Plutarco Eli´as Calles Campuzano"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Presidential Inaugurations",
      "prompt": "Given the clue, name the president who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the first president to be inaugurated",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inaugurated two weeks after the U.S. Capitol was stormed by supporters of his predecessor",
          "answer": "Joseph \"Joe\" Biden, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Died thirty days into his term after catching pneumonia during his inauguration",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the latest president not to attend his successor’s inauguration",
          "answer": "Donald Trump"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the outgoing president who did not attend the inauguration of Ulysses S. Grant",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inaugurated minutes before the end of the Iran hostage crisis.",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Started a tradition of walking to the Capitol on inauguration day",
          "answer": "Jimmy Carter"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first president to be inaugurated in Washington, D.C",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1 Belgium"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Domestic Threats",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "White supremacist organization whose first grand wizard was Nathan Bedford Forrest",
          "answer": [
            "KKK",
            "Ku Klux Klan"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nonprofit organization focusing on reproductive health which had one of its clinics attacked in 2015 by Robert Lewis Dear, Jr.",
          "answer": "Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc."
        },
        {
          "question": "Extremist who worked with Terry Nichols to bomb the Murrah building in Oklahoma City",
          "answer": "Timothy McVeigh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Texas city where federal agents raided the Mount Carmel Center occupied by followers of David Koresh.",
          "answer": "Waco"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church bombed in Birmingham in 1963",
          "answer": "16th Street Baptist Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deadly Idaho standoff that started after U.S. Marshals attempted to arrest Randy Weaver",
          "answer": "Ruby Ridge incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Militant organization that organized the Days of Rage in response to the trial of the Chicago Seven",
          "answer": [
            "Weather Underground Organization",
            "the Weathermen"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Self-described far-left \"urban guerilla warfare group\" who kidnapped Patty Hearst in 1974",
          "answer": [
            "United Federated Forces of the Symbionese Liberation Army",
            "SLA 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Famous Native Americans",
      "prompt": "Name the Native American, First Nations, or Aboriginal leader who was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Daughter of Powhatan, also named Rebecca Rolfe and Matoaka",
          "answer": "Pocahontas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last member of the Patuxet who taught farming to the Pilgrims in New England",
          "answer": [
            "Squanto",
            "Tisquantum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Creator of the Cherokee Syllabary who was also known as George Guess",
          "answer": "Sequoyah"
        },
        {
          "question": "Apache medicine man who broke out of a reservation and was exiled to Florida",
          "answer": [
            "Geronimo",
            "Goyaale"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Metis leader and founder of Manitoba who led the Red River Rebellion",
          "answer": "Louis Riel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mohawk leader who founded the Iroquois with Deganawidah",
          "answer": "Hiawatha or Ayenwathaaa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Yamacraw Creek chief who granted land to James Oglethorpe in Georgia",
          "answer": "Tomochichi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last member of the Californian Yahi people whose real name is unknown",
          "answer": "Ishi 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3 The Assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modern U.S. States during the Civil War",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about Modern U.S. States during the Civil War...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Home to the capital of the Confederacy at Richmond",
          "answer": "Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The subject of Sherman's March to the Sea which ended in Savannah",
          "answer": "Georgia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of Vicksburg, represented by Jefferson Davis in Congress",
          "answer": "Mississippi"
        },
        {
          "question": "The state off the coast of which David Farragut said, \"Damn the torpedoes!\"",
          "answer": "Alabama"
        },
        {
          "question": "A new state created as a result of the Wheeling Convention",
          "answer": "West Virginia"
        },
        {
          "question": "The site of the \"Gettysburg of the West,\" the Battle of Westport",
          "answer": "Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "The westernmost territory of the Confederacy",
          "answer": "Arizona"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to a Black regiment embroiled in an equal pay controversy",
          "answer": "Massachusetts 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Abraham Lincoln",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State where Lincoln served as a politician in Springfield",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who assassinated him at Ford's Theater",
          "answer": "John Wilkes Booth"
        },
        {
          "question": "Democrat he debated seven times during an 1858 election",
          "answer": "Stephen A. Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former general he soundly defeated in the Election of 1864",
          "answer": "George B. McClellan"
        },
        {
          "question": "College in New York where he gave a speech denouncing slavery",
          "answer": [
            "The Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art",
            "Cooper Institute"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the New York Tribune whom he greatly impressed with that speech",
          "answer": "Horace Greeley"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Allan Pinkerton prevented him from being assassinated on the day of his first inaugural address",
          "answer": "Baltimore"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future U.S. senator he nearly dueled on Bloody Island",
          "answer": "James Shields 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Simón Bolívar, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding simón bolívar, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern South American country which is named for Simón Bolívar",
          "answer": [
            "Plurinational State of Bolivia",
            "Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country of which he was named the first President by the Congress of Angostura",
          "answer": "Gran Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who, as Bolívar's lieutenant, won the Battle of Ayacucho",
          "answer": "Antonio José de Sucre"
        },
        {
          "question": "1821 battle where he defeated Miguel de la Torre which led to the independence of Venezuela",
          "answer": "Battle of Carabobo"
        },
        {
          "question": "1807 war in which Napoleon tried to conquer Iberia that inspired Bolívar to launch his campaigns",
          "answer": "Peninsular War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary he handed over to Domingo de Monteverde in exchange for a passport",
          "answer": "Francisco de Miranda"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman he called the \"liberator of the liberator\" with whom he had a relationship until his death.",
          "answer": "Manuela Sáenz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Irishman, his aide-de-camp, who disobeyed orders to burn Bolívar's documents after his death",
          "answer": "Daniel Florence O'Leary 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Sons of Liberty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Massachusetts city where they led protests against a 1770 massacre",
          "answer": "Boston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commodity that they threw into the harbor during a 1773 event in that city",
          "answer": "Tea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Cousin of a future U.S. president who founded the organization",
          "answer": "Samuel Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "1765 tax on printed materials whose repeal led the original Sons of Liberty to disband",
          "answer": "Stamp Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "British official responsible for implementing that act who was hanged in effigy from the Liberty Tree",
          "answer": "Andrew Oliver"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ship boarded by John Brown which ran aground while pursuing the Hannah",
          "answer": "HMS Gaspee"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tailor and spy who used his slave Cato to send secret information during the Revolution",
          "answer": "Hercules Mulligan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Customs official who was tarred and feathered after a dispute with George Hewes",
          "answer": "John Malcom 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 7 Margaret Thatcher"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Knights of Labor",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Common type of nonviolent protest against businesses involving refusal to purchase products utilized by that organization",
          "answer": "Boycott"
        },
        {
          "question": "1875 act, supported by the earlier Page Act, meant to limit Asian workers supported by the Knights of Labor",
          "answer": "Chinese Exclusion Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival union led by Samuel Gompers",
          "answer": [
            "American Federation of Labor",
            "AFL"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who succeeded Uriah Smith Stephens as leader of the organization",
          "answer": "Terence V. Powderly"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late 19th century depression that largely ended the importance of the organization",
          "answer": "Panic of 1893"
        },
        {
          "question": "Railroad tycoon opposed by the organization who attempted to corner the gold market with James Fisk",
          "answer": "Jay Gould"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman who travelled the country giving her \"Dignity of Labor\" speech as an investigator for the Knights of Labor",
          "answer": "Leonora Barry"
        },
        {
          "question": "1887 massacre of Black sugar cane workers in Louisiana sparked by a Knights of Labor strike",
          "answer": "Thibodaux ] massacre 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8 Ivan the Terrible"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Theater, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the theater, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Axis power that attacked Pearl Harbor",
          "answer": [
            "Empire of Japan",
            "Nippon",
            "Nihon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Second of the only two cities to have been hit with an atom bomb",
          "answer": "Nagasaki"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island home to Mt. Suribachi where Joe Rosenthal photographed the American flag",
          "answer": "Iwo Jima"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the U.S. Pacific Fleet and ranking U.S. admiral at the Battle of Midway",
          "answer": "Chester W. Nimitz"
        },
        {
          "question": "May 1942 naval battle that marked the first \"carrier\" battle in which all combatants were in aircraft",
          "answer": "Battle of the Coral Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Forced movement of American POWs across a portion of Luzon",
          "answer": "Bataan Death March"
        },
        {
          "question": "Aircraft carrier and sister ship to the Hiryu which was sunk at the Battle of Midway",
          "answer": "Soryu"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Tiger of Malaya” who allegedly hid gold around the Philippines",
          "answer": "Tomoyuki Yamashita 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "New York in the 1960s",
      "prompt": "In the 1960s in New York City, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Primarily Black neighborhood that rioted following the death of Martin Luther King?",
          "answer": "Harlem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Nation of Islam spokesman assassinated in the Audubon Ballroom in 1965?",
          "answer": "Malcolm X"
        },
        {
          "question": "New name given to Idlewild Airport in 1963, following the assassination of a president?",
          "answer": "JFK Airport or John F. Kennedy International Airport"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greenwich Village gay bar whose patrons confronted police in June 1969?",
          "answer": "Stonewall Inn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Historic railroad station in NYC that was demolished in 1963?",
          "answer": "Penn Station"
        },
        {
          "question": "Highway advocate who ended his long tenure as city Parks and Planning commissioner in 1960?",
          "answer": "Robert Moses"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bank whose tower at 270 Park Avenue was completed in 1960, only to become the tallest voluntarily demolished building in history in 2021?",
          "answer": [
            "JPMorgan Chase & Co.",
            "Chase"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Democratic mayor from 1954 to 1965 who quit the New York Athletic Club for barring Black and Jewish membership?",
          "answer": "Robert F. Wagner or Robert Ferdinand Wagner II"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "19th-Century British Politics",
      "prompt": "In the politics of the 19th-century United Kingdom, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Two-time Conservative prime minister of Jewish ancestry?",
          "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial laws restricting the import of grain repealed in 1846?",
          "answer": "Corn Laws"
        },
        {
          "question": "Opponent of the Conservatives that was later overshadowed by the Labour Party in the early twentieth century.",
          "answer": [
            "Liberal Party or Liberals",
            "Whigs"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of laws expanding suffrage starting in 1832?",
          "answer": "Reform Bills"
        },
        {
          "question": "Foreign Secretary who intervened in the Don Pacifico Affair and became prime minister during the American Civil War?",
          "answer": "Lord Palmerston or Henry John Temple"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conservative-leaning political humor magazine that popularized regular political cartoons in the 1840s?",
          "answer": "Punch"
        },
        {
          "question": "1839 constitutional crisis over monarchial power to choose ceremonial personal attendants?",
          "answer": "Bedchamber Crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname given by the deaf Duke of Wellington to Lord Derby's 1852 cabinet containing many political unknowns?",
          "answer": "Who? Who? Ministry"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of the Alamo",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Alamo, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern day U.S. state where the Battle of the Alamo was fought.",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mexican dictator who captured the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Antonio Lopez de Santa Anna"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future President of the Lone Star Republic who sent artillery to reinforce the Alamo.",
          "answer": "Sam Houston"
        },
        {
          "question": "Original purpose of the Alamo prior to its use as a fort before the battle.",
          "answer": [
            "Spanish Mission",
            "Christian Mission",
            "or Mission Station",
            "Station for Missionaries"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"King of the Wild Frontier\" and Tennessee representative who died at the Alamo alongside James Bowie.",
          "answer": "Davy Crockett"
        },
        {
          "question": "South Carolinian lieutenant colonel who professionalized the republic's army and commanded the soldiers at the Alamo.",
          "answer": "William Barrett Travis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Panic caused by the fall of the Alamo, leading to an evacuation of the city of San Antonio.",
          "answer": "\"Runaway Scrape\""
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee woman who, with her daughter Angelina, were the only two Anglo- Americans to survive the Alamo disaster.",
          "answer": "Susanna Dickinson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Adlai Stevenson",
      "prompt": "Concerning Adlai Stevenson II, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Republican president of the 1950s and early 60s who defeated Stevenson twice in back to back landslide victories.",
          "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern state which Stevenson governed.",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future Attorney General and victim of Sirhan Sirhan who served as an aide for Stevenson on the 1956 presidential campaign.",
          "answer": "Robert Fitzgerald Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted overthrow of the Castro regime by Cuban exiles which nearly led to Adlai Stevenson resigning as Ambassador to the UN.",
          "answer": [
            "Bay of Pigs Incident",
            "Playa Giron"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-communist period pushed by Joseph McCarthy that coincided with Stevenson's stint as governor.",
          "answer": "Second Red Scare"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. government official who was accused of Communism and spying by Whittaker Chambers and who was defended by Stevenson in a private deposition.",
          "answer": "Alger Hiss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee politician who served as Stevenson's running mate in the 1956 election.",
          "answer": "Carey Estes Kefauver"
        },
        {
          "question": "Derisive nickname of Stevenson later embraced by him on the 1952 campaign trail which poked fun at his baldness and intellectual air.",
          "answer": "Egghead"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nikita Khrushchev",
      "prompt": "Concerning the Soviet First Secretary of the 1950s and 1960s, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Present-day nation where, until the fall of Kiev to the Germans, Khrushchev headed the Communist Party.",
          "answer": "Ukraine or Ukraïna"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War Two battle on the Volga river which Khrushchev participated in under Georgy Zhukov.",
          "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crisis concerning the placement of ballistic missiles on a Caribbean nation by the Khrushchev regime.",
          "answer": "Cuban Missile Crisis"
        },
        {
          "question": "First artificial satellite launched by the Soviet space program in 1957.",
          "answer": "Sputnik 1"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oration given by Khrushchev to denounce his predecessor, Joseph Stalin.",
          "answer": [
            "Secret Speech or Sekretnïy Doklad",
            "\"On the Cult of Personality and Its Consequences\"",
            "or O kul'te lichnosti i yego posledstviyakh"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Debate\" between Vice President Nixon and Khrushchev at the American National Exhibition.",
          "answer": [
            "Kitchen Debate",
            "Kukhonnye debaty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Favorite of Stalin who immediately succeeded him before being politically outmaneuvered by Khrushchev.",
          "answer": "Georgy Malenkov or Georgy Maximilianovich Malenkov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Communist Romania who resisted Khrushchev's program of of de- Stalinization.",
          "answer": "Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej ]"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Adlai Stevenson",
      "prompt": "Concerning Adlai Stevenson II, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Republican president of the 1950s and early 60s who defeated Stevenson twice in back to back landslide victories.",
          "answer": "Dwight David Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Midwestern state which Stevenson governed.",
          "answer": "Illinois"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future Attorney General and victim of Sirhan Sirhan who served as an aide for Stevenson on the 1956 presidential campaign.",
          "answer": "Robert Fitzgerald Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted overthrow of the Castro regime by Cuban exiles which nearly led to Adlai Stevenson resigning as Ambassador to the UN.",
          "answer": [
            "Bay of Pigs Incident",
            "Playa Giron"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-communist period pushed by Joseph McCarthy that coincided with Stevenson's stint as governor.",
          "answer": "Second Red Scare"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. government official who was accused of Communism and spying by Whittaker Chambers and who was defended by Stevenson in a private deposition.",
          "answer": "Alger Hiss"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tennessee politician who served as Stevenson's running mate in the 1956 election.",
          "answer": "Carey Estes Kefauver"
        },
        {
          "question": "Derisive nickname of Stevenson later embraced by him on the 1952 campaign trail which poked fun at his baldness and intellectual air.",
          "answer": "Egghead"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Colombia",
      "prompt": "Concerning the South American nation, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Colombia, which was secured following the Battle of Boyacá.",
          "answer": "Bogota"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central American state which broke away from Colombia in 1903 with U.S. backing.",
          "answer": "Republic of Panama or República de Panamá"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Liberator\" of South America who became the first president of Gran Colombia.",
          "answer": "Simón Bolívar or Simón José Antonio de la Santísima Trinidad Bolívar y Ponte Palacios y Blanco"
        },
        {
          "question": "1980s head of the Medellin [[meh-deh-YEEN]] cartel known as the \"King of Cocaine.\"",
          "answer": "Pablo Escobar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Marxist-Leninist insurgent group in Colombia which utilized kidnapping and ransom.",
          "answer": [
            "FARC",
            "Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia",
            "Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias de Colombia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish viceroyalty which included modern-day Colombia, Venezuela, and Trinidad and Tobago.",
          "answer": [
            "Viceroyalty of New Granada",
            "Viceroyalty of the New Kingdom of Granada"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Colombian president from 2002 to 2010 who allied with the Bush administration to fight the War on Drugs in \"Plan Colombia.\"",
          "answer": "Álvaro Uribe Vélez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indigenous people of the Colombian altiplano that formed a namesake Confederation before being conquered by the Spanish.",
          "answer": [
            "Muisca",
            "Muisca Confederation",
            "Chibcha"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Women during the Civil War",
      "prompt": "Concerning women's many roles during the Civil War, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Conductor on the Underground Railroad who recruited black soldiers to fight for the Union cause.",
          "answer": "Harriet Tubman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of Little Women who depicted women during the Civil War in her non-fiction work, Hospital Sketches.",
          "answer": "Louisa May Alcott"
        },
        {
          "question": "Writer who Abraham Lincoln might have greeted by saying, \"you are the little woman who wrote the book that started this great war.\"",
          "answer": "Harriet Beecher Stowe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the American Red Cross who became known as the \"Angel of the Battlefield\" for her revolutionary nursing practices.",
          "answer": "Clara Barton"
        },
        {
          "question": "First woman physician in the U.S. who organized a corps of nurses during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Elizabeth Blackwell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Private detective agency which employed the capable female P.I. Hattie Lawton to scout in the northern Virginia theater.",
          "answer": "Pinkerton Detective Agency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boardinghouse owner and member of the Booth conspiracy to kill Lincoln who was the first woman executed by the federal government.",
          "answer": "Mary Surratt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hotel operator and Confederate spy known as \"the Siren of the Shenandoah.\"",
          "answer": "Isabelle Boyd"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Jill Lepore wrote about this man’s sister Jane in Book of Ages. He never reconciled with\nhis son William, a Royalist governor of New Jersey. John Sevier was elected to govern a\nshort-lived (20 pts) ",
        "state in modern-day Tennessee named for this man. This man drafted the\nPlan of Union as a delegate to the Albany Conference, and drew the (10 pts) ",
        "“Join or Die”\npolitical cartoon. This man created America’s first library and invented the bifocals. For 10\npoints, name this American statesman who legendarily used a kite to experiment with electricity."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Benjamin Franklin",
        "Franklin",
        "Ben Franklin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A riot targeting a certain group in this state began in the “Sand Lot” and was put down\nby the Pick Handle Brigade. This state was home to outlaws like Red-Handed Dick and\nJoaquin Murietta [wah-KEEN moor-ee-AY-tuh]. The Workingman’s (20 pts) ",
        "Party in this state\nwas led by Denis Kearney. The owner of the Central Pacific Railroad became governor of\nthis state in the 1860s. An influx of (10 pts) ",
        "immigration led this state to pass laws limiting the\nrights of Chinese to hold property. For 10 points, name this western U.S. state, admitted to the\nUnion after its Gold Rush of 1849."
      ],
      "answer": "California"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's staff secretary was Andrew Goodpaster. This president denied IMF\nassistance to one country to help halt Operation Musketeer. During this man’s presidency,\nthe CIA overthrew (20 pts) ",
        "Mohammed Mossadegh in Iran and Jacobo Arbenz [yuh-KOH-boh\nARR-benz] in Guatemala. This president’s Secretary of State, who coined the term\n“brinkmanship,” was (10 pts) ",
        "John Foster Dulles. This man signed the interstate highway act and\nended the Korean War. For 10 points, name this former Allied commander and president during\nthe 1950's."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Dwight D. Eisenhower",
        "Ike",
        "Eisenhower",
        "Dwight David Eisenhower",
        "Dwight Eisenhower"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Senators from this party included North Carolina’s Marion Butler. A predecessor to this\nparty articulated its goals in the Ocala Demands, which this party incorporated in its (20 pts) ",
        "Omaha platform. James B. Weaver carried four states as this party’s candidate for\npresident. It allied with Terence (10 pts) ",
        "Powderly’s Knights of Labor. It nominated Thomas E.\nWatson as a vice-presidential candidate in 1896, when both it and the Democrats nominated\nWilliam Jennings Bryan. For 10 points, name this American political party of farmers that\nopposed national banks and utilities."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "People’s Party",
        "People's",
        "Populist",
        "Populist Party"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two years before this scandal, a group central to it was involved in Operation Tipped\nKettle. In one part of this scandal, Israeli shipments of BGM-71 anti-tank (20 pts) ",
        "missiles were\nsupposed to achieve the release of American hostages. This scandal was partly the result of\nthe Boland Amendment, which limited funding for opponents of the (10 pts) ",
        "Sandinista [sandduh-nees-tuh] National Liberation Front. For 10 points, name this mid-1980s scandal that\nresulted in the indictments of Oliver North and Caspar Weinberger, in which weapons were sold\nto a Middle Eastern country in order to fund anti-communist rebels in Nicaragua."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Iran-Contra affair",
        "Iran-Contra",
        "Irangate",
        "Contragate",
        "Iran-Contra scandal"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A formative moment for this man was the murder of his mentor Cornstalk. This man\nridiculed the notion of selling land, saying “Sell a country! Why not sell the air?” He\nrefused to recognize the Treaty of (20 pts) ",
        "Greenville, and decried the “peace chiefs” who had\nsigned it. Richard Mentor Johnson claimed to have killed this man, whose brother\nTenskwatawa was known as “the Prophet.” After his death at the Battle of the (10 pts) ",
        "Thames,\nhis Native American confederation broke up. For 10 points, name this Shawnee chief who allied\nwith the British during the War of 1812."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Tecumseh",
        "Tecumtha",
        "Tikamthe"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This hero’s “Kooky Quartet” consisted of him, Quicksilver, Scarlet Witch, and Hawkeye. He is considered the successful product of the Weapon I program, also known as Project: Rebirth. In the Civil War story arc, this man led (20 pts)",
        "resistance to the Superhero Registration Act. His chief weapon is made from an alloy of steel and vibranium, and his love interest is Sharon Carter. This friend of (10 pts)",
        "Bucky Barnes battled the Red Skull before being frozen in ice for decades. For 10 points, name this patriotic Avenger who wields a red, white, and blue shield."
      ],
      "answer": "Captain America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Las Limas figure produced by this culture depicts a youth holding a were- jaguar. The Cascajal [cass-cuh-HALL] Block may demonstrate evidence of a (20 pts)",
        "written language among these people. These people's first major site emerged during the Early Formative Period. Their most notable artifacts may have been converted thrones and typically wear leather helmets, and can be found at sites like (10 pts)",
        "La Venta and San Lorenzo. This civilization's name comes from the Nahuatl [nah-wah-tell] word for \"rubber people\". For 10 points, name this Mesoamerican civilization that created colossal stone heads."
      ],
      "answer": "Olmecs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Restitution for a Canadian equivalent of this policy was passed by the government of Brian Mulroney. Ansel Adams photographed people affected by this policy at (20 pts)",
        "Manzanar. Places like Tule Lake were created by this policy’s early advocates on the State Personnel Board of (10 pts)",
        "California. Much of this policy was established through Executive Order 9066. Ex parte Endo concerned a man detained as part of this policy. For 10 points, name this policy that confined Americans of a certain Asian ethnicity during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Japanese-American Internment during World War II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of the signatories of this treaty would later be stationed in Constantinople. One side argued that its terms mandated the renunciation of claims to the Bay Islands and the (20 pts)",
        "Mosquito Coast. Many observers thought this treaty named for Lord Palmerston's minister to Washington and Zachary Taylor's Secretary of State violated the (10 pts)",
        "Monroe Doctrine. Eventually abrogated by the 1901 Hay-Pauncefote Treaty, for 10 points, identify this 1850 treaty declaring that neither the US nor Britain would build a canal in Central America without mutual consent."
      ],
      "answer": "Clayton-Bulwer Treaty"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man commissioned a thousand-page white paper intended to prove that the U.S. had no hope of successful military intervention in China, which was perceived as an attempt to deflect criticism for “losing China” to the Communists during his time as (20 pts)",
        "Secretary. This man was accused of running a \"cowardly college of Communist (10 pts)",
        "containment\" by Richard Nixon and of overseeing a spy-riddled State Department by Joseph McCarthy. For 10 points, name this much-maligned Secretary of State who served under the second Truman administration until 1953."
      ],
      "answer": "Dean Gooderham Acheson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man signed the Belavezha Accords as one of his first acts in office, and he apologized for Korean Airlines Flight 007 after meeting with South Korean President Roh Tae-Woo. Bill Clinton claims that, in 1995, this foreign leader was found on the streets of D.C. calling for pizza while (20 pts)",
        "drunk. A policy of economic “shock therapy,” suggested by Jeffrey Sachs, was implemented by this man in the (10 pts)",
        "1990s. For ten points, name this first President of a post-Cold War Russia, who was responsible for ousting Mikhail Gorbachev in 1991."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Vaughn Meader popularized this action, using phrases like “move ahead with great vigah,” while Chevy Chase performed this action with bumbling slapstick. The word “strategery” [stra-TEE-jer-ee] was coined for use in one of these actions by (20 pts)",
        "Will Ferrell, who staged a one-man play, You’re Welcome, America, featuring this action. Luther, the “Anger Translator,” used a megaphone to proclaim “I am not a (10 pts)",
        "Muslim!” to complement Jordan Peele’s performance of this action. For ten points, name this genre of comedy, currently performed on Saturday Night Live by Jay Pharoah as Barack Obama."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "comedic impersonations of the U.S. President",
        "descriptions of comedic sketches featuring an actor playing the President"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an effort to gain reconnaissance about this man’s army, Jeb Stuart and over 1,000 cavalrymen rode completely around it. This man’s forces retreated to Malvern Hill at the end of the Seven Days Battles, bringing this man’s (20 pts)",
        "Peninsular Campaign to a disappointing end. His failure to pursue the outnumbered Confederate army at Antietam led President Lincoln to (10 pts)",
        "promote Ambrose Burnside. For ten points, name this man who faced Lincoln in the 1864 Presidential election after being replaced as Commander of the Army of the Potomac in 1862."
      ],
      "answer": "George B. McClellan"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The deciding vote for this amendment was cast by Harry Burn, a Tennessee legislator who was persuaded to “put the rat in ratification.” This amendment overruled Minor v. Happersett, and its ratification was upheld in (20 pts)",
        "Leser v. Garnett. This amendment was advocated for by the Silent Sentinels and a 1913 parade organized by (10 pts)",
        "Alice Paul, and was popularly named after one of its first proponents, Susan B. Anthony. For ten points, name this 1920 Constitutional amendment that granted women the right to vote."
      ],
      "answer": "19th Amendment"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This year was the last time a major party was undecided on its Presidential nominee at the start of the convention. One presidential candidate in this election year defeated Arizona senator Morris Udall in the primaries, and gave an interview admitting that he had (20 pts)",
        "“lust in his heart.” The incumbent in this race was damaged by his assertion that there was “no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe” and his (10 pts)",
        "pardoning of Richard Nixon for Watergate. For ten points, name this election year in which Gerald Ford was defeated by peanut farmer Jimmy Carter?"
      ],
      "answer": "Presidential election of 1976"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This agency’s first head, retired General Hugh Johnson, advocated for a “blanket code,” and its Section 7a guaranteed the right of labor to collectively bargain. Charles Evans Hughes held that it overstepped the legislature’s Commerce Clause power in the (20 pts)",
        "“sick chicken” case. Until it was unanimously declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court in Schechter Poultry Corp. v. US, this agency was promoted with a (10 pts)",
        "blue eagle and the slogan “We Do Our Part”. For ten points, name this New Deal administration that removed competition by setting prices and fair standards."
      ],
      "answer": "NRA or National Recovery Administration"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first supplementary act to this legislation removed an exception for individuals possessing a letter of marque, as well as whaling vessels. One response to this law features the saying “Darn it, how he (20 pts)",
        "nicks ‘em.” This legislation, passed in response to the Chesapeake-Leopard Affair, was replaced two years later by the Non-Intercourse Act in the final days of (10 pts)",
        "Thomas Jefferson’s presidency. A political cartoon of the snapping turtle Ograbme lampooned, for ten points, what unpopular 1807 law attempted to prevent any American exports?"
      ],
      "answer": "Embargo Act of 1807"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) David Josiah Brewer did not participate in this case’s decision on account of his daughter’s death. The majority opinion in this case denied the existence of a “badge of inferiority.” Lum v. Rice applied this case to decide that a Mississippi public school was justified in denying a (20 pts)",
        "Chinese-American student. The petitioner in this case, who was represented by Albion Tourgee, was refused seating in a (10 pts)",
        "“whites-only” railway car despite being only one-eighth black. For ten points, name this 1896 Supreme Court that established the doctrine of “separate but equal” and was overturned by Brown v. Board."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Plessy v. Ferguson",
        "either"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1919, socialist Victor Berger’s seat in Congress was disqualified under this amendment’s third section. John Bingham reworded one section of this amendment to remove language describing (20 pts)",
        "racial discrimination in favor of broader protection. Its fourth section refused to honor debts made by the Confederacy, and its first section notes that “[no] State shall deprive any person of life, liberty, or property without (10 pts)",
        "due process of law.” The Equal Protection clause is contained in, for ten points, what Reconstruction amendment that granted “all persons born [...] in the United States” citizenship?"
      ],
      "answer": "14th Amendment"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech references a passage from the book of Isaiah, commanding to “let the oppressed go free.” Its speaker warned leaders of newly-freed countries that those who “foolishly sought power by riding the back of the tiger ended up inside,” shortly after stating that he will (20 pts)",
        "“bear any burden” and “oppose any foe.” This speech, which declared that the “torch has been passed to a new generation of Americans,” was preceded by a recitation of “The (10 pts)",
        "Gift Outright”. For ten points, name this speech, in which a newly sworn-in President declared “ask not what your country can do for you; ask what you can do for your country.”"
      ],
      "answer": "John F. Kennedy’s inaugural address"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wisconsin’s Supreme Court was the only state supreme court to declare one of these laws unconstitutional, although that decision was overturned in the case of Ableman v. Booth. Pierce Butler and Charles Pinckney proposed the clause in the (20 pts)",
        "Constitution that led to the development of the first of these laws in 1793. “Personal liberty laws” were meant to circumvent these laws, which were invalidated by the (10 pts)",
        "13th Amendment. For ten points, identify these laws, one of which was also passed in 1850, which stated that certain property could be returned to its owners after escape into a free state."
      ],
      "answer": "Fugitive Slave Laws"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man wrote that “The ‘power to regulate commerce among the several States’ cannot include a power to construct roads and canals” in his veto of the Bonus Bill. Macon’s (20 pts)",
        "Bills were passed under this President, repealing the Non-Intercourse Act. The charter for the first Bank of the United States expired under this man; five years later, he launched the (10 pts)",
        "Second Bank of the United States to help finance the rebuilding efforts after the War of 1812. For ten points, name this founding father who preceded James Monroe as U.S. President."
      ],
      "answer": "James Madison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader’s regime is the subject of Mario Vargas Llosa’s [yoh-sa’s] The Feast of the Goat . Johnny Abbes Garcia led the SIM, a secret police force under this leader. The OAS imposed sanctions on this leader’s country after he ordered a failed assassination attempt on (20 pts)",
        "Venezuelan president Romulo Betancourt. This leader’s government was responsible for the deaths of thousands of Haitians in the (10 pts)",
        "Parsley massacre, and he was assassinated in an ambush outside Santo Domingo in 1961. For ten points, name this dictator of the Dominican Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Rafael Trujillo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Karl Marx referred to this man as the “most miserable and meanest of blackguards.” While Santiago Marin˜o fought in the east, this man worked with Jos´e F´elix Ribas on the west to defeat an army led by Domingo de Monteverde. This man (20 pts)",
        "wrote about the failures of the First Republic in an 1812 document; nine years later, his forces were victorious at the Battle of Carabobo, allowing this man to (10 pts)",
        "establish, and become the first president of, Gran Colombia. For ten points, name this South American “Liberator,” honored as the namesake of a country with capitals La Paz and Sucre."
      ],
      "answer": "Simon Bolivar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing side in this battle gave command to Juan Landero to officially surrender, as Juan Morales refused to do so. During this battle, David Conner’s fleet provided bombardment support on Collado (20 pts)",
        "Beach. After this battle, the winning side marched on the capital, meeting the enemy at Cerro Gordo and capturing Santa Anna’s wooden leg. (10 pts)",
        "Winfield Scott led the first major American amphibious assault in, for ten points, what 1847 three-week siege of a port city on the Gulf of Mexico during the Mexican-American War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle or Siege of Veracruz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, the U.S. distributed copies of the Psychological Operations in Guerrilla Warfare manual. In 1986, the U.S. was censured by the International Court of Justice for mining this country’s commercial (20 pts)",
        "harbors. American funding to this country was officially halted by the Boland Amendment, but money was re-routed to one of its right-leaning factions by (10 pts)",
        "Oliver North. For ten points, name this Central American country, the subject of a scandal during the Reagan administration involving its Contra guerrillas."
      ],
      "answer": "Nicaragua"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The approximate location of this person’s death is commemorated by a statue in Gravesend near the mouth of the River Thames. This person was held as a prisoner, first aboard Samuel (20 pts)",
        "Argall’s ship and then at Henricus, where she converted to Christianity and adopted the name Rebecca. This woman’s marriage to John (10 pts)",
        "Rolfe secured an alliance between British colonists and Native Americans, and she had earlier encouraged her father to spare John Smith’s life. For ten points, name this daughter of Powhatan."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Pocahontas",
        "Rebecca Rolfe before “Rebecca” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A contingency plan to defend this structure was drawn up in Operation Sand Flea. A French attempt to build this structure failed when Ferdinand de (20 pts)",
        "Lesseps was found to be misappropriating funds. The Darien Scheme tried to build this strcuture, whose construction began in earnest after the (10 pts)",
        "Hay-Bunau-Varilla treaty. This structure was returned to the government of Omar Torrijos by Jimmy Carter in 1977. For ten points, name this Central American waterway that links the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An early proponent of this cause was mayor Neal Dow, who crafted the short-lived Maine Law. Wayne Wheeler pioneered “pressure politics” in support of this cause. Another advocate for this cause was known for using a (20 pts)",
        "hatchet to destroy contraband. The Volstead Act provided legal backing to this cause, which was supported by (10 pts)",
        "Carrie A. Nation and a Women’s Christian Union. For ten points, name this cause that became national policy with the passing of the 18th Amendment, then was revoked with the 21st Amendment."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "temperance or prohibition of alcohol",
        "descriptive answers that relate to the banning of alcohol"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s exile to Europe was reported by Lauren Lyman. His expedition to aid China after a flood is documented by the book North to the Orient. This man, who proposed a neutrality pact with Germany and supported the (20 pts)",
        "America First movement, had his son kidnapped by Bruno Hauptmann in the “Crime of the Century.” In 1927, this man won the Orteig Prize for his (10 pts)",
        "journey from Roosevelt Field to Le Bourget Field. For ten points, name this American aviator who undertook the first non-stop trans-Atlantic flight."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Lindbergh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Just before leaving for this event, Jed Bartlett teaches the Secretary of Agriculture how to pick a Chief of Staff in a Season One episode of The West Wing titled “He Shall, from Time to Time...”. That episode title references Article (20 pts)",
        "2, Section 3 of the Constitution, detailing the need for these events. Kiefer Sutherland’s character becomes President because he is the (10 pts)",
        "“designated survivor” of this event in a 2016 ABC drama. For ten points, name this annual political speech given by the President to a joint session of Congress."
      ],
      "answer": "State of the Union address or speech, etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man and William Pinkney produced a never-ratified agreement to extend Jay’s Treaty. This man provoked a controversy by allowing Andrew Jackson to cross international borders during the (20 pts)",
        "Seminole War. William Plumer voted for Richard Rush and John Quincy Adams instead of Daniel Tompkins and this man, becoming the only (10 pts)",
        "elector to vote against him in 1820. The Era of Good Feelings was led by, for ten points, what President who protected Latin America from European interference with a famous doctrine?"
      ],
      "answer": "James Monroe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man consolidated power in one union by forcing rivals to listen to peer abuse in a process known as “the Game.” In an attempt to drum up support from Filipinos, this man made the mistake of meeting with Ferdinand Marcos, leading to a break with (20 pts)",
        "Philip Vera Cruz. This man utilized the motto “Si, se puede” [see, say pway-day] during a hunger strike and joined the Delano (10 pts)",
        "grape march on Sacramento to fight for higher wages for laborers. For ten points, name this Mexican-American activist who helped found the United Farm Workers."
      ],
      "answer": "C´esar Ch´avez"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A prologue involving the Rumor family was cut from one of this man’s compositions; Rudolph Giuliani led a protest of a 2014 staging of that work. A work by this man opens with the “Chorus of Exiled Palestinians” and “Chorus of Exiled Jews” and depicts the (20 pts)",
        "hijacking of the MS Achille Lauro. Another of his operas features the aria “News has a kind of mystery” and centers on a (10 pts)",
        "1972 visit to Mao Tse-Tung. For ten points, name this American composer of The Death of Klinghoffer and Nixon in China, who shares his name with multiple U.S. presidents."
      ],
      "answer": "John Coolidge Adams"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this battle, the Minnesota was struck by stray cannon fire from the James River Squadron. During the battle, an explosion blinded Captain John Worden with paint, forcing his ship to withdraw. In this battle, the (20 pts)",
        "USS Congress and Cumberland were destroyed in an attempt to stop the Anaconda Plan. Catesby ap Roger Jones led the second day of this engagement, in which (10 pts)",
        "neither ship suffered significant damage. For ten points, name this Civil War naval battle, the first combat between two ironclad ships."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Hampton Roads",
        "descriptions of the battle between the USS Monitor and the USS Merrimack,",
        "between the USS Monitor and the CSS Virginia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man gave a press conference that opened with John Quinn quoting Ben Franklin’s “A republic, sir, if you can keep it” anecdote. Later in the press conference, this man discussed a tax deduction for giving his (20 pts)",
        "Vice Presidential papers to the government and misspoke, suggesting that John Ehrlichman was guilty until proven innocent. The press conference climaxed with this man explaining “I have (10 pts)",
        "earned everything I have got” after noting that “people have got to know whether or not their President is a crook.” For ten points, name this President who was grilled by newspaper editors in 1973 over the Watergate scandal."
      ],
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this election year, the “Draft Muskie” movement emerged to break a deadlocked convention. John B. Anderson ran as an independent in this election. Controversy from the (20 pts)",
        "Chappaquiddick incident 11 years earlier damaged Ted Kennedy’s chances of being nominated during this year. Despite the “voodoo economics” attack in this year’s primaries, (10 pts)",
        "George H.W. Bush was nominated for Vice President. The failure to resolve the Iran Hostage Crisis helped doom a re-election campaign in, for ten points, what year in which Jimmy Carter lost 44 states to Ronald Reagan?"
      ],
      "answer": "Presidential Election of 1980"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While in office, this man vetoed the Rivers and Harbors Act for its high cost. Robert Todd Lincoln finished his service as Secretary of War under this president. This man was initially distrusted for being a (20 pts)",
        "“Stalwart” Republican and supporting patronage, but he broke with his old boss Roscoe Conkling by reversing that stance and passing the (10 pts)",
        "Pendleton Act to reform civil service. This man served as Vice President under a man who was assassinated by Charles Guiteau. For ten points, name this President who succeeded James Garfield."
      ],
      "answer": "Chester Alan Arthur"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech laments how the “solitary inventor...has been overshadowed by scientists” and calls on Americans to avoid “plundering for our own ease and convenience...the precious resources of tomorrow.” This speech warns against allowing (20 pts)",
        "“public policy” to fall in the hands of the “scientific-technological elite” and warns against the “unwarranted influence” of the (10 pts)",
        "“military-industrial complex.” For ten points, name this speech, given three days before John F. Kennedy’s inaugural address, that ended a US President’s public career. ANSWER:DwightEisenhower’sFarewellAddress(acceptdescriptiveanswersofDwightEisenhower’s last speech as President) (3) A state named for this modern-day country existed for twenty-four hours under president Avgustyn Voloshyn. Symon Petliura led another state in this modern-day country, which was the site of an anti-Semitic nationalist movement led by Stepan (+) Bandera during World War II. Leonid Kuchma was overthrown as this country’s President in the 2004 (*) Orange Revolution, and this country was also the site of more recent Euromaidan protests. For ten points, name this country that lost control over the Crimean Peninsula after a 2014 Russian annexation."
      ],
      "answer": "Ukraine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles Ruthenberg organized a parade in Cleveland to protest the jailing of this man. This man, one of the many co-founders of the Industrial Workers of the World, was defended by Clarence Darrow for his actions in the (20 pts)",
        "Pullman Strike. This man declared “when I rise it will be with the ranks, and not from the ranks” in a speech in (10 pts)",
        "Canton, Ohio protesting the World War I draft. For ten points, name this five-time Socialist presidential candidate who ran his last campaign in 1920 from a prison cell."
      ],
      "answer": "Eugene V. Debs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man employed James Alexander, who was quickly found in contempt; Andrew Hamilton and William Smith then defended him. This man, upset over the promotion of James DeLancey to replace Lewis (20 pts)",
        "Morris, was condemned for his “scandalous [...] and seditious reflections” by William Cosby; this man’s supporters noted, though, that (10 pts)",
        "truth is a defense against charges of libel. For ten points, name this German-American editor whose 1735 trial became a landmark defense of freedom of the press."
      ],
      "answer": "John Peter Zenger"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people were suppressed in one country after Antoine de La Valette went bankrupt on land deals in the Caribbean. These people upset the Marquis of Pombal by defending so-called “Reductions” that housed Guarani natives in (20 pts)",
        "South America. Clement XIV refused to meet with a leader of this group, Lorenzo Ricci, and ultimately suppressed them in 1773. The Tavora Affair ended with the (10 pts)",
        "expulsion of these people from Portugal, making teaching of the Spirtiual Exercises illegal. For ten points, name this powerful missionary order that was founded by Ignatius of Loyola."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Jesuits",
        "members of the Society of Jesus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this event, Lieutenant Braunersreuther [brown-ers-roy-ter] demanded a surrender within 30 minutes and received it 29 minutes later. At the outset of this event, Captain Henry Glass was surprised to find only a Japanese merchant ship in port. The victims of this event, lacking proper guns in (20 pts)",
        "Fort Santa Cruz, rowed to the USS Charleston to verbally return what they thought was a salute, because they were unaware that the US had (10 pts)",
        "declared war on Spain. Only warning shots were fired during, for ten points, what bloodless 1898 event in which a western Pacific island changed hands?"
      ],
      "answer": "capture or invasion, attack, surrender, etc. of Guam during the Spanish-American War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1956, the leader of this organization wrote an open letter claiming that T.R.M. Howard’s “false charges” were “a disservice to common decency.” In 1971, a “Citizens’ Commission” used the broadcast of the Ali-Frazier “Fight of the Century” as a distraction to successfully raid one of this organization’s (20 pts)",
        "suburban offices in Media, Pennsylvania. That burglary recovered documents used by the Church Committee to declassify this organization’s (10 pts)",
        "COINTELPRO project, which illegally targeted activists like Martin Luther King, Jr. with illegal surveillance. For ten points, name this American law enforcement agency that was led for nearly 5 decades by J. Edgar Hoover."
      ],
      "answer": "Federal Bureau of Investigation or FBI"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Mitchell, Frank Morrison and this man were placed in contempt after marking Buck Stove and Range Company on an “unfair list.” This man worked with Adolph Strasser to form a trade union whose members included his successor, William (20 pts)",
        "Green. One organization this man founded pressed for immigration quotas like the Emergency Quota Act. This man called for (10 pts)",
        "“pure and simple unionism” opposing political party influence in trade unions. For ten points, name this former cigar maker who founded the American Federation of Labor, or AFL."
      ],
      "answer": "Samuel Gompers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the USS Baltimore destroyed the city of Iloilo [ee-lo-ee-lo] just hours after soldiers were killed in Santa Mesa. During this war, Jacob Smith wanted to create “a howling wilderness” and ordered his soldiers to kill everyone over the (20 pts)",
        "age of ten. Frederick Funston pretended to be the prisoner of indigenous Macabebe scouts during this war; that trick allowed for the capture of (10 pts)",
        "Emilio Aguinaldo. For ten points, name this war in which American forces put down the Tagalog Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Philippine-American War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Members of this irregular fighting force often used the “one slow, four quick” doctrine. Eddie Adams photographed a captain in this group who had recently killed a Lieutenant Colonel and his family; in that photo, the member of this group is wearing a flannel shirt and (20 pts)",
        "shot at point blank range by General Nguyen Loan [when loan]. This group led multiple attacks in January (10 pts)",
        "1968, striking the city of Hue [hway] and breaching the U.S. embassy in Saigon. For ten points, name this guerrilla fighting group that fought against the U.S. and South Vietnam during the Tet Offensive."
      ],
      "answer": "Viet Cong or National Liberation Front"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Paul Jones created an unconventional variant of this object after capturing the Serapis. The first official version of this object was created from the coat of Abraham Swartwout, for which he was reimbursed. In (20 pts)",
        "1777, Congress officially adopted this object, which is celebrated on June 14th. While aboard the HMS Tonnant, (10 pts)",
        "Francis Scott Key was inspired by this object which withstood the Siege of Fort McHenry. Betsy Ross legendarily created, for ten points, what national symbol that inspired “The Star-Spangled Banner?”"
      ],
      "answer": "the flag of the United States of America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While vice president, a man from this state reported to Fort McClary to take over as his Coast Guard Company’s cook. John Nutting and John Calef led a British strategy to create “New Ireland” in this state. The (20 pts)",
        "Mulligan Letters helped tarnish a presidential campaign for a politician from this state. The Webster-Ashburton Treaty settled a war in this state over border disputes, the (10 pts)",
        "Aroostook War. The home state of Hannibal Hamlin and “Continental Liar” James Blaine is, for ten points, what state that was admitted to the Union in the Missouri Compromise, breaking off of Massachusetts?"
      ],
      "answer": "Maine"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A theorem regarding this process demonstrated that it cannot satisfy all three criteria of non-dictatorship, independence of irrelevant alternatives, and Pareto efficiency; that theorem about this process is (20 pts)",
        "Arrow’s Impossibility Theorem. A method of running this process is named for Condorcet. As a territory, Wyoming was the first state to allow (10 pts)",
        "women to participate in this process in 1869. For ten points, name this civic process in which individual preferences are counted to determine an outcome, like choosing a Congressperson."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "voting systems",
        "elections and other equivalents",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing vice presidential candidate in this election year was an Oregon senator who had introduced a bill for the creation of the Grand Coulee Dam, Charles McNary. Both members of the winning ticket in this year had been interested in the philosophy of a mystic named Nicholas (20 pts)",
        "Roerich. The winning Vice Presidential candidate in this election year had earlier served as Secretary of Agriculture under the incumbent and succeeded John Nance Garner. (10 pts)",
        "Wendell Wilkie lost this election, which broke the tradition of two-term presidencies. For ten points, name this election year in which FDR won, just after the start of World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1940"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One man with this surname negotiated with France to obtain a loan that allowed for the creation of the Bank of North America. That man with this surname headed the “Secret Committee of Trade” during the Second Continental Congress and is sometimes known as the (20 pts)",
        "“Financier of the Revolution.” In addition to Robert, another man with this surname wrote the phrases (10 pts)",
        "“ensure domestic Tranquility” and “form a more perfect Union” at the Constitutional Convention. For ten points, give this surname shared by Robert and the author of the Preamble, Gouverneur [“governor”]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Morris",
        "Robert Morris",
        "Gouverneur Morris"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A vice-presidential candidate in this election year had taken over Walter Colquitt’s vacated Senate seat and would go on to become Governor of Georgia. In this election year, William Yancey, a member of the Fire-Eaters, helped (20 pts)",
        "split one party into geographic factions. The Lecompton Constitution was discussed during this election, whose winning ticket included (10 pts)",
        "Hannibal Hamlin. John Breckenridge and Stephen Douglas lost, for ten points, what Presidential election that helped trigger the siege of Fort Sumter after Abraham Lincoln won?"
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1860"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Curly Harris attempted to mitigate the financial losses caused by this event by having three of his employees dress in street clothes and act as customers. David Richmond and Ezell Blair were among the participants in this event, who were attendees of an (20 pts)",
        "Agricultural and Technical State University. After buying toothpaste, the four initial members of this event unsuccessfully tried to order a (10 pts)",
        "cup of coffee as employees appealed to a “whites only” policy. For ten points, name this 1960 event in which African-American students occupied a Woolworth lunch counter in North Carolina."
      ],
      "answer": "1960 Greensboro sit-ins"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who was accused of cannibalism in the Coffin Handbills, won a battle after the opposing soldiers forgot to bring ladders to climb the fortifications that this man had constructed. During that battle, this man was assisted by the French (20 pts)",
        "pirate Jean Lafitte. This man defeated the Creek at Horseshoe Bend, the last battle of the Red Stick War, and he defeated Edward Pakenham in a battle that occurred (10 pts)",
        "after the Treaty of Ghent ended the War of 1812. For ten points, name this general who won the Battle of New Orleans before being elected President in 1828."
      ],
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A message sent by William Draper to the overseer of this effort included a request for “seventy Dakotas.” After the success of this effort, a parade was thrown in New York City to celebrate Lucius (20 pts)",
        "Clay. On a day called Black Friday, low visibility conditions saw an abnormal amount of participants in this effort fail to arrive on schedule at (10 pts)",
        "Tempelhof. “Raisin bombers” helped improve children’s morale in, for ten points, what American supply effort that avoided a Soviet blockade of a divided German city?"
      ],
      "answer": "Berlin Airlift"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this year, an investigation by Clarkson Potter found evidence of bribery in the Cipher dispatches. The highest voter turnout in American presidential history took place during this year, whose candidates included a man who had gained fame for breaking up the (20 pts)",
        "Canal Ring. The Republican candidate in this year was granted twenty (10 pts)",
        "disputed electoral votes and became president after he agreed to bring an end to Reconstruction. For ten points, name this election year in which Samuel Tilden won the popular vote but lost to Rutherford B. Hayes."
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1876"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man introduced the phrase “Peace at Home, Peace in the World,” which became part of his country’s foreign policy. This developer of Sun Language Theory gave the Kastamonu Speech while wearing a Panama hat. This leader, who invited John (20 pts)",
        "Dewey to reform his nation’s education system, extended voting rights to women and forced Greeks and (10 pts)",
        "Armenians to take on new last names. This leader’s reforms included abolishing the caliphate and banning the fez. Secularism was one of the Six Arrows of, for ten points, what World War I hero who served as the first President of Turkey?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk",
        "either",
        "both names"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man spent his final years as an ambassador to Britain, where he proposed a partition of Belgium at the London Conference. Earlier, this man concluded the Treaties of Luneville and Amiens to end the War of the (20 pts)",
        "Second Coalition. This man had diplomats Lucien Hauteval, Pierre Bellamy, and Jean Conrad Hottinguer informally (10 pts)",
        "demand bribes from an American delegation before they would be allowed to speak with him. The XYZ Affair involved, for ten points, what foreign minister who represented France at the Congress of Vienna?"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles-Maurice de Talleyrand-P´erigord"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man offered to duel Henry Clay after Clay struck him with a cane in retaliation for siphoning votes in the Election of 1840. Though this man suffered serious wounds at the Battle of Lundy’s Lane, he recovered and led U.S. Marines in storming (20 pts)",
        "Chapultepec castle in the Mexican-American War. This man’s most famous scheme called for the (10 pts)",
        "blockade of Southern ports after the outbreak of the Civil War. For ten points, name this general known as “Old Fuss and Feathers” who proposed the Anaconda Plan."
      ],
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Supporters of one candidate in this election year cut their hair and shaved their beards in an effort to “get clean for Gene” McCarthy, whose 42 percent in the New Hampshire primary caused the (20 pts)",
        "incumbent president to drop out. Abe Ribicoff spoke out against the “Gestapo tactics” used against protesters at this year’s (10 pts)",
        "DemocraticNationalConvention. Hubert Humphrey gained the Democratic nomination after the assassination of Robert Kennedy in, for ten points, what year in which Lyndon Johnson did not run for re-election and Richard Nixon was elected president?"
      ],
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1968"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader wrote that he would “take my first step on the road to eternity [and] leave life to enter history” before he shot himself with a revolver. The Integralists supported this leader, who created a monopoly on copper known as (20 pts)",
        "Vale. After announcing that a communist plot called the Cohen Plan sought to overthrow his government, this man threw out the Constitution of 1934 and proclaimed an (10 pts)",
        "“Estado Novo” that lasted until 1945. For ten points, name this president and dictator of Brazil."
      ],
      "answer": "Getulio Vargas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This civilization’s artwork became known to academics after Melgar Serrano carried out an excavation of Monument A. The Cascajal [cas-ca-hall] block may have been evidence of a writing system in this civilization, whose people were the (20 pts)",
        "first to practice ritual bloodletting in Mesoamerica and became known as the “rubber people” because they could extract latex from trees. (10 pts)",
        "La Venta and San Lorenzo were centers of, for ten points, what early Mesoamerican civilization that became known for building large stone heads?"
      ],
      "answer": "Olmecs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In December 1945, this man was sent on a mission to China to unify the Nationalists and Communists; his negotiations lasted over a year before failing. Joseph Stalin ordered Poland and (20 pts)",
        "Czechoslovakia to refuse aid from an initiative named for this man. In 1953, this US Army officer was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize, in large part for his work on the European (10 pts)",
        "Recovery Program after World War II. For ten points, name this American diplomat who served as Secretary of State and Defense under Harry Truman and orchestrated aid for Western Europe in a namesake plan."
      ],
      "answer": "George Marshall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After this event, one victim issued a statement claiming that the American people had to decide “Whether ours shall continue to be a government of laws and not of men.” Leon Jaworski took over the central figure’s position after this event, which occurred after a refusal of the (20 pts)",
        "Stennis Compromise. Expansion of an investigation into the activities of the Plumbers was one of the causes of this event, which was ultimately carried out by (10 pts)",
        "acting Attorney General Robert Bork. For ten points, name this event in which Archibald Cox was fired while acting as special prosecutor of the Watergate investigation."
      ],
      "answer": "Saturday Night Massacre"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author of the memoir Standing Firm was one of several Congressmen to decline Leo Ryan’s fateful invitation to investigate Jonestown. This man attacked a “poverty of values” in a reference to TV character Murphy (20 pts)",
        "Brown during a speech about the Rodney King riots. Lloyd Bentsen attacked this man as “no (10 pts)",
        "Jack Kennedy” in a vice presidential debate, and during the 1992 campaign, he was ridiculed for his misspelling of the word “potato.” For ten points, name this Indiana native who served as Vice President for George H.W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "James Danforth “Dan” Quayle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An emperor of this name employed court astrologer Michael Scotus, a translator of Averroes. After an attempt to kill a ruler with this name involving Heinrich Raspe, the town of Altavilla was sacked; that ruler was excommunicated by Gregory IX and was known as (20 pts)",
        "“stupor mundi.” Another emperor with this name convinced G´eza of Hungary to join a crusade where that emperor won at Iconium. That man, who lost the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Legnano to the Lombard League, led a crusade against Saladin before drowning in the Saleph River. For ten points, give this name shared by a Holy Roman Emperor called Barbarossa."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Frederick",
        "Frederick II and/or Frederick I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Senator Olin D. Johnston declined to attend this event, noting “criminal, fanatical, and communist elements” would attend. Prisoners were moved to different prisons before this event because police believed there would be mass arrests. Before this event, Walter Fauntroy threatened “Do you want a fight here tomorrow?” after a $16,000 (20 pts)",
        "sound system was sabotaged. Josephine Baker gave an opening address and the “Queen of Gospel,” (10 pts)",
        "Mahalia Jackson, performed at this event. A. Philip Randolph and Bayard Rustin organized, for ten points, what event calling for “Jobs and Freedom” for African-Americans, at which Martin Luther King Jr. gave the “I Have A Dream” speech?"
      ],
      "answer": "1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s supporters burned down the Dayton Journal after his arrest, which the president offered to overturn in the Birchard Letter. As a defense lawyer trying to demonstrate how how the plaintiff could have accidentally shot himself, this man (20 pts)",
        "accidentally shot himself and died the following day. This man was arrested for violating General Order 38 after giving a speech at Mount Vernon claiming that “Defeat, debt, and taxation” were the work of (10 pts)",
        "“King Lincoln.” For ten points, name this head of the Copperhead faction in the Civil War who was exiled to the Confederacy in May 1863."
      ],
      "answer": "Clement Vallandigham"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man led a battalion in a desperate attempt to break Gordon Drummond’s line during the 1814 Battle of Lundy’s Lane, where this man's leadership showed that the U.S. had a truly professional army. This general had his orders disobeyed by future (20 pts)",
        "electoral opponent Franklin Pierce during the Battle of Churubusco [[choo- roo-BOO-skoh]]. This general captured both (10 pts)",
        "Veracruz and Mexico City during the Mexican-American War and was nicknamed \"Old Fuss n' Feathers.\" For ten points, name this 1852 Whig presidential candidate, a general who formulated the Anaconda Plan."
      ],
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A work by this man begins \"Universal empire is the prerogative of a writer\" and also states that a continent will \"startle at the unhallowed foot of an invader\" even when whispering a \"delusion\" like \"Satan to Eve.\" (*) \"Tyranny, like hell, is not easily conquered,\" according to this man, who also writes, \"These are the times that try men's souls.\" In addition to The American Crisis, this man wrote a best seller and donated the proceeds to the (*) American Patriots. For ten points, name this British- American author of Common Sense."
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Paine 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This man fought the filibusters in the Gutierrez-Magee Expedition and was cited for bravery after the Battle of Medina. With Guadalupe Victoria, this man signed the Plan of Casa Mata to oppose Emperor (*) Augustine's Plan of Iguala. This man traded his highest office with the leader of the puros, Valentin Gomez Farias. James Austin Sylvester captured this man hiding in a marsh after the Battle of (*) San Jacinto. For ten points, name this twelve-time Mexican president who lost the Mexican-American War despite his victory at the Alamo."
      ],
      "answer": "Antonio López de Santa Anna"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This monument was originally proposed by Doane Robinson, who intended to build it on the Needles. This monument was intended to house a vault containing valuable U.S. documents. This monument was built on a site whose local name means (20 pts)",
        "\"Six Grandfathers,\" and the construction of this monument led to creation of the Crazy Horse Memorial in protest. This monument was made in the (10 pts)",
        "Black Hills by the sculptor Gutzon Borglum. For ten points, name this large mountain carving located in South Dakota, which depicts four U.S. presidents."
      ],
      "answer": "Mount Rushmore National Memorial"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "This event effectively ended after Paul Revere's grandson, Joseph, performed a specific action at Sonoma Barracks. This event included the Klamath Lake massacre and was led by William B. (*) Ide and \"Stuttering Zeke\" Merritt. Participants were supported by Commodore John Sloat's USS Portsmouth during this event which included the Battle of Olumpali. John (*) C. Frémont encouraged this event which included the capture of Monterey by U.S. Marines. A Grizzly bear was used as the symbol of, for ten points, what California revolt?"
      ],
      "answer": "Bear Flag Revolt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 4"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) 116 out of 156 of these things were destroyed in Operation Deadlight while most of the rest were claimed as prizes or sold. The earliest of these things was Wilhelm Bauer's Brandtaucher, and during the Battle of the (20 pts)",
        "Atlantic, Karl Dönitz [[DEHR-nitz]] developed the “wolf pack” strategy with these things. This type of vessel (10 pts)",
        "torpedoed the RMS Lusitania, turning American opinion against the Central Powers during World War One. The Germans conducted “unrestricted submarine warfare” with, for ten points, which naval vessels?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "U-Boats",
        "Unterseebooten"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man forced James Webb of NASA to investigate the existence of the \"Phillips Report\" after the Apollo 1 disaster. In a debate, this man was told by his opponent, \"I will not make age an issue of this campaign.\" Karl Rolvaag appointed this man to fill (20 pts)",
        "Hubert Humphrey's Senate seat while Humphrey was vice president. This man questioned, \"Where's the beef?\" to Gary Hart, and he chose (10 pts)",
        "Geraldine Ferraro as a running mate. Winning only D.C. and his home state of Minnesota, for ten points, who is this presidential candidate who lost to Ronald Reagan in 1984?"
      ],
      "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This decade included the Loans for Shares scheme and the Xerox Affair, in which $500,000 was found in a Xerox box. During this decade, the Taman Division's tanks shelled the White House during (20 pts)",
        "Black October. Yegor Gaider led \"shock therapy\" liberalizations in this decade, in which Dzhokhar Dudayev [[JOO-car DOO- dai-yehv]] declared (10 pts)",
        "Chechnya's [[CHETCH-nee-ahs]] Independence before Vladimir Putin crushed the insurrection. Boris Yeltsin was president of Russia in, for ten points, what decade which included the fall of the USSR?"
      ],
      "answer": "1990s"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Grand Duchess of Baden enlisted this person’s help in setting up medical facilities during the four-month siege of Paris by Prussia, and this person was awarded a Prussian Iron Cross after the Franco-Prussian War. This person innovated the use of corn (20 pts)",
        "husks to act as makeshift bandages during the Battle of Antietam. This person became known as the “Florence (10 pts)",
        "Nightingale of America” during the U.S. Civil War. For ten points, name this founder of the American Red Cross, a nurse known as the “Angel of the Battlefield.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Clara Barton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "ABA head Frank J. Hogan rebuked this man on radio who was almost indicted for sedition by Francis Biddle. Michael Gallagher's support for this man eventually forced the government to restrict his free speech rights. This man, who coined the term \"Roosevelt (*) or Ruin,\" published the far-right periodical Social Justice, which among other things, claimed there was a Jewish plot to run America. The founder of the National Shrine of the Little Flower in (*) Detroit, for ten points, who was this New Deal-era Catholic priest who supported the Axis?"
      ],
      "answer": "Father Charles Coughlin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "During this court case, Associate Justice Frank Murphy introduced the word “racism” into the Supreme Court lexicon. John Roberts specifically repudiated the decision made during this court case by the Harlan Stone-led court in the decision of the 2018 case (*) Trump v. Hawaii. This case upheld the stipulations of Executive Order 9066, created by Franklin D. Roosevelt in reaction to the (*) bombing of Pearl Harbor. For ten points, name this 1944 court case upholding Japanese internment during World War Two."
      ],
      "answer": "Korematsu v. United States 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the 2020 senate election in this U.S. state, a conspiracy theorist who claims to have invented e-mail, Shiva Ayyadurai, was defeated in the Republican primary. The kidnapping of Colin Bower's children and the police killing of DJ (20 pts)",
        "Henry became issues in this state's Democratic primary, which determined who would face Republican nominee Kevin O'Connor. A congressman from a political dynasty in this state lost the primary to incumbent Ed (10 pts)",
        "Markey. For ten points, name this state from which Markey continues to serve as senator alongside Elizabeth Warren."
      ],
      "answer": "Massachusetts"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this man’s final run for office, he defeated mayor Emory Folmar after narrowly winning the Democratic primary against Lieutenant Governor George McMillan. During one of his four runs for president, this man survived an assassination attempt which left him paralyzed (20 pts)",
        "below the waist. This man briefly served as First Gentleman after his wife, Lurleen, became (10 pts)",
        "Alabama’s first female governor. For ten points, name this long-time Alabama politician who once declared “segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George Wallace",
        "George Corley Wallace Jr."
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man helped organize Illinois’ Populist Party and ran for U.S. Congress in 1895, losing to Hugh R. Belknap. After being charged for bribery, this man switched careers from being a civil lawyer to a criminal defense (20 pts)",
        "attorney. This man presided over a case where eleven Black men, including Ossian Sweet, killed a white man, as well as a case that the Chicago Tribune dubbed “The Trial (10 pts)",
        "of the Century.” For ten points, name this prominent criminal defense attorney who defended Leopold and Loeb [[LOBE]], as well as John Scopes, in the \"Monkey Trial.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Clarence Darrow or Clarence Seward Darrow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A person in this occupation nicknamed \"Madre Conchita\" likely masterminded the assassination of former president, Alvaro Obregon [[oh-breh-GOHN]] at Bombilla [[bohm-BEE-yah]] Cafe by José de León Toral. The constructed language lingua ignota was created by Hildegard (20 pts)",
        "von Bingen, who held this occupation in the County Palatine. Martin Luther first housed and later married a noble named (10 pts)",
        "Katharina who once was in this occupation. For ten points, name this monastic profession in the Catholic church held exclusively by women."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nuns",
        "Abbess",
        "or Sisters"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While in prison for supposedly perpetrating this violent event, German- American Louis Lingg killed himself with a blast cap hidden in a cigar rather than going to trial. Men arrested during this event are labelled (20 pts)",
        "\"Mad Dogs\" in a contemporary political cartoon where they attack a personification of the U.S. after being set free by Governor John Altgeld. Albert Parsons claimed a Pinkerton agent threw the (10 pts)",
        "dynamite which began this violent labor demonstration. Agitation for the eight-hour workday led to violence in, for ten points, what Chicago riot of the late 1880s?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Haymarket Square Riot",
        "Haymarket Affair",
        "or Haymarket Massacre"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man fought in the Battle of Tecoac, where he defeated then-president Sebastián Lerdo de Tejada’s forces and forced him into exile in New York. This man appointed his confidante, Juan N. (20 pts)",
        "Méndez, as provisional president before becoming president himself for (10 pts)",
        "seven terms, filling bureaucratic positions with his allies, the cientificos. For ten points, name this general and politician who served seven terms over thirty years as President of Mexico."
      ],
      "answer": "Porfirio Díaz or José de la Cruz Porfirio Díaz Mori"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The tavern of Henry Fite served as the meeting house for this legislative body following William Howe's successful New York and New Jersey campaign. The Olive Branch (20 pts)",
        "Petition was drafted by this body. The Conway Cabal sent a letter to this governmental body meant to elevate Horatio Gates to major general by facilitating the sacking of George Washington. The Thirteen (10 pts)",
        "Colonies were governed by, for ten points, which legislative body during much of the Revolutionary War?"
      ],
      "answer": "Second Continental Congress"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's refusal to return José Rondeau [[rohn-DOH]] led to a period of civil war known as \"The Anarchy of the Year XX\" [[\"Twenty\"]]. This man's victory at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Maipú [[mah-ee-POOH]] is celebrated in one nation as \"Armor Day,\" and his forces were reinforced at that battle by militia under his successor, Bernardo O'Higgins. This man met fellow (10 pts)",
        "\"liberator\" Simón Bolívar at the Guayaquil [[wah-yah- KEEL]] Conference in 1822. For ten points, name this 19th century South American revolutionary who liberated Chile, Argentina, and Peru."
      ],
      "answer": "José de San Martín or José Francisco de San Martín y Matorras"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Following a ban on these places during the American Revolution, figures such as Hugh Henry Brackenridge and William Dunlap helped revitalize them. Supporters of William Charles Macready clashed with those of Edwin Forrest during a riot at one of these places in (20 pts)",
        "Astor Place. After a man escaped from one of these places with a broken leg, Dr. Samuel Mudd assisted in harboring him. That man, whose brother Edwin worked at these places, shouted (10 pts)",
        "\"sic semper tyrannis!\" at one of them in D.C. For ten points, name this type of location where John Wilkes Booth shot Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Theaters",
        "Playhouses"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Intervention by mayor Theodore Lyman prevented this man from being tarred, feathered, and dragged through Boston Commons. This man and Benjamin Lund faced a libel suit after he reported on the barbarity of Francis (20 pts)",
        "Todd's practices in the local slave trade, resulting in the state of Maryland fining this writer. This figure formally dissolved the American Anti-Slavery Society in 1865 after declaring their mission accomplished by the passage of the 13th (10 pts)",
        "amendment. For ten points, name this abolitionist publisher of The Liberator."
      ],
      "answer": "William Lloyd Garrison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This woman’s feud with doctors during the U.S. Civil War prompted the War Department to introduce Order No. 351 in October 1863. That order allowed this woman, in her capacity as the Superintendent of (20 pts)",
        "Army Nurses, to appoint female nurses. Prior to this woman’s appointment by the Union Army, this woman penned a bill vetoed by Franklin Pierce to set aside ten million acres to be used for the benefit of the “blind, (10 pts)",
        "deaf, and dumb.” For ten points, name this social advocate who created the first generation of U.S. mental asylums."
      ],
      "answer": "Dorothea Dix or Dorothea Lynde Dix"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This figure, who said \"When the rich think about the poor, they have poor ideas,\" replaced the Sociedad de Beneficencia with her own namesake foundation. The Montoneros (20 pts)",
        "kidnapped the body of Pedro Eugenio Aramburu in an effort to repatriate this figure's corpse back to her home nation from Spain. This first Argentinian to receive chemotherapy was initially nominated as the vice-presidential candidate for her (10 pts)",
        "spouse in the 1952 elections. For ten points, name this actress turned First Lady of Argentina during the mid 20th century known affectionally as \"Evita.\""
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Eva Perón or María Eva Duarte de Perón",
        "Evita Perón"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The primary attorney of the defendent in this case, Thomas Addis Emmet, previously served as barrister for the revolutionary Society of the United Irishmen. In this case, Attorney General William (20 pts)",
        "Wirt argued that the federal patent preemptively applied for by the plaintiff superseded any regulation from the state. Congress's right to regulate interstate (10 pts)",
        "commerce was upheld in this 19th century court case. The monopoly of Robert Fulton on New York waters was deemed unconstitutional in, for ten points, which 1824 Supreme Court case?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Gibbons v. Ogden",
        "either"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This presidential election year saw the election of the first person with non- European heritage to vice president, who was the incumbent Senate Majority Leader. In this election year, the Democrats became the first party to nominate a (20 pts)",
        "Catholic for president; that man ran alongside Joseph T. Robinson. Charles Curtis became vice president in this election year, which saw the defeat of the \"Happy Warrior,\" (10 pts)",
        "Al Smith, by the former Secretary of Commerce. For ten points, name this U.S. election year won by Republican Herbert Hoover."
      ],
      "answer": "1928 United States presidential election"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician controversially blamed the debut album of rapper Tupac Shakur, 2pocalypse Now, for directly causing brutality against the police in a 1990s case in Texas. This man faced public embarrassment after erroneously telling a school child to add an (20 pts)",
        "\"e\" to the end of word \"Potato\" during a mock spelling bee. Lloyd Bentsen said to this man \"Senator, you're no Jack Kennedy\" during the 1988 Vice Presidential debate. The running mate of George H.W. (10 pts)",
        "Bush was, for ten points, which Indiana politician?"
      ],
      "answer": "Dan Quayle or James Danforth Quayle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The principle at the center of this crisis was promoted by James Hamilton Jr. and William C. Preston, both representing the same state. The Force Bill was passed to allow the president to resolve this crisis with violence, though it was symbolically (20 pts)",
        "blocked by one side after a peaceful resolution was reached. A state ordinance declared the Tariffs of 1828 and 1832 unconstitutional, sparking this crisis, which was supported in the essay (10 pts)",
        "\"South Carolina Exposition and Protest\" by sitting-vice president John C. Calhoun. For ten points, name this constitutional crisis during the Andrew Jackson administration in which states attempted to block federal law."
      ],
      "answer": "Nullification Crisis"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician successfully tacked several progressive points to the Republican platform in the Election of 1960 by striking the \"Treaty of Fifth Avenue\" with Richard Nixon. This man died of a heart attack in the company of Megan Marshack, who mysteriously called a reporter before dialing 911, leading to theories of an affair. This politician ordered the National Guard to quash the (20 pts)",
        "Attica Prison Riot while serving as Governor of New York. This man later became vice president under another man who became president by rule of the (10 pts)",
        "Twenty-Fifth Amendment. For ten points, name this New York politician and vice president under Gerald Ford."
      ],
      "answer": "Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "Due to encouragement from Gloria Steinem, this figure ran in the Democratic primary for the Mayor of New York City using the slogan \"throw the rascals in.\" This author controversially compared American \"Hipsters\" to the African-American populace in the essay (*) \"The White Negro.\" This man's experiences as a cook in World War Two inspired his tale of a platoon of U.S. soldiers fighting on the fictional Anopopei [[ah-noh-POH-pay]] during the Pacific campaign. The Naked and the (*) Dead was written by, for ten points, which New Journalist and best-selling twentieth century American author?"
      ],
      "answer": "Norman Mailer or Norman Kingsley Mailer"
    }
  ]
}